to prove that the number of scheme
in your problem-set I'm going to ask you
programs is countable and I'll tell you
the hint for that every one of your
scheme programs has a certain number of
characters in it right so we can list
all the scheme programs by by how many
characters they have all the scheme
programs with one character all the
scheme programs with two characters all
the scheme programs with three
characters right so I'm have making a
list so what about the programs say that
have 100 characters how should i order
them am I going to do it alphabetically
or something I mean it's not so hard to
order programs you make a list of them
you make a function that goes down from
1 to infinity but what about the things
that programs want to do what about
functions of programs want to compute
that's a lot harder so what I want to
convince you of is that there are more
things to compute than there are
programs to compute them and the idea
here is an idea to call diagonalization
it was in one of the main things that
Kanter use to prove that the real
numbers are not countable and it's going
to come up in in this example and I'll
do it real briefly just to give you a
sense of it you'll see it again in
recitation as I just mentioned you can
count all the scheme programs you can
number them this one's number one this
one's number two this one's number three
right in order and I'm going to number
them down here programs ok over here I'm
just going to list the numbers 1 2 3 4 5
Sacre and I'm going to fill in this
chart in the following way this program
number 1 that we call program number 1
can work on any input that we put in we
can put in the number 1 as input we can
put in the number 2 as input in fact
let's think of these numbers as
representing programs again so we're
putting in programs to this program you
have a scheme function and you type in a
program to it as input when it says you
know please type in your input you type
in program number one and your scheme
function is going to either say yes or
no it's either going to stop and say yes
I like this program or no I don't like
this program so these are all the
programs that just end up say
yes or no they don't do anything clever
except saying yes or no to an input so
let's put in some values say it says no
to this yes to this noted that yes to
this no no no etc and I can fill in this
chart with zeros and ones now if there's
something a little fishy with what I'm
saying can I really fill in this chart
why not okay it goes on forever that's
true but I could at least describe
filling it in is it even worse than that
what if I got up to this spot right here
program number six I put in program
number one and I wait to see whether it
says yes or no and I wait and I wait and
I wait a little more and July and Adu is
over and I go check on how you're all
doing ten years later down the road and
everybody's doing fine happily married
with lots of kids making lots of money
and doing their dream and everybody's
just completely content and I say hey by
the way that program number six is still
running on an input number one I'm still
not sure if it says yes or no all right
then we're all dead and ten generations
down and it's the earth gets destroyed
if there's new civilization they find my
little program running on a microchip
that's sitting there and it's still
running and running and this runs
forever and ever and ever how do I know
it's ever going to stop we got I wait
long enough right it might never stop so
it's possible that one of these things
you know I might not be able to fill in
but for the purposes of this argument
let's just say that look if it accepts
it I'll put a one in and if it doesn't
there's a zero and I might not know that
but here's what I could do to
conceivably fill in this chart I could
run each one of these programs for one
step and then I could run the second one
for two steps and then run the first one
for an additional step then I'll start
the third one I'll run this for one step
then I'll run this for another step
another just for another step I could
run them all at the same time adding one
step each time so that sooner or later
if the thing had a one in there I could
fill in it in other words I wouldn't get
stuck at one program waiting and waiting
and not be able to fill in the rest of
the table I would do one step of this
program and then add an extra step to
all the others I had done and then start
with the next one
so that's sooner or later if it's going
to stop and say yes I'll be able to put
a 1 and if it's going to run forever
it'll never put anything in there but I
won't have to worry about us getting
stuck along the way so I'm gonna
understand that trick that's sometimes
sometimes called dovetailing it's it's a
trick to get all these things to run at
the same time so I could convince you
that conceivably I'll put all the ones
in at some point all right so you're
saying the program sits in position 7
say program 6 on input one has an
infinite loop and I don't want it to get
stuck there because then I couldn't
convince you that I can so here's what I
do I run program one for one step on
this input ok and then I run program I
then I run program two for this one then
I one program three for this one and
every step along I add one step for each
of these programs what happens when I do
one step of that program and then I do
one more step for each of these on all
of these inputs and then I continue with
program seven right I leave it as a
question mark right and these things
eventually get fill in when we when we
need to fold omit all right I don't want
to spend too much time this is actually
a subject in theory of computation but I
wanted you to see this one idea of
diagonalization now let's say I've done
this I now have this big chart filled in
okay I have all these programs listed
here every single program in the whole
world listed here ok I have all the
inputs listed here and I have look at
these things a particular row here
represents a computation it represents a
list of programs that this program
accepts and a list that it doesn't
accept in particular elicited accepts I
want to convince you that there is a
list of acceptance that isn't in this
table in other words there's a
computation like this
that none of my programs are doing okay
each one of these infinite sequences of
zeros and ones represents a computation
represents something that you might want
to write a program to do I'm going to
convince you that after you've listed
all your programs down and I filled in
this chart there is a particular
computation a sequence of zeros and ones
accepting or rejecting these inputs that
doesn't exist in this table all my
programs are unique yeah but even if
they weren't it would be okay I mean I
could have two that have the same
computation I'm going to convince you
there's a new one that's different from
all the ones in my list right I don't
think I need to say that these are
unique it even if they're the same it's
okay I think so here's what I'm going to
do I'm going to go down I'm going to go
down this diagonal that's why it's
called diagonalization and I'm going to
create a new set of zeros and ones and
I'm going to convince you that that set
of zeros and ones doesn't exist in my
table anyplace that means there's a
computation and none of my programs
compute it that means it's a program
that's missing from my list in other
words as a computation and there's no
program that that does it here's how I'm
going to do it every place I see a zero
I change it to a one every place I see a
one I change it to a zero zeros are
question marks change to change to ones
ones changed to zeros you have there's
they're scattered question marks right
yeah I think we'll have to turn question
marks into ones zeros and question marks
will turn into ones and ones will turn
into zero is there yeah announced that a
question mark is a
back the other way right it's true yeah
I'm trying to I'm trying to avoid
technicalities and I'm getting more
technicalities all right I can't fix
that easily without changing the way I
want to do this so let's say no question
marks yeah let's say no question what's
that let's say these are all say zeros
and ones it's not so realistic but at
least we'll get the notion if I go down
this diagonal and I change the zeros to
ones and the ones to zeros then I get a
new list of ones and zeros and that new
list here let's write it in it's one
zero zero zero and then it would keep
going this list is different from this
one it's different from this one it's
different from this one it's different
from all the ones in this long infinite
list of programs that means yeah I guess
you know you don't need to really but
you could see in other words it's a list
of zeros and ones it isn't in there yet
which means that there's some
computation that exists and there's no
program that does it yeah because this
values got to be different than every
one of the ones that's already they're
different than the ones in the diagonal
what about 129 in row 29 it'll differ
from the 29th row in the 29th spot okay
it'll differ from row 152 and 150 second
spot right right so it's going to be
different from all the other
computations that's there and therefore
there's a program that that doesn't
exist anyway I the main idea I want you
to get here you'll see this in more
detail in a more rigorous way next in
recitation but what I want you to get
the sense is that this idea of
diagonalization does connect back to
programs and it's not just a completely
abstract idea
and you'll see it again in more detail
and theory of computation the conclusion
is that there are things that you want
to compute that there are no programs
for that if you try to list all the
programs and you think you have them all
listed and numbered from one down to
infinity that there's some computation
that could be defined and there's no
program that connects to that
computation that there are more things
to compute than there are programs
that's a good way of putting it but yet
the order of infinity is there's more
computable functions than there are that
then there are integers then there are
programs there's more things to compute
than there are programs such as a
program which for example multiplies any
input by two yeah I include anything
like that right oh you mean things that
don't just say yes or no you mean what
do you mean yeah here was we're talking
programs that do very simple things
programs that take an input and tell you
yes or no on the input but that's an
even smaller set than programs in
general and we still do the same thing
you just change right you can make a
program without put turn into something
with yes or no you could do them all
right I should say I promised at the
beginning that I would try to do lecture
notes for all these things and I do have
new lecture notes that I printed out and
you can look up these things and and
hopefully I will keep up to date here if
I have time to always give you guys
stuff unit if the scribble while I talk
again and again maybe the most common
thing you'll see for the rest of the
semesters you'll see it in Java you'll
see in an algorithm this is a topic that
talks about how to measure how fast
functions are growing and it's
fundamental and algorithms in the very
very early days of algorithms somebody
would come up with an algorithm to do
something they'd publish a paper they do
some experiments they print the results
kind of like like in a laboratory
setting they'd say I ran it on this
computer on this kind of input and
here's how many milliseconds it took and
it's hard to make a comparison between
that and somebody else's paper if they
ran it on a different machine or they
had a different compiler they had a
different implementation where they use
a different programming language so soon
after that the theory kind of came up to
to give a solid foundation and we
compare algorithms not by just
experimenting and looking at the actual
number of milliseconds but by somehow
looking at the algorithm itself and
saying this takes a certain amount of
time independent of the underlying
implementation and we compare algorithms
based on that criterion and that's what
this theory is all about it's about
trying to get a metric for how fast
functions are growing and those
functions are typically coming from how
long a particular algorithm is taking
sorting program called bubble sort for a
second we're going to calculate how many
steps this takes here's how the program
works you put a bunch of numbers up like
this in a list and you compare the first
two things in a list and if the you'd
like to make this an ascending order
from smallest to highest so if the first
one is bigger then the second one you
want to switch their locations okay so
in this case that becomes six and then
eight and then you continue going down
to the next pair eight and two so you
get two eight eight and ten ten and five
five ten that's called one bubble
procedure it doesn't sort the list yet
what do we have to do to sort the list
right we have to do it again
so if we did it again what would happen
to six five
I'm going to do the whole thing a ten
okay and then we have to do it one more
time it looks like two five six eight
ten all right
let's analyze how much time this takes
how many steps does this first bubble
procedure take let's say comparing are
the things we're counting up how many
comparisons one comparison here one here
one here one here if there's n numbers
then it's n minus one how much as a next
one take in the worst case and minus two
how come only n minus 2 not n minus 1
because this 10 what do you know about
it it's definitely the biggest number
when you're finished with a bubble
procedure you can prove that the biggest
number is sitting at the bottom and the
other numbers bubble so to speak upwards
in some less predictable way but the
heaviest one sinks to the bottom
therefore when you go next time you
never have to compare this one to this
one anymore that's a wasted comparison
so on the way down here we
do at most n minus 2 comparisons and
where's this going this is the triangle
numbers again right why did I spend so
much time in them because they come up
all the time from algorithms as well
this is an algorithm that takes time
proportional to 1 plus 2 plus 3 all the
way up to n minus 1 which you know
equals n times divided by 2 all right
that's the complexity of this algorithm
of this bubble sort algorithm it's not
too hard to analyze this algorithm but
now we want to get a sense of of what
the overall time complexity of this
algorithm is we like to give it some
kind of categorical value in this case
the categorical value is going to be
this is about N squared the about N
squared is the part that I'm going to
formulate and formalize in these
definitions that are coming up all right
are there questions about this so far
right this is worst case right right
although if we did the time for
flip-flopping it would double this and
the idea of this formalization it's a
good question Doug is that doubling or
quadrupling or any constant change won't
affect our category of this algorithm
and to be in the same category okay
questions about this yeah crazy number
of run the number of sorts required
actually have to do well since every
time we do one the correct number sinks
to the bottom
1 2 3 4 n minus 1 right sometimes it
gets done earlier and you can put a flag
in and say stop if the last one didn't
change anything that's right that's
right all right other questions ok
here's a very very dull definition but
we'll do some examples and bring some
life to it we say that a function is Big
O another function if and only if there
exists a C and some number such that
you don't have to write it down just
look at it and then we'll think about it
what it means in reality f of X is Big O
of G of X we say that one function is
bounded above by another this function
is is this function G is an upper bound
for X bounce it on top if basically
there's some constant some fixed number
times the G which is always bigger than
the app as long as you're past a certain
point as long as you're past
X sub 0 now this is completely obscure
if you see it for the first time so let
me give you an example from what we just
did here's a function here's our f
function f of n equals N squared over 2
minus n over 2 and I want to convince
you that this function that f of n is
order N squared
that is bounded above by N squared
according to the definition the way to
do this is you have to find a constant
so that the function you're interested
in is smaller than that constant times N
squared you want to show that N squared
over 2 minus n over 2 is smaller than or
equal to some constant times N squared
what constant can I use to get this tour
1 right this is always less than N
squared because this is half an squared
of this takes away things from it so
it's completely straightforward that
this function is order N squared because
1 times N squared is bigger than this
for every single and in the whole world
and bigger than 0 so the x0 here would
be 0 anything bigger than 0 and the C
would be 1 if you want to go through
these definitions and show that
something is order something else you
have to find the C and find the x x0 we
got an upper bound here so we could say
this yeah when did we do theater
notation well you did this this thing
already all right so all right so here's
the next step alright so I'm going to
zoom along they're all thinking I was
just getting it don't zoom along all
right whether you got this last month or
not I know how much they did on this but
this is an upper bound the very very
same definition looks like this but this
is reversed so that means Omega is a
lower bound it means it's at least as
big and if it's both this and this we
say it's big theta that's what it really
means to be in the category that it's
bounded above by N squared and it's
bounded below by N squared if it's both
of these we'd say it's big theta so let
me convince you now that this one is not
only big all N squared but it's also
Omega N squared
show you that this is Omega N squared I
have to show you that this function is
bigger than something times N squared
for all and past a certain point well
it's not going to be bigger than one
times N squared because it was less than
one times N squared so to show that it's
bigger than something times n squared
you better use a smaller number than one
so what number is going to work there
do you know one seventeenth work besides
if you're a seventeen lover what number
really works
that's that's easy to see a third just a
half work it doesn't right because a
half N squared is going to be bigger
than a half n squared minus something so
Sam just says well let's take something
that's smaller than that is this true
can you figure out whether this is true
or not and how would you figure it out
we're only worried with large and we're
worried to make sure this is true as
soon as n is bigger than a certain
number and you can tell me what that
number is that's the x zero as long as
it's going to be true past a certain
point this is okay what can't be zero
the constant the constant can't be zero
the constant has to be bigger than zero
yeah right that's true
these definitions we always use a
positive constant yeah yeah all right so
how do you how do you figure out what n
work is going to work here you can do
some algebra here right you could go
ahead and manipulate this around until
you had something and greater than or
equal to a number should we do it let's
do once okay so how do we manipulate
this to figure out this is true for all
N greater than something all right so I
get okay everyone see what I did we
subtracted 1/3 N squared and 1/2 n
squared minus 1/3 and squared is 1/6 N
squared
equal to three this is all going to be
true you can always find that number
that it's going to be true past that by
manipulating this algebraically once you
guess a constant that actually works and
depending on the constant you guess this
number may be bigger or smaller and you
can calculate it they come in pairs the
constant and the value after which it
starts being bigger than okay just a
little review before we state this
general theorem Sam just set who wants
to try this
it uh okay we're trying to show that
this is order N squared we want to show
that N squared over two plus 3n over 2
is smaller than or equal to something
times N squared what should that
something be okay let's figure it out
I know it's I know that N squared is
bigger than N squared over two right is
N squared bigger than three n over two
of this is N squared that means it's
like 3n squared so I 3n squared is
bigger than 3n over 2 right everyone
believes that so why don't I do this
why don't I use three unsquare to handle
this and squared to handle this it gives
me four N squared this is definitely
bigger than these two because one of the
n squares handles this one and one of
the n squares handled and three of the n
squares handle this one right makes
sense all right so this therefore is
order N squared and you can do a similar
thing for the Omega case it's even
easier in the Omega case here
all right don't go out of your way to
look for a smaller one this is bigger
than what times N squared agreed in this
case the Omega was the easier part here
the Big O was the easier part the point
is these definitions are formalizing the
idea that we don't care about the
constants we care about what happens
after the numbers and get very very
large we don't care about the two or the
divided by two or the three and this is
a formal way of saying that we don't
care about that okay let's do a so do we
need to state with the for N greater
than whatever in this case it's true for
all N so the greater than whatever is
just going to be zero this is true for
every N in the whole world and a lot of
times you can do it where that past a
certain point is just past zero close it
up to zero so you can say n bigger than
one it's certainly true for n bigger
than one okay I'm going to do one more
what I think is a straightforward
example then I want to do a harder
example to show you how much
manipulation you might need in order to
do these things so let's do this
question this is what Sam was talking
about a second ago here's a polynomial
have a polynomial and you'll want to
know what the order of it is what the
complexity of it is just go to the part
that has the biggest exponent ignore the
constant in front of it and that's what
it is so this should be big theta and to
the fourth and that's true and you can
prove this theorem all right so let's
just see why and how the proof goes we
won't prove it but I'll give you the
intuition same as we did before this is
going to be smaller than or equal to 2 n
to the fourth another 5 n to the fourth
another 1 n to the fourth
welcome to another end to the fourth so
how many does that make altogether one
to seven it's small or equal to nine n
to the fourth you can always go ahead
and dominate these terms by this major
term all right right yeah greater than
equal to one at least yeah two went to
the fourths here five into the fourths
here one n to the fourth here and went
into the fourth here you don't really
need to put one in for this it's just
overkill but you could do that and then
it would be true for for everything
right you can make it 16 not quite 17 we
might as well make it 17 all right let
me ask you a question is 2 to the N big
theta is 2 to the n plus 1 here are the
two parts that means 2 to the N is
bigger than or equal to some constant
times 2 to the n plus 1 and 2 to the N
is smaller or equal to some other
constant times 2 to the n plus 1 ok well
go and you can't make you're making an
argument on the intuition from the
theorem so go back to the actual theorem
what should the sea be to make this true
you're saying the right thing but is
there a sea that makes this true 1/2
these are strictly equal when C equals
1/2 right here this is true when C
equals 1 1 so here you use 1/2 here you
use 1 so they are big theta of each
other
right baby how about this it's 2 to the
2n let's just do Big Oil it's 2 to the 2
I'm Big O 2 to the M it's 2 to the 2 on
smaller than some constant times 2 to
the N how do you figure this out ok
let's try that idea if you divide this
by 2 to the N what do you get 2 to the 2
n divided by 2 to the N you subtract the
exponents you get 2 to the N so it's 2
to the N less than or equal to a
constant for any constant in the whole
world
well after you get past a certain point
this will also be be bigger than any
constant so you're dead here this is not
order 2 to the N definitely not Big O 2
to the N okay because no matter how big
a constant you pick this will eventually
be larger than that constant right a
two functions because of this trick you
do you see how we divided there a good
fast way is to take the functions and
divide one by the other so for example
N and N squared remember a problem set
on this which one of these is bigger
than the other for what n remember you
prove that well there's a reason if you
could prove something like this then
what do you know about N squared N
squared is less than or equal to 2 to
the N for all n bigger than 5 that means
that N squared is order 2 to the N well
that's not so interesting but actually
it's strictly less than right why don't
you put it in greater than 5 on the rub
side you can may get rid of the for no
reason typo this strictly less that if
you can get something strictly less than
then instead of saying Big O we
sometimes say small oh and that means
it's not only bounded above but it's
bounded strictly above that it's really
smaller than that it has no chance of
ever being the same it's the same exact
definition except without the equal sign
on the unless and just strictly less
that so it means it's it's a it's a real
real upper bound that you'll never ever
reach that you're definitely less than
shouldn't be if you switch this around
if you try to show the 2 to the N is
order N squared you won't be able to do
it 2 to the N less than or equal to some
constant times N squared one way to show
that you never can do this is to divide
both sides so it's like we did before
and then we have to show the 2 to the N
over N squared is smaller than or equal
to a constant C for all and past a
certain point one way to do this is to
take the limit of this as n goes to
infinity put in very large numbers
if this limit gets bigger than a
constant then you can never do it then
you won't get a Big O there but if the
limit equals a constant then you can use
that constant here so this limit goes to
infinity and you can go back to calculus
and use all the tricks you can possibly
think of to figure out limits in
comparing one function to another take
the function divide it by the other
figure out its limit as you go to
infinity that's a sure way of comparing
one to the other whether one is Big O of
the other and you can use all the
powerful theorems of calculus gives you
about limits okay questions about that
infinity over infinity deal with that by
taking the derivative yeah I'm not sure
did you guys learn how to take limits of
things that turn out infinity over
infinity maybe not but I'll tell you a
theorem that's I'll tell you the only
theorem that's particularly useful here
that if you get a limit where when you
plug in infinity you get kind of
infinity on top and infinity on the
bottom then there's a more or less
there's a theorem that says take the
derivative at the top and the derivative
of the bottom and redo the limit and if
that ends up being straight nfinity then
this one's straight infinity if that
ends up being having a real limit then
this one has a real limit the thing
about taking derivatives that it makes
it simpler the derivative of this is
approximately two to the end it's 0.7
times 2 to the N more or less and the
derivative of this is 2i then you can do
the derivatives again the derivative of
this would be 0.7 point seven two to the
N that's the second derivative the
second derivative of this is two so that
limit goes to infinity therefore the
original limit goes to infinity that
rule is called l'hopital's rule I'm not
sure l'hopital discovered it but it's
called his rule one of the first things
you do in an algorithms class is talk
about sorting and when you do sorting
you talk about actual algorithms for
sorting like we just did where the
triangle numbers come back in but
another thing you do about sorting is
you wonder hey what's the minimum amount
of time it's going to take me to sort
things I know I can sort things in N
squared I just showed you that
what's the minimum amount of time okay
what am I trying to beat while you're
trying to beat N squared but how much
better can you do can you get down to n
well you can prove that if you're using
comparisons to sort we won't do the
proof here but you can prove it in
algorithms that it takes at least big
theta n log n to sort numbers counting
the comparisons you can't get down can't
do better right it's very rare that you
can prove an optimum thing like this for
an algorithm you can always get an upper
bound on the time for an algorithm by
exhibiting an algorithm but to say an
algorithm needs to take this amount of
time you really need a clever argument
and this is a very clever argument it
uses binary trees and it proves that the
minimum number of steps to sort requires
n log n that's assuming you don't know
anything about the numbers that there's
no restrictions if you restrict the
numbers you can actually do a little
better but if you don't restrict
anything about the numbers n log n is
the best you can do now where does this
come from what really comes out of this
proof is this that you need this many
steps the log of n factorial that's what
really comes out of the proof and then
there's a whole big stage where we take
the log of n factorial and you convinced
the class that that's really the same as
big theta n log n this comes up much
more often in algorithms that you'll see
it in other places because logarithms
come from trees and n factorials come
from permutation so it's basically a
binary tree of permutations and that's
where that comes from but I want to
convince you and here's the main thing
I'm doing now why this is the same as
this why log of n factorial is the same
as order n log N and we're going to work
with the definition and we're going to
work with some algebra and you'll see
how mildly hairy some of these proofs
can get ok other questions so far yeah
Tony
depending on what numbers you have the
actual execution of it particular
instance could happen in last time yes
yes we're talking about the overall
algorithm time which means the worst
case yeah right right I mean a
particular instance where say the
numbers happen to be sorted and your
algorithm just looks at them quickly and
checks and that would be done in linear
time in order n time but but that
doesn't solve the problem that just gets
lucky right right right
about your hundred percent right all
right so let's get back to this how do
we show that this is going to be big
theta n log n yeah oh because okay I'll
leave it as a log in factorial and I
want to know where this compares to N
squared N and two to the N and n log n
these are kind of the stars in our
universe these are the things that come
up a lot and you come up with this and
if you don't know how it compares to
these things then it's just like a
shooting star out of nowhere so the
reason we want to go back to here is
because we know where it fits in we know
that it fits in in between N and N
squared in a nice place called n log n
that's a good question it's just a log n
factorial too some people might not give
them a sense maybe you'd think this is
exponential or something or who knows
okay that's a good question
other questions all right let's go ahead
and do this let's try to analyze log of
n factorial we want to show number one
that it's less than or equal to some
constant n log N and then we're going to
have to show that it's bigger than some
other constant n log n this will be the
big ol part this will be the big Omega
part alright so this is going to be a
lot of algebra and some math and stick
with me here because there's one clever
idea let's do the first part because
it's easier what constant could we use
here and how could we get any handle on
this at all Sam says it's one we believe
Sam right
good rays log dig into the log end to
the end alright you can do that ah I see
what you're thinking that's a good idea
that's a good idea that's a good idea
say that log n factorial is less than or
equal to log n to the N everyone agree
to that because this is just n times n
minus 1 times n minus 2 and this is n
times n times n times n times n so here
all the terms each one is bigger than
each of the terms here so I agree that
this is definitely bigger than this
because n to the N is bigger than n
factorial and if you remember your log
rules this equals exactly and log n so
log on factorial is less than or equal
to n log n so I could use the constant 1
and seems right and Michael's got a good
way to look at it so let's go with your
way I wanted to do it a little bit of a
different way because it leads to the
next problem which is much harder the
way I wanted to try to show you how to
do it is let's use the other rules for
logs and yeah go remember back month 0
now how do you do logs let's expand this
a little bit what's the log of n
factorial
run the lock through it you add all the
log values together plus log of 2 plus
log of 1 all right there it is that's
log n factorial we want to show that
this is bigger than or equal to some
constant times n log n you got to pick a
constant to make that work oh sorry
would you I don't think so if you
combine all these terms it becomes log n
factorial right goodbye yeah I'm good
except for the log n except for this
yeah thought up we can divide both sides
by log in we're going to have 1 plus
we'll get log of n minus 1 factorial
divided by n or something like that
maybe log of n minus 1 factorial
it would be equal to your the signs I
know in you're dividing by log n that's
a lot of trouble it's a lot of trouble
because the you get log n minus 1
divided by log n log n minus 2 divided
by those guys back together so you get
log n minus 1 factorial so you get 1
plus log n minus 1 factorial is is
greater than or equal to C 1 times n
times 1 right but you get log n minus 1
factorial over log n that's kind of ugly
well combined you divide log n factorial
by log of n you just get the factorial
they all cancel out except the
exclamation point
well let's get back to this question
what is what should this C be is one
going to work one works for less than or
equals so it's unlikely one's going to
work for greater than or equal you want
a number bigger than 1 or smaller than
one here smaller than one because you
need it to be bigger than than this
value how much smaller than one do you
need its look you can just guess you
can't pick 0 that's not that's not
allowed
you got to pick something which is
bigger than 0 so you could pick I don't
know you could pick a tenth you could
pick a hundredth but it's just it's just
a stab in the dark let's get something
that we think is going to work and yes
one seventeenth is nice let's see if we
can get a half to work but why would we
expect I have to work why would you ever
think anything's going to work here
maybe it's not true I mean why do you
think this is true why is it going to
work you want to cut this in half soon
all right the reason what I'm hoping you
look at here is is an idea that you've
seen before and you seen it when the
triangle numbers what was one way to add
up the triangle numbers first in the
last second and the second to last you
got no guarantee that's going to work
here but at least it's something to try
okay one of the things you're trying to
get in discrete math is a big bag of
tricks
you came in with hardly any tricks and
you want to leave with a lot of tricks
and you want to be able to do two things
when you pull out a trick you want to be
able to recognize it and know what to do
with it so it's not like oh this is
pneumatic double hammer I don't know how
to use this better put that bad right
you want to be able to use all the tools
in your basket but you know what makes
you really good what makes you really
good is you see this big complicated
machine you say oh I know the tool
that's going to open that machine and
you go right in and you grab it that's
the hard part
but minimally what you should expect to
get is I know every tool in my chest
that I know which ones more or less are
helpful so here let's try this tool
whether it works or not
before we guess the constant so here's
what we do we have log 1 plus log n log
n minus 1
this is a good way to pair them plus log
to set all right well we can try what's
the middle term I'm going to look like
more or less more or less like this we
just chopped the thing in half this is
what Sam suggested because he has good
intuition about these things he's done a
million of these things and he's got a
great bag of tricks so he had a census
would work in it maybe he was going to
work but let's look at it we've got
these things all paired up we've got
half as many pairs here as we had terms
up here and each one comes into log one
log n log N minus 1 log 2 and the middle
terms are log n over 2 log n over 2
2 3 all the way up to N so the middle
term is going to be halfway and over to
the question right what if there's an
odd number of terms and these two will
differ by one so you know what I should
say fudging here a little you're right
yet I mean I should really be very
careful about this if it's an odd number
of terms this misses a little but it
actually won't affect our argument so it
won't hurt that's the right way to write
it this rep you round up your round down
that that's actually right but you try
to do an analysis with this and the
analysis becomes harder and kind of
obscures your main idea but then if you
want to be very precise round up here
and round down here that I think works
fine but don't get let that go don't get
involved with the details work the
details out later if you get the main
idea first how do we we're still not
even up to the constant part we're not
even close what's going on here log 1
plus log in is log in log 2 plus
this is log n times log 1 so that's log
n this is log 2 times n minus 1 this is
log 3 n minus 3 and the last one is log
2 the minus 2
thank you and the last one is log dot
dot and over to more or less than over
to okay so now we've got it written like
that how many terms are here altogether
and over two terms right half as many
terms that we have before that's a clue
that we should try to put a 1/2 here
right that's a clue but where do we go
next
we got log in here right we got log of
something here it's don't know if it's
bigger than log n are smaller than log n
minus K times K over 2 okay we can do
something a little that's true but but
we can do something a little bit we can
avoid even if you didn't know that what
if you didn't have that in your bag of
tricks this is bigger than 1/2
n
why let's do this piece by piece how do
you know this part is bigger than log n
over 2 because it's n over 2 times
something right how do you know this
one's bigger than log n over 2 because
one of these two either 2 or n minus 1
is bigger than log n over 2 right you
have 2 times n minus 1 one of them is
going to be bigger than half of n 3 of n
minus 2 one of them is going to be
bigger than half of it so every one of
these terms this one this one this one
every single one of them is bigger than
log n over 2 so everyone agree with it
too many confused faces let me say it
again because this is an easy idea if
you just think about it for a second
what's going on here I got these numbers
going from 1 to N and these numbers
going down from n minus 1 so 2 times n
minus 1 one of those numbers is bigger
than half of n right so this is log 2
plus log n minus 1 right this one alone
is bigger than log n over 2 this one
alone is bigger than log n over 2 that
one alone is bigger than log n over 2
the best way right yeah question
add two logs together then it's the log
of their product but but a but following
on that line I mean we did this because
someone suggested it but now maybe we
didn't need to do it look back here each
of these pieces is something that adds
up almost to N right so one of these two
either the tour the N minus one is
bigger than half of it here it's n + 1
this one's bigger than half here it's n
minus 2 and 3 one of them is going to be
bigger than half of n so each pair of
these each pair is bigger than log of n
over 2 and how many pairs are there
there's n over 2 pairs yes and what do
you want to say can you give me a minute
on the board to show it much more
clearly
have you can have 5 minutes and show it
more clearly
alright so here's what we're up to we
have this original log n factorial it
reduces down here and now I know it's
bigger than 1/2 n log n over 2 are we
done
almost we have to write lug of n over 2
two so if I multiply this out I get and
over to log n minus and over to log 2
and over 2 log 2 log 2 is just the
constant it's it's 1 log base 2 of 2 is
1 so these two are the same so I've
gotten the number 1/2 I've shown that my
sum is bigger than n over 2 log n but
it's bigger than n over 2 log n minus n
over 2 and I don't want that minus n
over 2 in there I got to get that out of
there so there's one extra little step a
little fudge step I have to do here and
here's what I do I note that this part
here with a negative is actually bigger
or equal to n over 4 log n as long as n
is past a certain number as long as n is
bigger than 4 you could check this part
yourself by doing the algebra so what
constant actually works in the end the
constant that works is 1/4 as long as n
is bigger than 4 and you might be able
to get away with a half as long as n is
past something but I didn't bother
trying to calculate what that past spot
should be so instead I just change it to
here where the algebra is easier to do
and I rushed through that at the end but
the upshot of this is that log n
factorial is big theta n log n the upper
bound Big O part is easy to do the gamma
part is much harder to do it requires a
lot of algebraic manipulation Sam's
going to show you an easier way in a
second it ends up being bigger than n
over 2 log n minus n over 2 which is
bigger than or equal to n over 4 log n
so the C is 1/4 and the and 0 is 4 or
the x0 is 4 dinah question
I meant Omega is no gamma Alpha Delta I
was thinking of a fret Teresa I did this
quickly to a log of n divided by two is
the log of n minus the log of two okay
so it's a half n log n that's this minus
1/2 n log 2 log 2 is just 1 log base 2
of 2 is 1 so that's minus 1/2 n that's a
good question tree so I really went
through that way too fast
but that's true and that's just that
stupid minus 1/2 so we make the constant
a little smaller to handle that in this
particular case it actually is a binary
tree and it really is log base 2 in
order to do that if we didn't happen to
know it was log base 2 then at this
point it would be n over 2 times some
constant right all logs are a constant
factor multiplied by other logs so if it
wasn't if it was base 10 then I just
have it a little number there not n over
2 times some other number and it
wouldn't affect thee in the details too
much are there other questions
all right so Sam will give you five
minutes right now yeah by real quick
yeah what they see on the bone you have
log and the log n minus 1 plus blood 1
all this yeah side on the other side you
have log in plus log n plus log in again
now divided by 2
you know but we're trying to show is
that that this is good larger greater
than log n right greater than some
constant times n log n so I'm going to
use 1/2 for that constant it's not
bigger than n log n itself that's true
it's bigger than half of it though it's
bigger than some constant fraction of it
the constant that I ended up using here
is 1/2 C okay constant would do it for
every N larger than it doesn't that's
true oh you wouldn't believe that yeah
okay but it's okay so so before Sam does
five minutes I'll just say there is
getting my little story about believe it
there is I was in that I don't know
tenth grade or something and there was a
kid in my class named Bodnar Amos Bodnar
and math was a little challenging for
Amos and he studied his head off for
this New York I don't know some standard
exam that you had to take and you had to
pass this to get on to the next class
and he was one of these nervous kind of
people that was always worrying about it
he would study hours and hours it was
just horrible to watch him suffer this
way and he was ready and ready and he
wasn't the most likable kid either she
didn't really feel so sorry for me and
and he would work and work and work and
work
it's a he wasn't a happy kid so anyway
he took this he took this I wonder where
he is today
Oh
have been changed to protect the same
anyway oh gee can not so I'm so he took
this test and and the teachers you know
calling out the grades and the teacher
said well everyone has a choice I will
say your grade out loud or you can come
up and look at it here alright so
everybody you know comes to them and
make a decision you're not loud or not
you know and whatever so it finally gets
to him and he sits there squirming in a
seat oh I don't know if you should say
that loud oh maybe you should and he
goes back up everybody in the classes go
just finally he says talented me out
loud and the teacher with a completely
straight face
you needed a 65 to pass the teacher
reads his grade and says Bodnar 64 and
stares at him like this everybody
thought he was joking you know because
he's a funny guy the teacher and he
could conceivably have done this so
Bodnar goes you're kidding
I don't believe it I don't believe it
he's freaking out saying I don't believe
it I don't believe it and the teachers
not cracking a smile yet so we're
thinking oh my god it's like completely
like not a joke so the teacher goes he
goes is it really true and he was 64
binder so at this point he's like
virtually in tears and he's freaking out
and he says I don't believe in and he
doesn't shut up and he keeps over and
over again I don't believe it I don't
believe it I don't believe it
so finally the teacher never cracking
another face except his little pursed
lips telling him 64 looks at him and
says well believe it Bodnar and that was
the end of the story so anytime anybody
asked me and says like I don't believe
it it's like I always think of that
story and now the whole world knows it
and he really got a 64 well believe it
bad no poor guy anyway here's your five
minutes I'm done I'm done blab yeah I
don't know which ways Sam's going to do
but maybe if if Sam has a better way
here you should see it because he often
has a better way the factorial ends and
them on this one done let's go
- one to get an upper limit on that we
substituted for each of these terms and
itself so insect oil is going to be less
than or equal to n to the end we really
don't have to put the equal in but now
we want to get a lower limit on that if
we simply substituted one for each of
these it's not going to be a very useful
lower limit but I'm suggesting that we
cut it off at let's say n over two and
then it keeps going well n factorial is
going to be greater than one-half of the
the front tail because we've cut off the
rear tail and not only added more it's
going to be greater than n times n minus
1 all the way down to n over two and now
I'm going to substitute n over 2 for
each of these terms each of these terms
is greater than n over two or equal to
it so n factorial is greater than n over
two and there n over two such terms
I'm fudging a little because n over two
maybe halfway in between two integers
but the fudge you can work out for
yourself so log of n factorial is going
to be greater than log of n over two to
the N over two which is n over two times
log of n over 2 which is one-half n log
n minus log two and log of n minus log
two is we dealt with before but anytime
you have a sum of two terms or a
difference of two terms in which one
term overpowers the other you can
effectively ignore the second term so
this gave you the one-half and log in
again instead of substituting at the end
where you have to substitute one for all
of these terms and that's not going to
give you a
useful inequality you cut it off halfway
and you substitute the left side by its
lowest number which is n over two and
you're going to get as a lower bound and
over 2 raised to the N over 2 power
exactly the same as the upper bound was
n to the nth power
before you take the logs on both sides
and then takes a lot on both sides at
the end and it is easier to see that way
I think Sam also mentions this he says
look if you have n over 2 log N and then
there's a minus something since n log n
is bigger than n you can just forget
about this this minus n over 2 because
as n gets big sooner or later this will
overpower that and that is true but if
you really want to use the theorem
specifically you have to say at what
point that's going to overpower that'll
be that X 0 or else you just can do this
little trick that I did which is fixing
that the c-17 always local powered by
something that's 17 what we're here