out what it's all about but
traditionally this course is got a funny
you should look at the syllabus and find
history discrete math is a hodgepodge of
different topics if you talk to
professor's in the last 10 years they
have different opinions they feel like
we shouldn't have a course in discrete
map because we have a course in logic
and we have a course in combinatorics
and we have a course in graph theory and
we have a course in analysis of
algorithms and what are you doing you're
doing little bits of all those courses
in calling it discrete math and this was
kind of a popular argument and some
schools did not develop a discrete math
course because of that but as the years
went on even those kind of diehard
people with those arguments kind of gave
in and said well you know what all these
techniques kind of lead toward things
that come up in computer science and it
does make sense to put them all together
under one rubric and call it discrete
math and there is something in common
with all these different areas graph
theory combinatorics logic number theory
say the thing that's in common with them
the most is that the course is about
it's about counting it's about counting
things counting things is usually pretty
easy I can count the number of people in
this class you're 36 people that's
simple but there's hard things to count
and counting comes up as a separate
topic in this class and about a week or
so we talk lots of detail about it there
are two main things that are clever
about counting one is noticing when two
things are the same counting things that
seem like they're separate but they're
really the same and then the other part
is developing all sorts of clever tools
to count stuff that just doesn't seem
easy to count and we'll get to those
things so what's an example of discrete
math an example of counting say you have
36 people in a room okay and there's a
job I need to get done like Xerox these
lecture notes right every day we're
going to Xerox lecture notes but say we
need two people to do it right I don't
know why two people walked out before
what you need two people to do it and
every day every day I need to send a
different two because I don't want to
show any favorites right so how many
different ways can I choose a pair of
people to go Xerox my notes at a 36
that's a question of counting we have to
count that okay it's more than 36 and
we'll figure out a way we'll figure out
a way today we'll do it in a few minutes
another question say I go to a bowling
alley that's what the pins look like in
a normal bowling alley but in a baby
bowling alley it looks like this so the
kids can actually knock all the pins
down and in an extra super bowling alley
for people who get three hundreds
regularly they do it like that
now you can knock down 15 pins so this
is called the one lane the two lanes of
the four lane the five lane you know
because it's got five ropes so how many
pins are in the lane that's numbered
five or numbered n how do you count
those so these two problems are the same
okay if I went to the 36 Lane and I
counted the number of pins in the 36
Lane that would be the number of pairs
of people I could throw out of this room
in different ways it's not too hard to
see that these problems are the same and
we're going to see it in just a few
minutes so we'll get back to it but I
want to give you an example of a problem
of counting which is much much harder to
see the connection between which you
won't see it until much later in the
course and you'll think about it a lot
and try to see a connection here you
might even figure it out before I get to
it but the the harder one is trickier
here's a harder one in scheme you guys
aren't about binary trees right did you
tell me you did all right so so here's a
binary tree with with three nodes right
here's another one with three nodes are
there more
think that's it
well the directions matter so we count
these are different oh yeah good so good
we get five five is the right number for
three notes if you add another node you
get a lot more trees and in fact well
why is it useful to know how many binary
trees there are with end nodes because
you might give a project to somebody
who's trying to figure out say a minimum
spanning tree of a graph that means a
tree that's going to go over a graph and
have the least weight on all its edges
it's a very common problem you'll study
it in algorithms and let's say
somebody's idea of a good algorithm is
well I'll just try all the trees and
pick the one that has the minimum weight
okay that's an idiot algorithm because
the number of trees for n nodes is
something on the order of 4 to the N
it's huge the minute you get up to 100
nodes this algorithm will take a few
centuries to run right so it's no good
you need to know how to count the trees
because you need to know sometimes what
not to do
all right there's other reasons why you
might want to count binary trees number
of binary trees on Ed nodes here's a
different problem from linear algebra
back two months ago if I'm multiplying
three matrices together let's assume
they're square matrices so they all can
multiply one by the other how many
different ways are there to to multiply
them well you got to multiply and left
to right right but you can either do it
this way and then the last one right how
else could you do it good good Michael
right if I put another one in but put
another array in that'd be even more
ways okay it turns out that well if
there are three arrays it corresponds to
the number of ways there are of having
two node binary trees for raise three
node binary trees five arrays
4-node binary trees there's a
relationship they're the same this
connection is not obvious at all
you might get some intuition maybe it
makes some sense but but it's not
obvious and you're going to see why this
is true much later in the course when we
talk about combinatorics but this is an
introduction this is what people who do
discrete math care about they care about
problems like this they don't care about
what's the best way to build the jet
fighter airplane so that I minimize the
resistance on the air wings that's a
continuous map problem what's the ratio
of height to width of a cylinder that
has the most volume okay that's a
Campbell Soup production problem that's
a discontinuous problem it's not
discrete math the screen that deals with
stuff you can count things you can get
your hands on and ironically sometimes
getting your hands on something makes it
actually even a little more difficult
things you can count sometimes are
really really deep and tricky okay
questions about all this stuff in doing
discrete math you're going to be doing
proofs some of you have never done
proofs before some of you have so we
need to talk about what talk about what
a proof is it's a little tricky in
reality a proof is no more than just
convincing somebody else that
something's true okay but mathematically
you'd like to be able to be a little
more rigorous than that I am NOT going
to teach you this month how to be
mathematicians I'm going to teach you
about discrete math so when I ask you to
prove something the definition that I
want to use for a proof is you have
convinced me or the TA or one of your
colleagues according to the standards of
our class that we believe that what you
just said is true
it's a very vague definition but we're
not going to have your right formal
formal formal proofs it'll come close
but ask yourself whether you've been
convincing real proofs can be done at
the bottom level turning everything into
logic which we'll talk about later today
and nobody ever writes a proof like that
because it's incomprehensible the way
you really explain a proof is you do
interactively I give you some intuition
I do example now then if you wanted to
write the proof up what would you do you
would cover up all your tracks of how
you discovered the theorem because
there'd be all these dead ends you'd
clean it all up you'd present it from
the very beginning till the very end in
a nice
beautiful whale mo lemma theorem
corollary conclusion and the person who
would read it on a desert island all by
themselves could reconstruct your result
because you've been completely rigorous
and careful even though they would take
much much longer to understand it than
if you just sat with them for ten
minutes explaining your idea so the best
thing is to have a combination of both
in class I'm going to be explaining to
you how things work when I write proofs
on the board and I explain it
they are meant not meant to be
publishable they're not meant to be
reconstructed if you want to see good
proofs for things look in the textbook
that's where people have really written
it out in detail so that if you were by
yourself you could read it and figure it
out there needs to be an understanding
and an interaction when I'm explaining
it and that is always true and you
should always try to do your proofs not
by deciding what I'm going to write down
next step but by thinking of the idea
and writing an English paragraph just
being communicative and you'll get it
right all right so in order to explain
this I'm going to do examples of two
proofs really cool proofs are proofs by
contradiction here's the first one I'll
explain what a proof by contradiction is
as I go through these this proof is
originally due to Aristotle as far as
anyone knows and it's been copied many
times and attributed to lots of other
people but he was the first one I think
to actually write the argument down a
rational number is a number that can be
written as a fraction a over B like 2/3
is a rational number 1.4 is a rational
number because it's 14 tenths an
irrational number is a number that can't
be written as a fraction so you need to
know if there are any numbers that can't
be written as fractions in the square
root of two is one of those numbers so
here's a proof that the square root of
two can't be written as a fraction it's
a very clever proof because trying every
fraction and seeing that it doesn't work
is not a good proof right you do that
forever so you need a better proof so
here's how the proof works it's really
clever the proof says look let's assume
for the moment that the square root of 2
can be written as a fraction and I'm
going to show you something very strange
happens I'm going to convince you that
if you can write the square root of 2 as
a fraction then the top and the bottom
of that fraction both have to be even
well that's a very strange fraction is
there any fraction that the top and the
bottom have to be Eve
I can just train this into two over one
now the top and the bottom aren't even
but I'm going to convince you that no
matter what you do when you're all done
giving me the fraction the top and the
bottom have to be even there is no
fraction in the whole world where the
top and the bottom has to be even you
can always turn it into a fraction where
the top and the bottom aren't even so
I'm going to assume that this will give
us a horrible contradiction and I'm
going to prove to you that the top and
bottom have to be even all right another
way to look at it the way some people
say it is let's assume the square root
of 2 equals a over B where a over B has
already been put into lowest terms okay
you think you've got a fraction you come
back to me you say I got a fraction I go
we'll do me a favor put it into lowest
terms before I start my argument and you
go okay so now what's in lowest terms
the top and the bottom can't be even and
now I'm going to convince you they have
to be even that proves that you lied
that proves that the square root of 2 is
really irrational that it can't be it
would equal 2 any faction right so let's
do it
here's how the method goes it's really a
very straightforward proof and it's it's
magical in a lot of ways let's square
both sides of the equation I should tell
you that when I say it's an easy proof
and it's magical I could make a proof
that I would be doing this and we're all
friendly together and there would be a
very subtle flaw somewhere in the middle
and I would everybody would miss it so
so never believe anything I say in this
case it really works but but there are
proofs that have subtle flaws and one of
your problem sets I ask you to find
subtle flaws and these following proofs
and you'll have to find them 2 equals a
squared over B squared and now 2b
squared equals a squared all right so
what does that tell you about a squared
it tells you that a squared has to be an
even number because it's twice something
in fact we can even use that as the
definition of an even number and even
number is anything you can write as 2
times something there's other
definitions but that's 1 so this implies
that a squared is even and now we need a
little theorem or sometimes what's
called a lemma helper theorem something
that helps us along the way if a squared
is even we want to know what a is I'd
like to get the fact that a is even so
is that true if a number squared is even
the number have to be even let's do some
examples
16 is evens that mean fourth fours even
36 is even six is even is it always true
do you believe it's true why do you
think it's true okay yeah he can't be
broken into two parts I guess we'd have
to argue but that's one way to look at
it good
another way to look at it is well what
else could it be if it wasn't even it
could be odd right if an odd number got
squared that would have to be odd that's
odd yes you can prove that an odd number
square design take any odd number it's
something that looks like this and
square it out using the algebra that you
learned and you'll find out that it
equals two times something plus one I'm
not going to do the details because I
asked you to do it in a problem so
you'll do it later but this implies that
a is even and I'll put a little star
here that's based on the lemma that if a
number squared is even then the number
is even so now we've got that a is even
and if a is even I'm going to write it
as two times some number so I get two B
squared equals two times some number
squared a equals 2k so everybody see
what comes next
2b squared is four K squared B squared
is 2k squared and now by the same
argument before B squared is even and
then B is even and the world explodes
because you lied you told me you had a
lowest terms fraction equal to the
square root of two and I just convinced
you that a is even and B is even so what
you claimed isn't true therefore there's
no way anybody could ever get a fraction
equal to the square root of two I just
took any possible person's claim and
debunked it this is called a proof by
contradiction I assume it can be and I
derive a contradiction that I have a
fraction where both halves have to be
even even though the fraction is in
lowest terms that can't be that
contradicts the assumption other
questions about this proof the next
group is about number theory and I
wanted to mention
besides graphs and comment
Horrocks and logic and all the different
pieces of this discrete math course
there's one really cool piece that will
do toward the end that I think everybody
will like number theory has
traditionally been one of the most
elegant and abstract and just more
beautiful areas of mathematics one of
the areas where if you were going to
pick on an area of mathematics that have
no application at all it would be number
theory there was a famous number
theorist
Hardy who wrote a big paper at the end
of his life basically trying to it was
called a mathematicians apology and it's
all about how his life was worthwhile
because he's an artist and he's not
curing anybody from cancer but what he
does is beautiful and it's beautiful in
the same way that music is beautiful
it's worth reading it's only about ten
pages long it's reprinted in a lot of
places I'm sure you could find it on the
web it's a very nice work and in it he
actually goes through this proof as an
example of beautiful mathematics the
point of the point of this is that it
turns out serendipitously that number
theory is at the complete heart of the
most practical application that runs on
the web the thing that lets you send
your credit card over to a company and
have it be encrypted safely is based on
three theorems in number theory one
called for my little theorem and one
theorem about congruence is stuff that
was completely never expected to have an
application ends up being the crux of
public cryptography where I can safely
have somebody encode something and I can
be the only one to decode it so we're
going to go through the details of that
and do the number theory behind it
that's one of the last topics we'll do
right now I'm going to do the second
most famous proof of math that there's
an infinite number of prime numbers this
proof is due to Euclid on the site I
have a I have a link to Euclid's
elements Euclid wrote a 14 volume
masterpiece called the elements it's the
it's the heart of all Western
mathematics ever since then it's the
beginning of thinking of mathematics in
a rigorous way with proofs in his 14
volumes he's a book on number theory a
book on geometry a book on solid
geometry a book on arithmetic etc the
way he structured his books is very much
like
symphonie he starts with definitions and
postulates and works his way up through
theorems and the early theorems are very
simple and trivial and he works his way
up and he has got a climax theorem at
the end all right so the climax theorem
in the geometry book is the Pythagorean
theorem the climax theorem and one of
his number theory books is a theorem
about perfect numbers and one of the
climax theorems in one of the other
books is that there's an infinite number
of prime numbers so this is a beautiful
theorem it's easy to explain it's all
it's the same kind of proof it's a proof
by contradiction yeah so I want to do a
little preliminary before I explain this
proof to make sure everybody's able to
do this quickly so here Greg easy
question that's I'm putting you on the
spot is that the visible why - yes or no
no - easy six times 128 thousand one
hundred thirty-six plus one who knows if
it's divisible by two it's not why is it
not because because this part's
divisible by two and there's one left
over 2 times 3 to the 512 plus 1 no it's
not even because this parts even you're
adding 1 what if I have 3 times 859 plus
1 is that the visible by 3 that number
no because the first parts divisible by
3 and there's one left over I want this
to seem obvious because if I just wrote
it up it might not seem obvious but I
want to make sure you think this is
obvious writing numbers like this is a
sure way to know whether they're
divisible by the number that's sitting
out here you can just look at this point
what if I change this to 2 is it
divisible by 3
now what if I made this 6 is it
divisible by 3 here's smart
birthday alright so here's your clothes
you could says look there's not an
infinite number of prime numbers you
come to me you come back you'll work
really hard at night and you go I'm
certain there's a finite number of prime
numbers and here they are so if that's
what you claim I claim you should list
them for me all right and I'm going to
do this by example but this works in
complete generality here's your list
your list starts with two three five
seven and it ends up at some point let's
say the last one you come up with this
31 we could call it n but it I think
it'll be easier if I just write 31 all
right say that's your list of prime
numbers okay and here's what I'm going
to do I'm going to multiply all these
numbers together or you could we'll
multiply all these numbers together and
add one to them is this number divisible
by two no right because this whole the
whole thing you're we're smart up until
this item here this part is divisible by
two but when you add one it's no longer
divisible by two is it divisible by
three this part is because it's got a
factor of three but you add one so it's
not the visible by three anymore in fact
it's not divisible by any of these prime
numbers whether they are but they're but
I just made a list of the prime numbers
so there are no other number done but
you're right alright so what so what do
you know about this number you sure it's
prime be really careful it's either
prime itself or it could have a factor
but if it does have a factor it's not 2
3 5 7 etc up to 31 so as proof is
actually a little bit subtle it's not
that he has constructed a number for you
that is definitely prime that's bigger
than yours he's constructed a number
that either is prime which shows that
there's another one you missed or has a
factor which itself is a prime number
different than all of these which means
you missed one everybody got those two
possibilities I'm focusing on this
because one of your problems in the
set is right a scheme function what kind
of scheme function would you write to
solve the following problem you want to
write a scheme function to figure out
the smallest prime number for which this
ends up actually not being a prime
itself everyone understand what I mean
sometimes it's ends up being a prime
number sometimes it ends up having a
factor which is bigger than 31 what's
the smallest number for which it's going
to end up not being a prime maybe it
always ends up being prime right well it
doesn't but what's the smallest number
what kind of what problem set does that
fit into in last month's course streams
right it's screaming out streams because
you want to miss make the stream of
prime numbers and then construct the
next one with the next part of the
stream if you had just finished problem
set eight you could probably go back and
do this in ten minutes by the time you
do it it'll be a week since you did
problems today so it will take a half an
hour to reconstruct it but that's a cool
problem to work and I'm trying to
connect up all the different threads of
this year together and I think that'll
that'll make a good little braid first
when you see that you think well it
could be or you could think if yours is
really hard you could have as a factor
and some number that wasn't one of those
Prime's at non prime number right it's
only when you think that all those
non-price break down into those problems
that that every number can be divided
into factors that are prime numbers so
so there's going to be one of those
prime factors that isn't one of these
numbers through 31 but yeah you've got a
point there's there's more I have to say
this theorem came after a bunch of other
theorems that are necessary you're right
Chris other questions if it was not
directly a prime number would have to
contain at least two prime numbers we're
not in our list
did have to contain - so right I mean
right missing water missing - all we
need is one to get the infinite right
because this could repeat itself right I
mean if you what if you took this prime
number and added it to your list
maybe I should point this out this is a
completely general argument if you take
this prime number now that I pointed it
out to you and add it to your list and
say oh I forgot that one here's my new
list I would just do I wouldn't even
come back into the room I just say well
why don't you replay that argument for
yourself again right with the new number
and add it to your lesson you just got
another new number the point is that
this argument will work repeatedly
forever and you can never get them all
it would be is that the new number of
might not be at the end of the list it
could be in the middle right absolutely
what's more that idea of always
recreating a new one is actually an idea
that comes up in one of the most
fundamental proofs in computer science
the proof that there are programs that
can't actually there there are things
that you'd like to program that can
actually be done that don't have a
program for that and the idea is you
list all the possible programs and you
prove that there's one program that's
missing and if you include that program
in there you list the programs again and
you can conclude that there's another
program that's missing there's always
things you want to do that there are no
programs for and it actually is a little
reminiscent of this proof that's called
the halting problem and you'll see it
you'll see it in this course a little
bit you'll see it in the theory of
computation course you'll see it but I'm
going off on my tangent new thing we're
gonna go back to that counting idea the
bowling pin stuff and the and the
sending out pairs of people from this
room and I'm going to show you that
those two are the same so how many pairs
of people can you pick from a group of n
how many pairs from n
them out as a group we don't care which
one gets to the door first right right
so if I send out the Todd and Doug it's
the same as send it out Doug and Todd
that counts as one all right one think
of it as lunch dates right we're not
gonna oh all right oh I'll just quit
there all right let's let's count this
how many person here's one way to count
it there's a lot of ways to count things
one mate account this is just brute
force here's what I'll do I'll include
myself in the group I get sent out and I
can go with every one of you people in
this class so me and Michael me and
Sharon me and Sam etc now let's say
there are n people in the class right
I'm one of them how many people can I go
with n minus one right that's fine that
takes care of me I'm now out of the
picture right so now we'll go down the
list we'll go to Michael Michael can go
out with how many people an additional n
minus two because we already counted him
going out with me right so he only gets
to connect with the people that are left
over n minus 2 and then Sharon can go
out with n minus 3 and sooner or later
we get all the way out to Brian over
there in the corner and the only person
that we haven't matched him with is Tara
so it ends up being plus 3 plus 2 plus 1
okay you add all these numbers up you'll
find out the number of pairs of things
you can pull from n now this is also the
number of bowling pins in the
appropriate alley right 1 2 3 you can
see it so those two now are the same you
can see they're the same these kind of
numbers are called triangle numbers
because they look like triangles you're
already familiar with square numbers
right 1 4 9 16 so these are triangle
numbers it'd be nice to get a formula
for the triangle numbers the formula for
the square numbers is N squared right
the formula for triangle numbers as well
I don't know by the way there are
pentagonal number
is an hexagonal numbers also and you can
that's what mathematicians do you come
up with a good idea you generalize it
you connect it to other ideas you go
wild but we're just going to we're just
going to work on triangle number
triangle numbers we'll call
the enth triangle number to be equal to
this 1 plus 2 all the way up to n minus
1 ok that's the end triangle number it's
a number of pairs you can choose from n
people it's the number of bowling pins
in in something with n minus 1 rows ok
so let's get a formula for this we are
not going to prove this by induction
even though that's the most typical
example of showing a proof by induction
proof by induction is a very common
proof which I haven't showed you yet I'm
going to show you a proof by induction
later today we're going to spend a whole
day on induction later on in the course
but today I want to prove this in other
methods because just because you can
prove something by induction doesn't
mean it's the easiest way induction is
one technique and you'll learn when it's
the best when it's not the best and
we're going to stay away from proving
this by induction we're going to try to
prove a formula for this
in another method and let's see I had
two methods here let's try this method
an example of then we'll generalize the
example here's a method where the number
of the number of numbers is even let's
do a geometric method
triangle into a rectangle because I know
it's an even number so I can do that
all right go that's going to be half
what's the dimensions of my rectangle
here if I did this for a general end if
this was n n dots and it was a triangle
then when I turned it into a rectangle
what are the dimensions of my rectangle
because i've cut it in half and what
happens here on the bottom I get this
one extra guy coming up so if it's even
if n is even and even I get a formula
that's equal to n over 2 times n plus 1
let's take the same argument and check
what happens when n is odd let's do an
example how do I do this with the
rectangle argument I'm just going to
take the top part not including this I
don't have a middle spot so I'll just go
up one above the middle and I'll put it
down over here what's the dimensions of
my new thing now this is still going to
be n right and what's this part going to
be n plus 1 over 2 there's a proof ok
it's a geometric proof now look at this
bizarre formula I have two cases this is
for n is even this is for n is odd
you're coming at a ninth grade
look at these formulas are they the same
they're identical so why do I need to
write them twice and you're thinking
well you don't and now I know you don't
and it's just because the proof does two
cases and maybe it didn't need to but
there's actually a much more subtle
point here and and now I can put on my
history and math hat for just 30 seconds
in the 13th century in the 14th century
when people wrote theorems like this
theorem 32 was this
theorem and theorem 33 was this theorem
and nobody thought that was redundant
because there wasn't any algebra nobody
wrote formulas like this nobody could
glance and see visually that these two
were the same this formula this theorem
reads like this if you add up an even
number of numbers from one increasing by
one as you get to the last number that
equals half the number of numbers times
one plus the number of numbers you have
and the other theorem reads if you have
an odd number of blah-blah-blah that
equals the number of numbers you have
plus one two it's just that reads
differently it doesn't look the same in
English these two don't look the same
and math they do look the same this is
actually a simple example of something
that's very important in that notation
can give you intuition good notation for
an idea can lead you to the next step
bad notation can obscure the next step
so that you don't see it ever so be
really careful with notation there's
good choices for notation and you'll see
a lot of notation in this class that's
possible not sure they would all do it
but actually the truth is they have
three theorems for this but yet you
might be able to you can certainly do
better than this even without algebra
next next stage there's a folklore story
I think I told you this story the
folklore story about Gauss one of the
greatest mathematicians of all time in
the in the early 1800s and that a school
teacher told him to add the numbers from
1 to 100 together because he was a
little bored in class and hoped that
would keep him busy and he quickly
blurted out the answer and it's really
just this problem asking him what the
hundredth triangle number was add the
numbers from 1 to 100 and he did this
quickly and what a lot of kids
rediscover when you tell them this
problem is that they pair numbers up on
the two ends one in a hundred equals 100
and one two and 99 equals one hundred
and one three and 98 equals one hundred
and one and how many times do you do
this half as many times as you have your
list so that gives you like the classic
n plus one times n over two right n plus
one is the sum of the two numbers on the
end and you do it half as many times as
there are things in the list
and that's another way to look at if
there's a lot of ways to look at this
theorem you should remember this formula
for adding up the numbers 1 to N for the
triangle formula comes up again and
again yeah done like if you start with 0
plus 1 it would but the way triangle
numbers are defined is that you start
from 1 if we define triangle numbers
start from 0 then we'd have to change
the formula now you're right it would
change it would change it but we don't
include 0 all right so you might wonder
at this point you know what the sum of
the squares are what the sum of the
cubes are what the sum of the fourth
powers are all these things are part of
discrete math and we'll get to them in
time all right but now I'm going to
switch to a cool problem that we will
prove by induction hmm here's a puzzle
here's a pancake and you want to cut it
into pieces with a big sharp knife I cut
it into two pieces if I cut it again how
many pieces do I get here's the rules
about the cuts every cut has to go
through each of the other cuts in
exactly one place and you can't cut
through the same spot here again the
next cut has to go here for example
that's the rules about the cuts in this
game so let's make a little chart number
of cuts number of pieces if I make one
cut how many pieces zero cuts one piece
two cuts how many pieces three cuts four
cuts whew we got to do four cuts really
carefully hmm you got to cut through
every other cut exactly once and you
can't go through any points they're
already there so maybe I should
rearrange my lines it's going to be hard
to draw it can I do it like right here
will that go through all the other cuts
ones how many cuts how many pieces do I
get now a little bit here's a discrete
math problem
what goes there and what goes there
in the lurch here I gave you a big hint
what did we just do we just did triangle
numbers what are they 1 what are the
triangle numbers 3 triangle numbers plus
1 TN plus 1 question mark are we lucky
or is that true it's true but we're
going to prove it's true and we're going
to prove it's true by a method of proof
called mathematical induction which is a
method of proof that concentrates in a
particular style of thinking and I want
to give you that idea and do it in
detail here here's one of the neatest
things about proofs by mathematical
induction sometimes you can discover a
theorem like this even though you know
the slightest clue why it's true and you
can prove it by mathematical induction
because you concentrate on a particular
aspect of where this comes from even
though you still don't really understand
why the whole thing works out and that's
the coolest thing about a proof by
mathematical induction you can kind of
not only discover the truth and prove
the truth but still feel like somehow
it's kind of magic and that's ok that's
a good way to do it that's true that's a
good way to do it
how many pieces we get here and see
what's happening as we go and see if we
can convince ourselves that it's an
accident or not an accident how many new
pieces do we get every single time I add
a line let's do it again
I have the first line how many new
pieces that I get one new piece how many
new pieces do I get when I add the next
line two new pieces how many new pieces
do I get when I add the next line three
why how come I got three new pieces when
I cut through that third piece how come
line and I have to cut through this line
the two lines that are there every time
I cut through a line what happens there
used to be one piece here right I cut
through that line I got a new piece
there used to be one piece here I cut
through this line I get a new piece
through that line I get a new piece so
what happens is if I have to cut through
two lines how many new pieces do I get
three new pieces if I have to do the
next step how many new pieces would I
expect I have to cut here through three
lines I would expect four new pieces is
that what happens seven to 11 for good
so now we have not only a conjecture we
have something that's plainly obvious
that we've just kind of proven by this
argument here's what we prove it let's
call this P P n we'll call the pieces
that you get with n cuts we've proved
that P n is equal to whatever you had
before sorry
erase this make sure we have plenty of
room P of N equals the number of pieces
we had before right plus how many new
ones we had n minus 1 lines before if we
cut through all of them we get one extra
piece so altogether how many new pieces
and this is something we just proved
this is a recursive relationship a
recurrence relationship we're going to
talk about solving equations like this
later in the class not today what we're
going to do today is prove the following
theorem PN equals TN plus 1 and one of
the things we're going to use in proving
this theorem is this relationship that
we've just proven ok I think we proved
that I think every new line has to cut
through the number of lines that were
there before which is n minus 1 and you
get one more piece so you get n new
pieces every time you add a line I think
that's a good enough proof I don't know
if you don't think so then I have to
prove it better no really what is it not
rigorous enough what do you think what
just intuitively also whenever you get a
new line you could actually see the
circle the number of pieces you're
adding Falls neatly on one side of the
line and the number of pieces that were
there on the other side of line right
right I agree you can you buy that now
all right so right the measure of
whether our proof is right is whether
huh is whether we vote on it and it
works so that means whoever gets to be
President next is going to be right mmm
all right it's okay there's some
democracy in math there is reviews on
papers all right let's get back to this
let's prove this is true here's the
method of mathematical induction let me
let me give you some intuition behind it
then I'll show you how it works because
it will seem a little magical the idea
of mathematical induction is you want to
prove something for an infinite amount
of cases in this case for N equals 1 for
N equals 2 for n equals 3 for all these
cases so rather than come up with a
general argument that works for all of
them which may be hard to do sometimes
it's easy sometimes it's hard instead
let's concentrate on convincing somebody
that if it were true for say the case of
3 I could convince you in general that
it would work for 4 let's come up with a
general argument that shows somebody why
the truth of the next case is definitely
valid as long as the truth of the last
case was valid if I came up with a
general argument like this then all I
have to do is show you that someplace at
the beginning it's true and you could
use that argument repeatedly to show the
truth of all the subsequent cases that's
the idea instead of focusing on the
general case focus on the transition
from one case to the next sometimes that
transition implies a very deep idea
about the general case that you don't
have a tough time getting a handle on
but you can focus right on the
transition and you're going to see
dozens of examples of this in this class
it's the most commonly used proof in
computer science this is going to be a
very short one and a very simple one but
we're going to go through it in detail
here's how it works
mechanically we assume that the theorem
we're trying to prove is true
for this case and we have to come up
with an argument to show
that therefore it must be true for the
next case so let's write it this way
we'll assume that P of N equals TN plus
1 we want to prove that the next case is
true that P of n plus 1 equals TN plus 1
plus 1 we want to go from here to here
some of you here's what you can't do you
can't say oh if I'm assuming this is
true then I'll just put in n plus 1 for
n and that shows that's true that's not
allowed
you're only assuming that it's true for
this particular n not for any other end
in the whole world except for this one
can you go ahead and then show that it's
true for the next step so we're going to
have to use other ideas and hopefully
this will help us so here's what we're
going to do we're going to work with
this and try to prove it's true at some
point if we need this assumption we'll
work with it we're going to throw P n
plus 1 equals TN plus 1 plus 1 what do
we know about PN plus 1 what's the only
thing we know about it good we can use
this formula on PN plus 1 this we know
works in general let's use this formula
on PN plus 1 what does PN plus 1 equal
it equals PN plus plus n plus 1 okay
equal to TN plus 1 so this equals TN let
me get in this write TN plus 1 plus n
plus 1 okay so first I use this theorem
and then I use this assumption I got
this on the Left I'm looking to get this
on the right am I almost there write
this to you now let's see n I just move
them around what is this
TN plus n plus 1 if you have a triangle
number up to n and then you add the next
number on you get the the next triangle
number CN plus 1 PN plus 1 equals TN
plus 1 plus 1 three steps one assumption
here one assumption there and the
definition of a triangle number this
yeah the the n plus one here is the next
number that we add on to the TN triangle
number so that gives you TN plus 1
there's a lot of words here that I left
out and this proof is going to see
magical if you've never seen a proof by
induction before and I cleaned
everything up because I created this
proof to see magical so I didn't give
you any motivation or where we're going
I just made it look magical and that's
somewhat on purpose I want you to see
how elegant and Swift induction proofs
are but we're not
right but what I want you to realize is
that you still need an idea here and the
idea here is using this recursive
relationship for P N and then showing
that you can get from this step to the
next step
alright Sam's right you do need to show
that this has a starting point so we
have to show that this is true for a
particular end so let's show that it's
for a particular n let's start with n
equals 1 P of 1 equals 2 what is T of 1
equal 1 so 2 equals 1 plus 1 and that's
true so it does have a starting point it
does work this general method of going
from one step to the next works over and
over again look at it on your own study
it make sure you get the idea behind it
you're going to see lots and lots of
examples of this some of which will be
much more intuitive some will be less
intuitive but that's a proof by
induction prove the connecting step this
math is not just some egghead sitting at
a desk coming up with formal proofs and
I don't mean that in any kind of a
general way I mean it what it really is
is a scientist there's experimenting in
that I gave you problem sets that you're
going to have to learn to think like a
mathematician really thinks instead of
how you think of mathematician things a
mathematician doesn't think oh I get it
now and I'm going to going to write the
proof line-by-line a mathematician
struggles they discover the experiment
they try things a lot of the problems
that I gave you are going to force you
to experiment and try things and write
programs to generate more data and when
you see the pattern you think you have
the truth only then do you go back and
try to figure out hey now that I think
it's really true why is it really true
and you know what by that time you
probably have a pretty good idea why I'm
going to switch gears now let's move
away from proofs and our intro I'm going
to start on what I decided would be the
first topic in this class logic and I
decided on this because another way to
write proofs is to turn them all into
logic formulas where everything is
represented by some variable and we
connect things by logical connectives
and we can actually turn it into a
mechanical process and there's a big
area in computer science called
automated theorem proving and you do
just that
you take statements you turn them into
mechanical strings you write a program
that can manipulate them in some logical
way and you come up with new statements
and one of the neat things that their
improver once came up with in geometry
for example is a proof that if you have
an isosceles triangle these two angles
are the same ok there's a lot of ways to
doing this the make way most kids do it
in high school or whenever you is to put
a little perpendicular bisector here and
fold it on itself that's one way and do
side angle who knows what there
Pot News live forget hypotenuse leg
theorem but this this theorem prover
came up with a filing clever proof that
actually makes you think twice it said
well triangle ABC is congruent to
triangle ACB it took the triangle itself
and it said it was congruent to the
mirror image and it got the result that
way and it didn't do it because it was
clever it did it because the random
collections of mcmechen eyes rule
implications actually came up with a
cool proof it's true you got to look
through 5,000 idiot proofs to come up
with this but but machines can come up
with clever things as long as you don't
mind looking at the young clever things
what I want to do now though is give you
the basics of logic the basics of
boolean algebra the basics of
representing things in logic and this
stuff is not only useful in proofs but
that's what mathematicians think about
it's useful in computer science because
it's the foundation for building
circuits in a computer it's the
foundation for algorithms because the
most difficult algorithm in the whole
world is figuring out whether a
particular boolean formula has any set
of values that makes it true that's the
first np-complete problem you'll hear
about that actually if you go to the
talk later tonight at Harvard he'll talk
about that it's useful in computer
science because it's a way to model
almost every kind of computational
problem so you'll see this in a million
ways I'm going to start off with really
really basics of this and here's the way
will work will consider variables it's
have some meaning like W is it's wet
outside or or this tie is colorful I
mean something that has a value true or
false either it's wet outside or it's
not wet outside and every variable in
this boolean world is going to have a 0
or 1 a true or false one is usually true
zero is usually false and we can connect
them in various logical ways so W is wet
outside R as it's raining let's put some
words and things together it's raining
and it's wet outside
it looks like this this symbol the
up-arrow this symbol the word and and
just multiplication use without anything
are all synonyms for and this and this
are both true you can check whether this
formula is true by checking whether both
r and w are true okay it's raining
outside and it's wet only if both of
those are true this is what logicians
use this is what circuit developers use
and this is what you'll see in a lot of
computer science books our book uses all
three in different places depending what
chapter you're in all right so keep in
mind ah
so one connective is an another
connective is or or is the word or the
symbol plus or the upside-down of the
end I talked about notation before
there's a reason why people use this
notation mechanically we are going to be
able to manipulate logical formulas the
same way multiplication and addition
manipulate there's a distributive
property for multiplication in addition
it works the same for ands and ORS so
there's a reason people use that
notation alright questions about this
yes
you finish your question or means that
either this is true or that's true or
both of them are true
it doesn't mean exclusive or which is a
different logical connective meaning
that either one of the other but not
both it means that one or the other or
both okay but your question is why
should they use +4 or that seems like it
should be an to you it's just you get a
bit of distance between the end because
you think of Plus as being an N because
you're adding yes you know what you're
gonna have to like go into your mind and
take that neuron that's used to that and
twiddle it the other way one zero if
well actually wait a minute now if you
added two trues two ones you can get a
zero well you're all jumping right ahead
and what I hope I can actually finish
today the the issue of boolean
operations is at the heart of doing
binary addition which is at the heart of
building a circuit that does addition
and we're going to we're going to show
that that actually does connect and Plus
does correspond to addition in binary
you'll see soon what is kind of lose the
world a plus sign with a circle around
it
that we'll start with is a connected
that doesn't connect two boolean things
but just works on one call not so not W
means it's not wet outside sometimes
that's written like this sometimes it's
written like this three sets of
notations when to think of these things
not from Circuit's point of view but in
terms of logic point of view here's a
very common thing that you'll see this
means if it's raining outside
then it's wet outside ok implication
it's the way we argue it's the way we
think it's the way proofs go from one
step to another now everybody thinks
they know what this means but what I
want to do is make sure that we all have
the same agreement and the way I want to
do it is I want to actually write out a
table and this writing out a table I'll
do it here are W it's called a truth
table just to show you how it works
we'll do R and W here's what a truth
table does you put all the possible true
and false values here for R and W I use
zeros and 1 0 for false 1 for true
there's four possibilities who can fill
this in for me 0 0 0 1 good ok it's only
1 when both of them are 1 now let's fill
in our for W that's going to be 0 1 1 1
and now let's go over here and we'll
fill in our implies W and let's be
really careful because we actually have
to decide what this means what does it
mean for something to imply something
else it means a difficult one over here
on the left side is true then this has
to be true
let's put that in if this is true this
is true that means that's a 1 there what
about when this is true and that's false
that means 0 what about these two here's
the convention the convention is that
when the left side is false we don't
care what's on the right side we still
consider the implication to be true if I
say if it's raining outside
then it's wet then if it's not raining
regardless of whether it's wet or not my
statement of the implication would still
hold so if the left side is not true
then the right side can be anything we
want and we still say the implication is
true that's a logical decision which
generally makes sense and we go with
that so this is the this is a by
definition this is what we mean by R
implies W and it corresponds to what we
mean logically as well all right
questions about this what I want to show
you is that this is particularly are
implies W could be re-written in terms
of ands ORS and nots without a new
symbol and what you should know is that
any boolean formula can be written in
terms of ands ORS and nots always and
sometimes we say that therefore the set
of operators and or not is a complete
set it can get any function you want in
the whole world and I'm going to
convince you of this in just a minute
that it can be done in general but first
I want to do it just for this R implies
W okay questions so here's how we're
going to do it my convincing is going to
be done by rewriting this table just for
R implies W it reads 1 1 0 1 and what
I'm going to do here could be done in
general for any boolean truth table or
function at all where I list all the
possibilities and I tell you what the
output should be what I'm going to do
now could work for anything and I'm
going to come up with a formula that
just uses ands ORS and nots ok so let's
look at my method and it's very very
it's very logical there's nothing tricky
here I want to come up with a formula
that's going to have a 1 here 1 here 1
here so I'm going to concentrate on
those 3
and let's ask ourselves when should this
formula be true it should be true here
here and here
what makes this row true what has to
happen for this to be true
not our and not W ok what has to happen
for this possibility to be true not our
not our and W but it's this possibility
or this possibility or this possibility
so not our and W or what's the last
possibility are n W let me go through
this again
we take the three rows that have ones in
them or if there were more than that
look at all the rows with ones in them
take it a row at a time we're going to
or the possibilities together because
this formula will be true if either this
is true or this is true or this is true
either this condition or this condition
or this condition these conditions for
them to be true each have to have both
variables satisfying a particular
condition namely both have to be false
not or not W I can do it here I can do
it here I or them together
I got a connection of things that have
not sands and ORS no other connectives
and I get a final formula equal to R
implies W and I could do this for any
formula I didn't even have to give you a
name for it I could just list a whole
bunch of variables put ones and zeroes
in here any way I want it and do it the
same way that's a proof that ands ORS
and nots together make a complete set
you can go to the radio shack buy a box
of an Gates or gates and not gates and
put them together and build any boolean
function at a circuits all right yeah
question
you also do that by doing a knot with a
third one so it'd be like not
as not R or W were you asking something
like this this is what I wanted to say
next anyway some I'm jumping on your
shoulders to hit that I think Michaels
question is is there another formula
that would be equivalent to this or
could I do it in an ad hoc way that
isn't mechanical the answer is yes and
yes this mechanical way you could make a
computer do you could write a scheme
function to print out these functions
but it's true that there's a much
simpler equivalence to R implies W and
you can check it yourself check not R or
W make a truth table for not our Oh W
you'll find out it's the same as 1 1 0 1
so not R or W is the same as this you'd
probably want to go build this circuit
instead of that circuit this one takes
more gates this one has more wires is
there a general rule for always coming
up with a minimum one the answer is kind
of building minimal size circuits is a
hard problem and it's more of an art
than a science there are some techniques
you'll study it next month little know
and is commutative I just put the parens
to show that the ORS go last I mean I
didn't want you to do not why or not are
didn't have the terrain if I didn't have
a friend good day if you always do nots
first and Anne's next and then ORS then
you'll be ok it is it is but I never
said that so I just put the parentheses
in you're right right baroque is right
that if I don't put parentheses in the
implication is do Anne's first because
that's like multiplication do do nots
first that's like negative signs do
Anne's next that's like multiplication
and then do or is that's like addition
so if you don't see parentheses you
assume that that's the right order
Barack's 100% right yeah Chris
what's the left behind kick our than W
equal zero what back in the truth table
mm-hmm I mean here in here yeah what's
the what I see now it's like how about
this let's say I say if I'm ten feet
tall okay then you're a genius all right
is that true or not if I'm ten feet
taller than you're a gene sure whether
or not that is right is the is that
implication true based on the condition
since I'm not ten feet tall I could say
if I'm ten feet tall then you're a 75
year old lady and that implication is
still true because there's nothing to
contradict it since I'm not 10 feet tall
we can't even test it so we consider the
implication true if the thing on the
left is always false does that help a
little I think it's a subtle point I
kind of went over quickly because I
don't want to get into a long discussion
about it because if you get it quickly
it's good and if you don't you get it
later and and I didn't want it to to be
a fussy thing but but yes a good
question yeah and making your three part
equivalence yes you're focusing of the
ones on the right side right since
there's only one zero focus on the
zeroes that put a mounted who's got
problem set one number seven it's a
problem set question I'm not answering
it you answer
formulas
this means it's raining or it's wet
outside and it's not true that it's both
rating in it's wet outside okay
this means it's not raining and it's wet
or it's not wet and it's raining so you
read it you can take English sentences
and turn them into these formulas you
can take these formulas turn them into
English sentences most importantly you
can determine whether one formula is Wow
there is some chalk one formula is
equivalent logically to the other there
are two basic ways to do this one way is
a brute force method that you can
already figure out in your own make a
truth table for this for R and W make a
truth table for this for R and W and see
that they're the same
therefore these formulas will agree on
any inputs of true or false to R and W
let's do it quickly our W 0 0 0 1 1 0 1
1 put in 0 0 into this formula and
calculate the result set I'm picking on
the big guy 0 that's this one can you do
the next one for me to put 0 1 in there
for this also follow zero or one is
going to end up being 1 and then 1 and 0
0 and 1 is going to be false 0 and then
naught that is going to be 1 so we get 1
and now not as the not of this whole
thing
ok so it's 1 ok good
what are the rest somebody do it while
Stalin was f10 what happens with this
one it should be the same both these
functions are equivalent to something
that I mentioned a minute ago
r or W but not but not both our Earl W
and not both of them here it looks just
like I said it in English R or W and not
both of them that happens to be
equivalent not obviously but it's
equivalent to not the first one or the
second one or else not the second one or
the first one can't have both of them
being true or false this is sometimes
written as our exclusive or W exclusive
R is a very common combination I'm going
to go on a complete side thing here for
those of you who just like little
puzzles that happen to connect to
exclusive or there's a it's a cool
puzzle things are really like yeah
that's right here's a good puzzle you
learned about variables and scheme some
of you programmed in other languages
that have variables one thing that you
typically see in a programming language
is you need to switch the value of two
variables a is got to get the value of B
and B's got to get the value of a you
actually hardly do that in scheme but in
other languages it's like you do it on
the second day here's how it's typically
done so you want to switch values of a
and B you do this you have a temporary
variable temp equals a B gets the value
of
a did I do this right sorry it gets the
value of B and B gets the value of 10
now why don't you just do a equals B and
B equals a because you'll lose the value
of the first one before you copied it
over to the value of the second so you
do these three steps you see these in
every book if you open a java book just
open up to those I don't know page 80 on
the sort routine you'll see this it's
called a swap routine if you use
exclusive or then you can do this
without a temporary variable so I'll
leave that as a puzzle you can swap a
and B using exclusive or without any
temporary variables so think about that
it relates to a circuit problem too but
push back to back to here that's the
other way of showing two formulas are
equivalent one is checking all the truth
and false possibilities and one is
manipulating them algebraically to make
them look like one another and that
second way of doing it is from an area
called boolean algebra so let me give
you some of the basic rules and boolean
algebra you can look these up in the
notes or the book and all these rules
could be proved by truth tables here's
one that we've already done are implies
W is equivalent to not R or W that's
worth knowing here are some more basic
ones not not R what's that equivalent to
R all right so just what you think are W
do it this way our are W and C and C and
s you can use the distributive law R or
W and s is the same as RS or good
than regular algebra in regular algebra
the distributive property doesn't work
the other way right if you do R times W
plus s does it equal R times s plus W
times us did I do that right no I didn't
do it right does it equal R plus s times
does that work in real arithmetic no in
fact they bang you on the head and
fourth grade and and and that does work
that doesn't work and nobody ever
remembers this you know they just end up
doing R plus W times s so kind of remind
kids and sooner or later they get this
but if they ever did this the teacher
would say that they're silly but this is
true in boolean algebra this
distributive property works it's
perfectly perfectly symmetrical you can
distribute ends through ORS and
distribute ORS through ends looking at
it in this notation it's really ugly
that's about the worst notation you can
use to show the distributive property
because you're so used to thinking of
this is not distributing so if you want
to look at the distributive property a
little better maybe it's better to do it
this way R and W or s equals R or s and
W or s you're not so used to these
symbols so they don't stick the wrong
idea in your head and this really is
true
you could show these two things are true
through truth tables you can distribute
either an x' through ORS or or strands
questions all right there's two other
main rules yeah Tony yeah
answer to my question yes right oh the
question was how do you swap two
variables without a temporary value and
you can do it using X or actually the
hard way to ask that question is to ask
it without the big hint that it uses X
or and and the follow-up to that well
all right I got oh there's so much to do
in this class I can't go off on my
gazillion tangents but but I need to
move on here two more rules these this
is called the distributive rolls the
next rules are called there's also the
normal rules commutative rules
associative rules and this commutative
or as commutative
they're all associated not going to
write them down you can look them up
but here's rules that aren't as obvious
they're called de Morgan's laws and they
come up in other contexts to liking sets
that will do soon here's the Morgan's
laws it relates nots to Anne's and ORS
not a and B not a or B here's the
general idea if you have a not sign in
front of a collection of things that are
ANDed together you can kind of push that
not sign through just like you push a
negative sign through but when you do it
the operators change from an to or so
this is the same as not a or not the
let's think about that logically if it's
not true that both these things are true
if it's not true that a and B are true
that means either the first one isn't
true or the second one isn't true it's
very logical same thing here this equals
not a and not C okay that's called de
Morgan's laws that's the way to push not
signs through formulas and that's what
lets you do Sam's idea before of
concentrating on the zeros and putting
it not in front of the whole thing it'll
switch all the ends to ORS and all the
ORS to ads and you'll get a nice result
chris is asking whether not an and alone
those two operators are a complete set
can we get rid of or based on this what
do you think I'm going to leave you with
that question this does relate knots and
Ann's tours the question is I think in
order to prove what you're trying to
prove you need to show how to take any a
and B and rewrite it in terms of orders
this doesn't do that exactly if you
could do that if you could take any a
and B and write it just in terms of
knots and ORS then I could take any
formula with Anne's knots and ORS in it
pull out the places where there are
Ann's and replace them with ORS and nots
but this doesn't let you do that because
there's a knot in front of this so it
only lets you replace things with not
live in a visual dot on the right right
so I'll leave it as a it's a very good
thing to think about but I'm going to
let you guys answer it and come with me
next class and tell me the answer but
I'm but it's a perfect question because
it's what I'm going to talk about next
it's like having chills in the audience
I can look at you said you asked your
question now that's looking all right
one little thing before we quit hmm all
right one example and then we'll quit I
wanted to talk about these complete
things but I want of time let's do a
mechanical example to show that these
two things are completely equivalent
that the two exclusive or formulas are
equivalent
what it means Seth it means do R and W
and it's not that whole thing okay or I
could put the knot in front of it too
but it will look like a minus sign I
didn't want to do that I know you knew
it how do we show that this and this are
equivalent mechanically we're going to
use the rules of distributive and de
Morgan's laws and and logical rules to
mechanically manipulate this
syntactically to look like that every
step of the way using things that change
it into stuff that are logically
equivalent and this is really kind of
what they're improvers doing their own
twisted way all right so here's my first
step it's a really kind of a strange
thing to do
in this step what's the justification
for this step which you put a negative
sign over both of those parentheses
there yes so what did I do in this step
I distributed the R and the W over this
term okay that's the distributive rule
for addition over multiplication what do
I do next I'm trying to get it to look
like this experiment what do we do next
here what do I get when I push the not
sign through there not R or not W plus
same thing here not R or not W now what
I'm still not quite like that but I'm
getting really close now what now
distribute out the multiplication over
the addition our R Oh L is good this is
quality chalk here's what I get I can
rearrange these terms because community
community and associativity what about
these extra terms I mean these two match
there that's fine I could you know turn
them around and make a match but these
two are extra what about R and R naught
can that ever be no that can never be
this is false this is false that's one
of the rules one of the basic rules that
are and the negative of are always false
what about something or false a or false
what's that the same as a right in other
words the false doesn't affect it at all
for an or what about a and false
about a and true that's the same as a
what about a or true it's so beautifully
symmetrical boolean algebra distribution
works both ways true and false rules are
just the inverses of each other
everything is just the perfect circle
it's so nice George Boole discovered
this stuff a hundred years ago with no
notion that it would be at the heart of
building computers which is what it's
primarily used for by electrical
engineers so these two things are the
same now you know how to show two
formulas are true by truth tables you
now to show true formulas are true by
algebraic manipulation you know the idea
of a complete set you know that any
formula can be written with ands ORS and
nots and therefore they are a complete
set and you have a notion of what a
proof is and how to do a mathematical
induction proof and all you need now is
25 days of intense practice and we move
on alright so we're going to continue
with the stuff next time tarah today is
going to do another proof by induction
and before that she and I are going to
do this magic trick which I told you
there's a problem set about so get ready