know it's only been two days but we're
moving away from logic and we're going
to shift towards sex and the reason I'm
doing sets right away now is because
now we're going to shift gears okay I
sets build on logic and the things that
we're going to prove about sets and the
connections the computer science we can
prove using the very things that you
just learned about logic by the way if
you look at other books the order of how
discrete math books are laid out is
completely completely very depending on
the book and this guy really has thought
a lot and most of the way he's ordered
it is the way that I would order it to
the way he does logic and then sets
that's very unusual most people don't do
it that way a mathematician always
starts with sets and then does other
stuff and in computer science it makes
more sense to do logic first and I'll
show you why let's start with sets where
the steps come up in computer science
when you're writing a program say
somebody's typing stuff in and you want
to check if the last thing they typed is
a vowel so you'd say hey is the last
thing this person type in the set
AEIOU right it comes up in your programs
it comes up in in data structures the
easiest way to represent a set and
scheme is to just have a list but you
should realize that in mathematics a set
has no implicit order even though in
scheme there would be an implicit order
so a set is just a collection of things
and you can write a set just like that
AEIOU got a nice clean blackboard or you
can describe a set in words
X such that X is an even integer you can
write sets like that you can describe
them in English you can list them
sometimes they'll even see strange
things like this it's not very formal
but everybody knows what this means it's
a set of all natural numbers first one
how do you know there's always even
though you don't have the for all it's
just the notation when you use sets you
give a variable this means such that and
then you give the condition so so it's
implicit that it means from there's a
lot of different language to learn in
doing that but it's all pretty logical
you describe a set there's a particular
algorithm that I mentioned last time
that came up when we talked about trees
called the minimum spanning tree this
has come up twice so I'm actually going
to talk about it for just two seconds
edges and the minimum spanning tree of
this graph is a tree that hits all the
vertices that has the smallest weight so
one horrible way to do this as I
mentioned last time is to try all the
trees and see which one has the least
weight that's terrible but a faster way
and there's a lot of ways to do this is
you start with a smallest edge and you
include that and then you connect the
next smallest edge and you include that
and then the next smallest and as soon
as you've connected all the vertices
you're done and this is actually the
smallest weight spanning tree of this
graph okay and this algorithm was known
maybe about 30 years ago by now invented
by a guy named Kruskal there's another
version by a guy named prim the point of
it is when you actually implement this
algorithm one of the fastest ways to
implement
one of the fastest ways to make it run
is to have a data structure that uses a
set and the set is a collection of these
little piecemeal trees before they get
connected and you build the sets into
bigger sets until you have just one big
set that's the final spanning tree and
that data structure is sometimes called
the union-find data structure you got to
be able to combine sets into bigger sets
and you go to AU to be able given a
vertex to find what set is it in so as
you're building it up you might have
different vertices and different pieces
of different trees if somebody says what
tree is that vertex in what piece is it
and you want to be able to find that out
I'm not going to do any details about
this but you should know that it's one
of the fundamental algorithms and it's
used as a big big important data
structure all right so sets come up a
lot we're going to do some of the basics
of sets here's how you describe sets
here are some of the operations you can
do on sets let's prove some of these
operations let's make sure we know we
can manipulate sets and for that purpose
here's how it works
whenever you talk about sets there's
always a set called the empty set it's a
set of nothing there's nothing in that
set there's also something called the
universal set whenever you talk about a
set of things presumably they're all
subsets of some bigger Universal set so
your universe might correspond to say
all the numbers in the world and then
this would be a subset of that Universal
set this would be a subset of that
Universal set this would be out of the
universe alright so whenever you talk
about sets you have a universe we're
talking about and then subsets of that
and because of that you probably learned
this in grade school you have this
picture where a big rectangle represents
the universe and your your sets are
these circles and sometimes sets overlap
they intersect they have things in
common and these diagrams are called
Venn diagrams and they give you a
picture view of what is going on with
these sets so we're going to get back to
these later because we're going to do
some counting with these that will
actually help us solve some pretty cool
problem
at the universal set that's like what's
outside of our universe in this example
I said these to say this is the even
integers and these would be say the
natural numbers so this might be all
possible real numbers it's just a big
big big collection of things that all
the sets we're dealing with our subsets
up right right because there's no Val
right right the vowels aren't part of
our universe
and you can make the universe just be
everything in the whole world and then
which case everything is there
well he is yes and I guess yeah trouble
maker a union B equals B Union ends it's
so transparent that if I ask you to
prove it you'd all give me a groan and
go well I know it's true but what do you
mean prove it here's what I mean by
prove it what does a union B mean what
does it mean to be an element of a union
B what does it mean to be an element of
B Union a if I want you to prove to me
that these two sets are the same you'd
have to prove to me look it's a long
winded proof even though it's trivial
and transparent but here's what you'd
have to do you'd have to say that if X
is an element of a union B then acts as
an element of B Union a that's what you
have to prove to me and then you'd have
to prove vice-versa that if X is an
element of B Union a then it's an
element of a union B you have to prove
those two things to show that these two
are identical
goes both ways in fact equal in sets is
the same as double implies in logic how
do you do this just unravel it into
logic X and elements of a union B
implies X and elements of B Union a how
do we do this
we want to show that this is true what
is X and elements of a union B mean it
means
acts as an element of a or axis and
elements of B and what does this mean
axis and elements of B or axes and
elements of a well I can turn these two
around how come because or has the
commutative law I can turn this around
because I know I've already proved the
commutative law for or so whatever works
for or is going to end up working for
Union you just unravel it for X a and at
this point I can stop and I can say hey
you know what goes both ways these two
are identical it's definitely true this
direction and that direction these are
identical this proof is trivial there's
nothing to do here except unravel it
reverse the or because you can do it for
ORS and then see that you get two
identical things it's a little less
trivial for an example I'll do in just a
minute I'll do the distributive law for
sets and we'll run through it the same
way unraveling the definition into logic
using the rules we know for logic seeing
that it works and being done I'm going
to do just a couple of these because
they're really dry and I want to go on
interesting stuff yeah here it here this
is a definition of a union B X is an
element of a union B if and only if X is
an element of a or X's and ohm to B
that's definition okay so if you gave a
reason to go from here to here it would
be the definition of a union B the
definition of Union the crucification
from something to itself is we're done
you can make a truth table for this
right that you just make a truth table
for any possibilities of a and B here
it's identical to this so actually we're
done with the proof though we had an
implication for something that's
integral on both sides we can call it
that's like cm PI C right that's going
to be well not just make a truth table
making truth they believe so sure you
can do that if you take all the possible
values for C zero and one and you check
C M PI C 0 implies zero is true one
implies one is true so this is a true
formula C implies C actually this is a
true formula two you wouldn't even have
to go through and do it backwards you
you're already here okay other questions
involved than this trivial one
actually at the bottom there we had
already done it vice versa because we
had an identical thing on the left on an
identical thing on the right you'd have
to do it but it would be the exact same
thing and you get the exact same result
and you write yes yes is the answer okay
let's do a let me give you the
distributive laws it's just what you
would expect that you need an
intersection distribute just like and
and or there's one distributive law once
you give me the next one not you
for a and B or C good equals a intersect
B Union C equals a intersect B Union
is what we did before for andin or it
works for union and intersection it's
the exact same idea and the proofs
behind these are going to be the same
proofs that work for and and or we're
just going to unravel the definitions
turn them into ands and ORS and see that
the theorems are true and we're going to
pick one of these and do it and I'll
leave de Morgan's laws for you to prove
on the problem set so right down to
Morgan's laws here you want the
complement of a union B one second don't
look what's your question these are all
unions and intersections yes you know
what I will um I'll try to make them
sharper the ends in the order so you'll
see but these are all unions and
intersections here's de Morgan's laws
that the complements of a union B is the
complement of a intersect the complement
of B let me make sure everybody knows
what this means by a picture here's a
here's B a union B is this okay
what's the complement of a union B it
it's all this stuff
union B is that the same as the
complement of a intersected with the
complement of B let's think about that
the complement of a is everything except
this whole the complements of B is
everything except that whole were those
two things intersect is every single
place except this funny binocular shape
you can go through this with pictures
and convince yourself that it's true but
we're going to prove it or you're going
to prove it on your pset by unravelling
the logic you can always do it with
pictures to convince yourself and you
can always check it with logic formally
we're going to do one of these now with
logic now let me stop for a second other
questions so far yeah Sharon this says
that if you take the union of a and B
and then you complement it that's the
same as if you complement it a
complemented B and saw what was in
common between them okay so that's this
picture let me do this picture here's a
I complement it I will there's B I'm
going to complement the B by going the
other way and where they both share
places is every place outside of that
binocular spot that's where I get cross
hatches so that picture is the same as
that picture does that make sense it
questions other questions let's do one
formal proof of this you'll see how to
do it and then let's move on to
something that's more fun
prove this particular distributive law
for sets that they distribute through
this way this is the only proof like
this we're going to do because because
they're boring and because once you know
how to do them you get the idea there's
other more fun stuff to do so let's do
it we're going to show that this is
equal to this they're equivalent rather
than do a double implication like like
we said we would do before we're just
going to take this unravel it we're
going to take this unravel it and we're
going to show that we get identical
things at the bottom
okay so we'll kind of do it
simultaneously well this is a theorem
but we have to prove that it's true now
this you could probably prove a general
theorem that if you replace any union
with an or and any and and any and with
a with an intersection that the
corresponding theorems from boolean
hounds will remain sure you probably
could do that but we're going to do this
more general than logic for many things
logics more particular and gives you
applications and circuits and various
other things and sets is more of a
mathematician way of defining bigger
objects and a data structure in computer
science what does this mean that
something is an element of a union B
intersect C what does it mean to say
that something is an elements of a union
B intersect C what does that mean
unravel that najuk Joe
good can we unravel that a little more X
is an element of a or good okay this is
what I have so far let's do a similar
thing on the other side well through a
similar thing on the other side X is an
element of a union B intersect a union C
I call on you today can you help me you
believe me huh perfect perfect Heather's
right X is an element of the first one
and X is an element of the second one
how do we unravel this Doug you want to
unravel this thing for me what does it
mean for X to be an element of a union B
going to happen here there's one more
step let's distribute this side out
using or distribute it over this end we
get X as an elements of A or X's and
elements of B and X is an element of a
or X's and elements of C at Y Wow right
these two are identical we're done all
right this is as dry as this course gets
I'm not going to do any more you'll do a
couple yourself make sure you know how
to do it you should understand that
proofs about equality's and sets are
really based on the logic that you
learned and now let's do some more stuff
about sets let me stop for questions
about this before I let this go so
Anthony asks before you know whoa we
just did the stuff by induction and we
kind of plowed into it and boom we're
supposed to do proofs by induction and
yet a some extent that's true but what
you're going to be seeing is little
little bits and pieces and examples of
proofs by induction so that when I
really get to the hey today we talk
about proofs by induction and you'll see
it from the beginning you've already had
kind of a an intuitive exposure so this
is going to happen again right now I'm
going to do another proof about sets
it's the last proof I'll do before I
talk about counting in sets and the
proof I'm going to do is an extension of
this proof but it won't involve any
logic unraveling it'll be a proof by
induction here we go
math is we'll find out all these symbols
and all this language and as I told you
before you know notation makes a big
difference and and I like to stick with
these dot dot dots until they get so
obscure we have to wrap them up into
another symbol and you'll see an example
of this today or tomorrow where the
notation makes a difference but if I can
get my notion across with dot dot dots
that I will this means if I'm going to
take a and Union it with a whole
collection of other sets that are
intersected with one another I'm just
generalizing the last theorem instead of
one set here I got n sets okay this is
like a dull grad student okay here's a
problem here's something to work on
generalize and that's the best I could
think of it's just a boring
generalization but it's true and we
should know that it's true
you can distribute over lots of things
not just one thing why is it screaming
for mathematical induction because this
is just n cases and before we did the
case where you had to write so it's
screaming for mathematical induction
there must be a nice way of just going
from one stage to the next make it nice
and clear and be done with this and get
on to something else so that's what
we're going to do we're going to prove
this by induction yes
some programming languages depending on
how old you are
also it indicates a range in some older
you know one dot n means this is the
data structure consisting of all the
values between 1 and n when you're
talking about ordered it comes up a lot
any symbol you can think of has a
meaning send some context there is
actually a common gesture in Israel
which can mean anything from you are
really bugging me wait a second - excuse
me a moment I'll be with you soon and
it's really hard to know what this is
and all all those gestures are bundled
into one single body movement which is
something that looks more or less like
this now this is so ubiquitous and
occurs everywhere in society so often
during the day and is so offensive to
most Westerners because this you know
it's typically you go into some place
you ask for service and the person's on
the phone person is supposed to serve
you so you know in this country that's a
no-no you get off the phone you sort of
the person who comes in you know and
you'll step down your wait 10 minutes
and then you'll finally excuse me and
the person with a phone on their
shoulder will look at you like this no
so look it's what does it mean it
culturally there it is not a root thing
to do at all it's completely part of the
culture it's what you do when you simply
want somebody to wait a moment and
you'll be with them so my son who went
to school there for the year I was
picking him up after school and then
he's waiting by the bus stop and I'm
yelling at him come on we're late come
on let's get out of here and he's
playing with his friends and he runs
over to me in the car and he goes and
I'm thinking oh no
but anyway it's um it's a lesson about
culture it's completely in in offensive
gesture and you have to get used to it
and you have to learn to interpret the
time that it's meant to be offensive to
the time that it isn't what does it have
to do with this nothing but now I got
your brains clear and ready to think
again so the base case is when N equals
two and we just did that before we just
did that okay that's done so now we're
going to assume that this theorem is
true for any number of B's up to N and
we just want to show that it's true if
we add one more everybody with me so far
how do we do that
we're going to assume it's true here
that's our inductive assumption we want
to be able to get from there to the next
case where we add one more B where we
make it be n plus 1 all right well let's
work with the BN plus 1 that's what we
want to prove and in working with it
whenever we need this assumption we'll
say I got it and I'll say by the
assumption so I don't like to say start
with this and work our way up I like to
start with what we're trying to prove
and then whenever we need the Assumption
reference the Assumption all right so
here's what I want to prove I want to
prove that a intersect this is going to
be a lot of drawing here a intersect B 1
B 2 up to BN plus 1 equals a union B 1
intersect a union B 2 dot dot dot a in B
and plus 1 that's what I'd like to prove
prove this now right is this true or not
do we have anything that's going to help
us we got a lot that's going to help us
here the one thing we have that lets us
distribute through here with sets is
what we have one rule that we already
proved that lets us distribute with sets
what is it you can expand it out if it
has two things in it right a so instead
of having this be n plus one via let's
turn it into two pieces this is the same
as a intersect B one intersect V two
intersect B three intersect V n
justifies that step that this is the
same as this what justifies that step we
know that intersection is associative do
we really know that I didn't 'day but
you could prove it and it's based on the
fact that ands are associative this is
because you can do things associatively
and that's the justification and you
should write that down because
intersection is associated that's how I
go from here to here but the motivation
for doing this the reason why I did this
is because I am dying to get this
parenthesis into two pieces not n plus
one pieces because I can work with it if
it has two pieces
here's piece one here's piece two by the
base case by what I did before what is
this equal and these are really are
equals right these are for sure this is
because of the associative property this
is because of the base case we want to
show that it's true for n plus 1 where
so we'll assume it's true for n but we
want to show that it's true for n plus 1
about that thing well it seems like we
were trying to
prove that it was for in in the first
case and I just changed in order that to
show that it's true for any end of the
whole world we're going to pick an N
plus one and show that if it were true
for this end then it will be true for n
plus one and that will show that it's
true for any n in the whole world if we
have a base case right so I pick this n
plus one I'm going to show that it's
true for this n plus one and in doing so
I'm going to use in the middle of my
proof somewhere the assumption that it
really does work for the one before it
you know what maybe to be easier for you
not to feel funny about it if I call
this N and I call that n minus one then
I'm proving the general case for N and
I'm assuming the n minus one case I
think it's just the question of which
one I called n but but they're both as
general as the other it's just that I
need to assume the one before it is
going to apply the one that's next what
is this equal based on the base case hey
Donna can you do that what do I get if I
distribute this out keep going I only
got two pieces here that's the only
thing I'm allowed to do b1 b2 good
this to what we're trying to get on the
right side are we close now we're very
close we're almost there
this part matches this part check check
if we can get the rest of this to match
the rest of the part before then we're
done how do we get that to happen that's
what we can assume by induction we can
assume by induction that a intersect B 1
up to BN is equal to a union B 1
intersect a union B 2 all the way
intersect a union B n so I can take this
and in its place I'll be able to put in
that I'm not going to finish writing
this proof now because it's boring me to
death
you finish writing this out say last
step by induction this piece equals that
which is identical to this write it out
in English make sure you understand that
part who thinks yeah
with two then it's true for you
we know that it's true for two and this
argument shows how to go from two to
three and we can use the argument again
to show how to go from three to four so
Shannon this shows us that if we're
trying to prove that it's true for three
say n plus one is three if you want to
show that it's true for three I've just
done it as long as you grant me that it
was true for two that's what I've done
in this argument I've shown you that I
can prove that this formula is true for
this number being three as long as you
grant me the fact that it's true for one
n is two but we know it's true for N
equals two so this argument runs through
and now I know it's true for B 1 B 2 B 3
but if I know it's true for B 1 B 2 B 3
I can go through this argument again and
this time I'll make this floor and since
I know it's true for B 3 when I get to
this point
I'll have that it's true for before also
this is an argument that shows me how to
get from one step to the next step all
right
a little better maybe not almost ok this
that's the whole idea of induction is
that is that you concentrate on this
step I want to point out what if I said
unravel this logically it'd be an uglier
proof right you'd have dot dot dots
through all your proof you'd have to go
through the same kind of dot dot dot in
the ands and ORS and we maybe we didn't
even prove it for ands and ORS I mean
you just it's a little neater to do this
by induction this is a screaming for
induction kind of proof I should say
that sub proofs are not screaming by
induction did ha did tara do this did
she show you the sum of the first n
squares she didn't show you that all
right she did show you that she had a
formula for this
but it's the most unnatural way to prove
this formula you know what this formula
equals here's what it equals
one was pretty logical right I gave you
a geometric way to look at it I gave you
a counting way to look at it I gave you
a bowling pin way to look at it later
today I'm going to give you another way
to look at this formula you can figure
out this formula by thinking about it
how many people if I give you 10 minutes
and ask you how to add up the first n
square is going to come up with this
twisted formula if you really know about
comment of two arcs you might guess it
but you're not going to guess it if
you're just a regular old Joe off the
street it's just not obvious you can
prove this by induction and still have
no idea why it's true I could prove to
you that if this is true I could get to
the next step and the next step remains
true it should be a little algebra and n
plus 1 square to the side add it to the
side rearrange the terms see if you get
n plus 1 times n plus 2 times two
parenthesis n plus 1 plus 1 it's just
that ugly boring it's the worst
inductive proof I can think of it's just
it just ruins the whole idea what if I
said here's the sums of the numbers from
1 to N squared and I say come up with
that formula if you could prove things
by induction you'd still be dead because
you wouldn't know what the formula is
you can do lots of examples and maybe
guess at the formula maybe you might
have a way of guessing at it there's
lots of good ways to guess at it but you
might be dead in the water so there's
another way to prove this the way that
most people proved it back in 1300 when
induction was a new idea they would
prove things like this inductively they
would prove things like this inductively
but they would do things like this the
way they discovered the formula they
would show you the actual constructive
way where this formula came from and
I'll do that maybe later today maybe
tomorrow but I'll show you a bit much
better proof that really strips away the
magic behind this formula saying all
that it's still kind of cool that if you
know how to prove things by induction
and you happen to guess this right that
you can prove it's true even though you
don't know what's going on that's
powerful that's a really powerful idea
there's going to be a time when we talk
about that seven rings problem we're
going to try to catch
how many moves does it take to solve
that problem we're going to come up with
a recursive formula we're going to do
some tables we're not going to be able
to guess any formula but we're going to
notice that there's a really simple
relationship between one number and the
next number in the table that like it
doubles and gets added by one and we're
going to use that relationship prove it
by induction figure out the formula in a
backhanded way all because we know how
to prove things by induction so it can
go the other direction too sometimes
noticing things step by step is the way
to go sometimes seeing the big picture
is the way to go and don't ask me how do
you know which one is best because
that's what makes mathematicians feel
they're special okay if you're good then
you have the right intuition and it
takes years and years to get the right
intuition yeah jump you can assume that
why can you choose the associate
property on these on your assumption to
prove it out that way what do you mean
you uh you mean I could go up to b1 to
the BN minus one here you come down
there here we add the 3 n minus n plus 1
yeah yeah to do this yet well if you can
assume the annuity property says your
property is true why don't you just do
it with your assertion and show you with
your split ever it is you're assuming
the I'm assuming that's right why do you
have to go down the end B to the n plus
1 and you can just use the associative
property or what you're assuming I can't
use it to prove that it's true the only
thing I can do with the associative
property is parenthesize sets of
intersections in any way I want as long
as they stay in order and that's what I
did here I could parenthesize these to
my heart's content till the cows came
home and I wouldn't be any closer to to
getting this proof I could do this up to
be n minus 1 and it doesn't do me any
good
understand why you have to go approve
the n plus one step if you can just
prove it prove what you're assuming you
can't prove it you can't there's no
assumption that says that a union B 1 B
2 B 3 that you can distribute it out
over all the pieces you can soon based
on the base keys you can do it over -
right you can do it over two pieces so
if you break that first B to the end to
the one you win into these two pieces
that's an S then this equals a Union
this intersect a Union that and then
you'd have to break this and do this
again and do it again and do it again
that's kind of doing induction backwards
you're starting with your case and
you're wounded all the way down to the
base case and this is just going forward
it's the same idea you have the right
idea that's the right idea except that
here I just went forward from n to n
plus one and you're thinking of taking n
and working your way back until you get
to the base case but you'd still have to
do all those steps the key thing is
showing the connection between the end
step and the step before it or previous
steps before it still not oh I can maybe
address this later maybe if it's more
helpful okay so now we can put that away
cuz I don't like these proofs they're
boring ok I want to talk about counting
a little bit and counting that us to do
with sets and this for me this is a
little more interesting and and at least
gets us to a different part of where
sets come up in computer science and
that's to do with counting oh here's a
great example where the book leaves this
for a chapter four chapters down that
it's in the counting chapter even though
it's something that has to do with sets
and I just think that's a bad idea I
think they should do it here the most
interesting thing about sets as far as
discrete math goes is something called
the inclusion exclusion theorem this
theorem is so naturally inductive and so
logical for
the base case and has so much to do with
counting that I think you should see it
here before you forget all about sets
because it's the neatest thing about
sets that relates to combinatorics
here's what the theorem says in the
simplest version it says let's say you
have two sets and B and you want to know
how many you want to know how many
different elements are combined in a and
B together in a union B here's how we
would write that when you put vertical
lines around a set that means how many
elements are in that set that's
sometimes called the cardinality of the
set so if you want to know how many
elements there are in a union B you tell
me let's be a little more interactive
and I want a wrong answer here I'm going
to write a wrong answer right why is
that wrong because they overlap right if
they didn't overlap that would be right
right but they overlap so that's not
right
such a key idea in counting one of the
key tricks and counting remember this
there are I would say in counting
there's some ABCs you have to learn and
then there's two big tricks and these
tricks can be so subtle and twist it out
of shape in so many ways you won't even
recognize them as the same trick but
they are the same trick two tricks and
Counting trick number one if you're
trying to count something you can't
count it count the stuff you're not
interested in
I asked you guys to read that birthday
paper that I wrote remember you're
trying to calculate how many different
birthdays where everybody's got
different birthdays that's hard right
but if you count the stuff you're not
interested in hey how many birthdays
everybody's got the same that is
something you can count it's easier to
count sometimes the complement of what
you're trying to count so if you're
having a hard time counting something
count the complement that's one trick
check number two count double or
multiple times in a controlled way
that's the second kind of trick that
you'll see I would say that almost every
trick in combinatorics can be based on
the ABCs that I'll teach you
permutations combinations and
combinations of these two tricks this
trick is the one we're going to talk
about right now number two and I'm going
to give you a simple example of it then
we're going to go back to this example
remember the triangle number is 1 plus 2
Plus 3 plus 4 up to n we figured out a
million ways of proving that formula 1
is I counted it out you know Mike goes
with everybody else and then and then
Chris goes with everybody else except
Mike you know so that's n n plus 1 and n
minus 1 n minus 2 etc down to one we did
in another way where we geometrically
shifted the things around here's another
way to do it every single person in the
class can go with every other single
person in the class except themselves
right so if there's 36 people in this
class every one of you can be matched
with how many other people 35 other
people that's fine but that means I
counted dog going with Anthony and
Anthony going with Doug twice right in
fact every single pair in that list of
combining each one of you with each of
the other ones was counted exactly twice
once from person a's point of view once
from person B's point of view so all I
have to do is take that n times n plus 1
as I counted each value twice from what
I really care about and divided by two
now I'm back to what I want everybody
see what I mean by count double in a
controlled way if I know that I'm
counting in a particular way that
doubles everything I really want to
count that I can count that way as long
as I divide by two when I'm done I think
in this example you can really see it in
a simple way and you'll see the same
simple idea here in inclusion/exclusion
and this idea you'll see in so many more
complicated ways that make sure you get
it here because it'll make sense here if
you give it a little time and it won't
make sense in the complicated ways
unless you get the basic way down first
Donna it would be it would be right to
say n times n times what a polite woman
huh I went at a student who said I was
writing some program some C program up
on the board like 15 years ago and I put
a bracket in the wrong place and this
guy was a bit of a jerk and he raised
his hand and he go
is that a formal parameter or do you
mean an actual parameter there I didn't
know what he was talking about I didn't
notice this bracket and I just sat there
going I don't know I'm not sure what you
mean and we went back and forth like
this for 10 minutes just kill in the
class and and finally I go what are you
getting at he goes because I just never
seen a formal parameter really written
at that particular spot in the program
and after a long time he finally said
did you mean to put the bracket there
and I didn't look I go give me a break
shut up but Donna's like the opposite
she goes excuse me but did you just make
a complete error there and write
buzinova Donnie or riot it's n times n
minus 1 / - you're right
I made a mistake thank you thank you
it's the sum of the first sum of the
first n minus 1 right because because
when Michael starts he can connect with
n minus 1 people and then when Chris
goes next he can connect with n minus 2
people that are left and we go all the
way down to 1 so it only goes up to n
minus 1 if you have a class of n okay
let's go back here we said this is wrong
and Anthony already yelled out the
answer before he was right that the
reason it's wrong is because we have
counted what double right look at that
nice control boom boom I'm dominating
this guy I know just what we counted
double it's not some weird thing we
counted double we counted this area
double this stuff got counted once this
like but stuff like a kept put mumuga
got counted once that stuff got counted
double so how do we fix it subtract it
out and then you'll only count it once
this is the inclusion/exclusion theorem
in the case of two sets now I have to
tell you that there's an inclusion
exclusion theorem in the case of three
sets and four sets and five sets at any
number of sets and when you get past
three there's no drawing it on the board
for three I can still draw it on the
board and the way you prove this and I'm
not going to prove it cuz it's a hairy
notation but how do you prove this kind
of thing it's screaming induction right
I mean it's it you're proved it very
similar to what I did before you use the
base case to start out you take n sets
you associate them so you get two pieces
a one to a and then the n plus one set
and then you use your base case to get
this and then you it's much uglier than
what I did before but you can do it I'm
not going to do it the book does it you
can look it up you can see it I'm not
going to ask you to do it but it can be
done and it's a classic proof by
induction but what is the theorem we
haven't even said what the theorem is
much less prove it so let's talk about
the theorem let's do a couple
applications of it just looking at his
watch but we started really late today
that dollar change you brought me
yesterday that's it
succotash for everybody all right no
more counting double now we got three
sets we're moving up how do you figure
out how many things are in the
collection of the union of three sets
let's start again with the same wrong
idea this is not a joke a lot of times
in math you start with a wrong idea
because you got a better chance fixing
something that's close
then you do sitting there waiting for
the light to go off in your head and I'm
completely serious don't sit there
waiting for the light to go off in your
head unless you see it somewhere in the
distance like down the subway line if
you see something coming you see you
have an idea you just got to work it out
fine but don't sit there thing I have no
idea to do this do something wrong and
fix it and and that's not a joke that
really works you can often make progress
by doing something wrong and then
figuring out what's wrong in it so you
know this is wrong you know that's wrong
because they overlap so how do we fix it
this is counted how many times twice
this is counted twice this is counted
twice all those things are counted twice
right not exactly right what about that
little teeny piece inside this is
counted twice this little piece here
this cross it this is kind of twice this
is counted twice how many times lots of
times
oh it gets really hairy well here's a
perfect opportunity to give you a sense
of how a mathematician would think
there's two ways here do we just go
ahead and start subtracting these off
and see how far off we are that and
continue like we did last time or do we
try to figure out how many times was
this counted is it two or six right over
three or six everybody's got a different
idea there's two different directions
which way do you go right well I'm not
going to tell you because nobody's going
to tell you in real life when you're
working on a math problem and I'll tell
you the truth either way would be okay
the way that I think is going to get us
to the answer faster is to do what we
did before is to notice that these
little crescents were counted twice and
let's take them off and let's see what's
still missing so a intersect B is taken
off what else intersect C and B
intersect C
this part was taken off right this part
was taken off right this part was taken
off right but we took that middle part
off too many times how many times did we
take it off we took it off three times
we got to put one another think we need
to put two back because we counted this
guy twice but we took we need to put it
back once it's a little tricky you've
counted it three times and you're taking
it away three times so you have to put
it back one suppose you want to come
that's that's excellent
good Sam just saved me some brain powers
because they're thinking of I don't know
but I'm going they're thinking of this
they're thinking of this being once that
being twice and they're thinking maybe
there's six different ways that you
overlap here but there's really only
three doug is asking what why are people
making a natural okay write this formula
that i have here for three is right
let's see if we could you have a
question Andrew yeah that's you would do
that that's how you'd prove it you would
and then you go back to the two case but
we're not going to prove it but you
would do that that's exactly how you
prove it and you repeat it it his his
question was why don't we turn B and C
into a new set and call a D and then
just use what we did before and see what
happens and he's exactly right and
that's exactly what induction is all
about and if we had n plus one sets we
turn n of them into one set and use the
original formula and but there'd be a
lot of notation and unraveling and
manipulation to see what actually works
but that's exactly what you do why don't
we look
there's a nice way to do it what happens
if we're going to add more sets it's
hard to actually write this theorem out
so I'm going to have to describe it to
you let's do it with four what do you
think happens you start out with all the
single stats add it together you
subtract off all the all the pair's you
add on all the triples and you subtract
off the single all the one there's one
quadruple write the quadruple you
alternate plus and minus you start with
the single sets you move on to the
double sets you go on to the triples of
the sets and then the end of the set
that's the general rule this is just
dying to hint towards counting how many
of these single ones are there well if
you have n sets there are n of these how
many of these are there n times n minus
1 over 2 it's the number of ways I can
pick two people from a group number of
ways I can pick two sets from a set of n
people just like sending you guys out to
do the xeroxing in pairs so there's
going to be about n squared of these
pairs and squared minus n over 2 so you
giving me that look like you're cooking
what what are you thinking about what
are you saying is in money the number of
pairs so in this case where n equals 3 3
times 2 divided by 2 equals 3 that's how
many sets of pairs that are not 2 sub
just how many of these terms are there
how many ways can I pick 2 sets from a
collection of 3 I can pick a B I can
pick a C I can pick B C I'm just talking
about how many of these terms are going
to be no no
all right you write it like this that's
the number of ways you can choose two
things from three things 3 choose 2 3
choose 2 you say this is way ahead these
are called binomial coefficients this is
a week and a half from where we are now
this is just a little preview but make
sure you get this theorem I want to do a
couple applications of this theorem
because it seems like ok well so what
there are an amazing amount of difficult
problems that you can just manhandle
with this theorem and I'm going to do a
couple of very simple ones today and
when we get into the counting week I'll
do much harder ones let me give you an
example of one that's much harder that I
won't do today but it's a famous one you
all come to class and you all bring your
lunch ok and you all give me because I
told you to because I'm not treating
it's a lot of different ways I could
have given the lunches back we're not
talking about how to count that right
now but of all the ways that I could
give the lunches back how many of them
result in nobody getting their own lunch
back no there's lots
right right right there's lots of ways
for me to give the lunches back so that
nobody gets their particular lunch they
handed me
that's called a derangement because it's
it's raised evident there really is it's
called a derangement it actually has
applications in particular areas and
discrete math and solving it one really
cool way to solve it is where the
inclusion exclusion theorem alright so
that's a hard problem that uses
inclusion exclusion let's do an easy
problem let's do an easy problem
computer scientists
there it's a range anywhere from 3 to 12
people total alright let's do a picture
computer scientists there's 10 smart
people there's 5 computer scientists
there's 12 people all together so the
union of these two together is 12 the
number of smart people is 10 the number
of computer scientists is 5 this 12 is a
union B a is a number of smart people
visa number computer scientists I have
to subtract off the number of people who
are both smart and computer scientists
smart computer scientists so what's the
answer
universe the universe another of our
people - I didn't you're kind of done
that's all
the total number of people in this whole
universe is 12 that's there's nothing
there there there maybe jus that maybe
one that maybe zero but I'm trying to
tell you that there's none I'm trying to
I'm trying to imply that there are 12
people total that are eight that are
just here there's nobody outside of this
you know that 10 of them are smart five
of them are computer scientists then
this guy has to be three right we
require simulation of their know what
not smart yes it requires a stipulation
that all the people all the people are
either smart or computer scientists in
this universe or both right right there
are no right yes yes yes right there's
12 people in my universe ten of them are
smart five of them are computer
scientists how many of them are both
oh you're right I have to say that there
are no people that are that are dumb non
computer scientists you're right I do
me give you another problem it's a
little bit less arbitrary here this is a
good one how many numbers from 1 to 21
same question with one two twenty one
thousand one way to do this problem is
just to go ahead and and check how many
numbers are divisible by three or seven
between one and twenty one right the
truth 3 6 9 12 15 18 21 and 7 14 right
so 9 all together all right
inclusion exclusion for it but now I
bump up the ante how many numbers
between 1 and 21,000 are divisible by 7
really just 9,000 I don't want 2,000
times and that they're going to be 900
it is too easy yeah I let you I led you
to a way to do it that doesn't require
the technique that I wanted I'll do it
my way anyway all right I want to do it
my way where you really feel you need my
way so here's the way you all forget
numbers oh no all right divisible by
here we'll do three or five or seven and
between one and say a thousand now we're
cooking I want just to give you an
example where inclusion exclusion is a
natural thing to try to do one way to do
this is to numerate all the numbers from
1 to 1,000 and try another way to do it
is the way we just try try to find a
smaller interval and then expand out
that's a clever way let's do it by a
brute-force inclusion/exclusion way and
see how that works here are the numbers
divisible by 3 here are the numbers
divisible by 5 and here are the numbers
divisible by 7 okay if you want to have
how many numbers divisible by 3 or 5 or
that's the case of the three set
inclusion/exclusion theorem take all the
numbers that are divisible by three add
the numbers divisible by five and the
numbers divisible by seven subtract the
numbers divisible by three and five
subtract the numbers divisible by three
and seven subtract the numbers divisible
by five and seven add the numbers
divisible by three five and seven all
right well what good is this this is a
classic example of counting the opposite
if you can't count what you want we
can't count easily three or five or
seven but three and five and seven on
three and five the ands are always
easier to count the ORS ands are easier
to count the ORS let's see why we'll get
to these ands or intersections in a
second and you'll see why they're easier
to count but let's go through this and
get numbers here a is 3 B is 5 C is 7
how many ways how many numbers are
divisible by 3 between 1 and a thousand
you just divide a thousand into three
parts
that's a division problem so 333 number
divisible by 5 200 number divisible by 7
that part's easy now how many numbers
are divisible by both a B that means
both 3 & 5
if you divisible by 3 and you divisible
by 5 then you're divisible by if and
only if so all you got to do is divide
by 15 and Tsar easier to count than ORS
almost always so one of the things that
the inclusion exclusion theorem is
showing you is when you have to do
things by ORS look for a way of dividing
it into pieces that are all made up out
of ends and that's just what the theorem
does so once a thousand divided by 15
thank you and now we have to divide by
Oh
21 and we have to subtract off another a
thousand divided by 35 and we got to add
on how many numbers are divisible by all
three that means by a thousand over 105
there's nine if you add all these up did
you do it I must have done it
come 533 633 676 75605 43 math by
democracy what the answer is at 543
let's make sure we get it right five for
this 543 for the record is it 534 Rob we
have to have at least we have to have a
quorum of three who agree it definitely
ends in three I just added up the the
unit's digit so I know it ends in three
inclusion exclusion theorem can be used
for all sorts of complicated things like
that the arrangement problem I showed
you but you should know what it is and
you should be willing this is a
completely as an example more examples
of test questions this question a
simpler version of this question is a
question that is perfectly fine for a
time test a question of truth tables and
showing equivalences between them is
fine for exams if you can do the problem
set one and you've got the basic idea on
all these kind of questions you're just
kind of you're just going to shrug your
shoulders and say okay why was I so
anxious okay if you're not sure about
problems that one then you've got a lot
of work to do and for my sense as most
of you really aren't quite sure yet and
right need somewhere right yes should
the beginning of problem set choose this
stuff yes so the beginning of home set
two is also covered yes yes I mentioned
that before you should definitely look a
problem set to in order to help you
prepare and talk about those on Sunday
absolutely
sure absolutely yeah what oh no I'm no
of course right I mean look these
problem sets are due every two three
days right but if the idea is for you
guys to learn if there's somebody who
needs me to actually go through every
single solution to every problem until
you finally discover it up until more or
less the end then we're going to do that
I mean most of the time that's not