um so we're on for let's see five so if
we have our our base set being the
integers then there's a relation and
Fries going to get into these a little
bit more when he starts talking about a
little bit of number theory so there's a
relationship equivalence modulo 3 this
means so two numbers are equivalent
modulo three if they have the same
remainder when you divide them by three
so
equivalent modulo 3 so this is not in
equivalents modulo 3 1 & 4 would be as
would 9 333 everybody understand this
relation yeah so we could write this as
1 is equivalent to 2 mod 3 that's
another way to write this or I guess you
could even say no right so in this case
we could write 9 is equivalent to 333
notations this is the more usual
notation this is not so
talk about was subset relations so if a
as a set of sets let's say and all the
subsets of one two three then the subset
relation is the relation that says this
subset is a subset of this other subset
so for example one is the subset of one
three and I guess the more usual way of
writing this we would say one is a
subset of one three and two is not a
subset of one three
really bad notation actually I shouldn't
have even done this but I just changed
it to the normal subset notation so okay
so does everybody understand what a
relation is so what the Cross means is
ordered pairs of elements of the set and
they're ordered exactly because we might
have a case where a comma B is in the
set of become a is not so this is the
same cross we've seen before
yep so this cross is just ordered pairs
a comma B where a and B are in a yep yep
this allows a a
maybe usually easier to think of our
relations of these dots and arrows
rather than in terms of these ordered
pairs I personally prefer the ordered
pairs in fact Prolog uses relationships
in exactly this way in terms of ordered
pairs and we talked about Prolog at the
very beginning I don't remember if
anyone remembers but essentially in
Prolog you can define relations you can
just say okay here are some relations
and here are the things that satisfy
these relations go find my answer to
this really hard convoluted problem and
it just sort of recursively searches
through all your relations and somehow
magically finds the right thing at the
end so that's kind of cool
so so if a so Chris is asking if we have
just the set a equals one two three
right then in this case we couldn't well
the only so if we consider the sub is a
subset of relation on this set the only
element of it I mean it doesn't really
make sense because is if subset means
that this must be a set or this must be
a set or this must be a set so if we
think of those as sets then we get into
yeah right so the relationship I mean it
doesn't make sense I couldn't define a
relationship on the set one two three is
a sibling of because it doesn't make
sense to ask whether two is a sibling of
three or not so the relation has to make
sense in your universe whatever
universes and in this case if we just
have a set a equals one two three then
is a subset of doesn't make sense on the
universe of one two and three unless
you're a set theorist but we won't go
there
so are there any other questions about
relations to was not a subset of 1 comma
3 right right right so this this is not
in the relation but each of these is a
subset of 1 2 3 no it's just the sixth
yeah yep the empty set we could put you
know the empty set is a subset of
everything so the empty set comma 1 3
that's certainly in our relation does
that make sense so far
okay so people have already noticed some
properties of subsets so when we saw the
parent relation bill was a parent of
Michael but Michael wasn't a parent of
Bill when we saw the sibling
relationship Andy was a sibling of Chris
and also Chris was a sibling of Andy so
that's one thing that we could that may
or may not be true of our relation R is
symmetric if well if a comma B is in the
relation then so is a comma a so if a is
related to B then B is also related to a
well say it's antisymmetric if that's
not true so I guess I should be more
careful if for every okay so r is
antisymmetric
not an R and this is when a Sonic
wouldn't be for every a B so this is if
for every and of course it wouldn't make
sense if a it was equal to B because
then we would be saying if a comma a as
an R then a comma a is not an R and so
we just restrict ourselves to the case
when a is different from B ok so it's
symmetric and the parent relation is
antisymmetric unless you're from West
Virginia and we just don't want to know
ginger yeah even I mean I guess that's
parents yeah I guess parent will be
pretty much be not symmetric so we yeah
sibling is symmetric less than or equal
to well that's hard to say because so
because well five is strictly less than
six and six is not less than five but
five is less than or equal to five and
five is less than or equal to five so
it's neither symmetric Nouri
antisymmetric well maybe it is
anti-symmetric I said one a is not equal
to B
yeah so less than or equal to is
antisymmetric
is equivalent to two yeah so equivalence
modulo 3 is symmetric okay
another property of relations so a
are for every day okay so let's see I
because my number has the same remainder
as itself modulo 3 so yeah so is less
than or equal to
because it's not strictly less than
itself and let's see parent and sibling
are both well I guess it depends on how
you define sibling if you define sibling
to be has the same parents as then
you're maybe you have the same parents
as yourself so maybe your sibling of
yourself I guess that's a matter of
personal taste we call sibling reflexive
or not that's too bad we'll see why in a
minute
why we might want sibling to be
reflexive so this is by vote what that's
true so so let's see sibling is not
reflexive neither as parent again unless
you're in some bad time traveling movie
so it's not okay the last relation the
last property little relation might have
and this is maybe the most important
well maybe not I don't know which is the
most important is transitivity relation
complicated so if a comma B and B comma
C are in the relationships and so is B
comma C a comma C good okay so now
there's a question I guess if I guess
you have to now be careful if we had C
equal to a and our relationship was
symmetric and transitive and it would
also have to be reflexive so a for
relations well before we do this let's
think about some other things so let's
see less than this then is certainly
transitive because if a is less than B
and B is less than C then a is less than
C that's sort of how we define less than
or equal to
so if a is a parent of B & B is a parent
of C that means a is a grandparent of C
not the parent of C so parents it's not
transitive
think at first thought so you know this
now depends on how we define siblings so
if Andy's a brother of Chris and Chris
is a brother of Andy that would apply
the Andy's a brother of Andy and so
there's this question now for there's
your half sisters
yeah I guess where we mean strict
siblings so sibling question marks
Chris and Chris Andy and this would
imply Andy Andy yeah I mean if we if in
this case if we require that a is not
equal to C then it will be transitive
transitive
a it's not equal to B it's not equal to
C then sure sibling is transitive so
that would make more sense what else I
guess equivalents modulo 3 is transitive
because if 1 is equivalent to 4 and 4 is
equivalent to 13 then one's also
equivalent to 13 so these are basically
relations are there any questions about
relations so far I've only talked about
relations with one set to itself you can
also talk about and I don't know if I
wrote anything in the notes about this
or not
sets and then this met this well okay so
if we have a set a and set B then a
relation would be a subset of a cross B
and in this case it's almost certainly
easier to think of
much easier to think of here's a here's
B and here's a bunch of arrows so this
is just another way to represent our
relation and they're in fact the same
thing because you're ordered pairs are
just the one thing here and the thing
that it points to over here so we can
also compose relations so if I have a
relation from A to B and then a relation
to C like this I now can think of the
composed relation from A to C simply by
first following an arrow from A to B and
then following an arrow from A to C so
I'm actually really only going to want
to think of these in terms of one
relation to itself so if R is a relation
on a then R squared is also a relation
on a
B and become a CR in our so what's the
square of the parent relationship we'd
have to have a as a parent of B&BS a
parent of C so that'd be the grandparent
relationship
wanted to talk about I forgot to write
this in the notes so so there's some
relationships like parents that are not
transitive
but transitive relations are somehow
really nice and non-transitive ones are
kind of a pain and so somehow it would
be nice to take a relationship that
wasn't transitive and find some other
relation that contain that relation that
was transitive so
closure of a relationship so the
transitive closure of a relation is the
smallest relation I haven't talked about
how one relation contains another so one
relation is compatible with another if
in the first relation well in the in the
bigger relation if everything that was
compatible in the first relation is
still related or compatible in the
second relation so before I finish this
definition
well maybe I'll finish this and then
clarify so over the transitive closure
of a relation is a bigger relation that
is transitive so let's call this one R
and the bigger relation TCR that is
transitive
and contains all the relationships
ancestor and/or descendant of maybe just
as an ancestor of yeah so it contains
all the relationships that were in your
original set are so what do I mean by
say are is contained in TC of our and
since these are subsets that that makes
sense what does that mean well that
means is if you know I have this this
new relation and why what I want is that
everything that was related in the old
relation is still related in the new
relation so it's Chris noted the
transitive closure is a parent of is
certainly an ancestor of their child it
sounds a little weird I mean the
ancestors are supposed to be dead but
strictly a parent is an ancestor of a
child and so our original relations are
respected
is an ancestor of me and God who knows
the Queen of Spain is an ancestor of
Martha Washington then the Queen of
Spain is also an ancestor of me
so it's transitive not that that's any
of those sorry in the relationship but
that's okay
so does transitive closure make sense
good how can you determine analyst
yes that's supposed to be the smallest
bigger relation what does that mean
well there's a couple ways to find this
could just take our relation so neither
of these is computationally very useful
but I'm a mathematician so I somehow
want to at least have some way of
computing these things okay so the next
thing I want to talk about is
equivalence relations and well it's
unclear to me whether equivalence so
equivalence relations and partial orders
are both really useful and I don't know
which is more useful so equivalence
relations okay so an equivalence
relation is supposed to be one that's
transitive and symmetric and reflexive
idea is it might be that well depends
how we define transitive if we define
transitive as I originally defined it
with you know yeah then it's yeah so
this may or may not be redundant if you
right yeah may be symmetric and
transitive are complete but we throw a
reflexive in there just to make
ourselves happy so actually maybe it's
not even redundant well anyway so the
idea is is that what we see equivalent
so this is some house busting model
equals and these are somehow supposed to
be the three most important properties
of equals I mean certainly equals is
reflexive because X is equal to X it's
certainly symmetric if X is equal to Y
then Y is also equal to X and it's also
a transitive if X is equal to Y and y is
equal to Z then X is equal to Z so
properties
name equivalents yeah using the family
of or is in the ancestral line over
isn't the lineage of does that we mean
something like that yeah there's there's
some question of whether we can say this
for any of our actual relationships I
guess we define a person to be a sibling
of his or her self him or herself then
sibling would be but so if we just say
is in the family of and we're not very
specific then we'll be fine
all of our properties and which examples
satisfied them of course another
property that was satisfied was or
another relation that satisfied these
was equivalents modulo 3 so equivalents
modulo 3 was certainly reflexive because
if one was cloned 4 then 4 was also hurt
sorry 1 is equivalent to itself mod 3 1
has this any number has the same
remainder as itself modulo 3 it's
symmetric because if one number has the
same arena modulo 3 is another number
then that other number has the same
remainder is the first number modulo 3
and it's transitive so equivalence
modulo 3 is one of these and let's
explore this guy a little more so quit
once modulo 3 we're working over the
integers and so zero was equivalent to 3
to 6 to 9 18 etc and 2 minus 3 minus 6
etc so these are this is the set of all
things equivalent to 0 if we look at the
set of all things equivalent to 1 when
we have 4 7 10 19 minus 2 minus 5 dot
dot dot if I look at all the things
equivalent to 2
things equivalent to three I'm gonna
land back up here again because I'm
gonna get three six nine etc so this is
kind of nice in fact I have divided up
the integers into the ones that are
equivalent to zero I'm on three
equivalent to one nine three and
equivalent to two mod three party oops I
forgot oops for no reason just because I
was not counting very well see this was
supposed to be 12 was the next one yeah
have the equivalence class if you will
of zero and that I mean we sort of
divided up the integers into three
different sets there's sort of three
possibilities either it's divisible by
three or it has a remainder of one or it
has a remainder of two and that's all of
them and those are disjoint if five
appears in here it doesn't appear up
here so it turns out we can do something
like this in general when we have an
equivalence relation the equivalence
class of a an element of a so if R is an
equivalence relation then the
equivalence class
equivalent to a in this relation so a is
going to be in the equivalence class
itself because it's equivalent to itself
because an equivalence relation is
reflexive and well so this is all things
turns out that the set of equivalence
classes are a set of non empty sets that
whose Union is the entire set and
they're destroying the union of the
equivalence classes is a and the
equivalence classes are disjoint so
certainly the Union is an a because
every element today is supposed to have
an equivalence class so if we take the
Union over all of them then we get all
of a they're disjoint well because if
you have a and one equivalence class and
be in another equivalence class that's
different
well they couldn't possibly be this I
mean they couldn't possibly overlap
because of this transitivity property
let's let's prove this
easy it's sort of by definition if we
take the equivalence classes of all the
elements then of course we're going to
get everything the fact that if we have
CA and CB different then if CA
intersected CB was not empty so I want
them to be disjoint that means they have
no elements of comment suppose they do
have an element come and suppose C is in
both of them little C well it's in the
first one if C come a is in the first
one and it's in the second one if C
comma B is in the relationship so C
comma a and C some C comma B are both in
the relation furthermore I know that the
relation is symmetric so C comma a being
in the relation is the same as a comma C
being in the relation and now I have a
comma C and C comma B in the relation so
this is by symmetry and now I combine
these two by transitivity to get that a
means that B must be in C sub a and a
mus B and C sub E and therefore they
must I mean they're equivalent and so
they're equivalence classes are actually
the same so
season ANC's would be we're different so
if contradiction art contradicted our
assumption I read a contradiction that
land not exactly the hungarians right
contradictions that way and i studied
math and hungary and so i don't know why
they write them that way yeah it's it's
the same symbol that they have on all
their you know beware of electricity
electric things there and so i don't
know why they use it but they do so this
completes the proof okay so does that
make sense
are there any questions add three
equivalence classes and there's lots
more nice math to say about that but i
won't go there because it could take
years so so if anyone is interested in
equivalence classes and that kind of
things i mean they're useful in well
they're useful in computer science
because if things are equivalent then
it's much easier to deal with
equivalence classes of sets then then
the big set you start with maybe just
love for whatever reason then used to
sort of greatly reduce your problem to a
much smaller one they pop up all over
the place in other math as well and so
that's sort of the idea so these reduced
classes and that can be useful this
makes probably smaller yes yes that one
is reducible to the other in polynomial
time so there'd be an equivalence class
of problems okay the last thing I want
to talk about today with partial orders
so and I'm probably leaving something
out and I'll remember it and I'll tell
you tomorrow because I always do okay so
now we're moving on to partial orders
order is another kind of another kind of
relation rather so a partial order
and transitive so one of the examples we
had earlier was is less than or equal to
or less strictly less than I guess if we
want to be careful so less than is a
is a total order every two so a partial
order and I don't want to go here it's
actually a total order and if you want
to know about that come ask me later so
less than is a partial order simply
because well if a is less than B then B
is not less than a it's greater than a
and so it's antisymmetric and it's
transitive because if a is less than B
and B is less than C then a is also less
than C so it satisfies both these
properties so it's a partial order
we let a be subsets of 1 2 3 then
subsets or equal to is also a partial
order on this set
it whether or not it should be proper
subset or not and I'm gonna say
always use this notation when they
really mean this and let's just use that
I guess anti-symmetric doesn't say
anything about whether or not
something's reflexive because
anti-symmetric remember meant that if a
comma B was in the set then become a was
not and this was for a not equal to B so
if we leave the equal sign there then
it's okay because certainly a said as a
subset of itself but then the anti
symmetry law doesn't come into effect
because a is equal to a little a okay so
that are partial orders there's another
example that we'll talk about in a
minute but first I want to talk about
hasa diagrams so hasa diagrams hasa
diagrams are way of ways of drawing our
partial ordered sets I guess a partially
ordered set oops I should have written
that down so a partially ordered set or
a post set is a set with a partial
ordering
ordered set is I represent each element
by a vertex or a dot and I represent the
relations by lines between them but my
lines sort of always go in one direction
because it's anti-symmetric and so if I
have a line one direction then I don't
have a line in the other direction but
what I'm actually going to do is not
include all the transitive relations so
I can write down all my subsets of one
two three
of 1 2 and a 1 3 and it's also a subset
of 1 2 3 but that is sort of implied by
the fact that it's a subset of this and
this is a subset of that so I don't
include the all of the lines I just
include sort of the minimal ones to make
this complete so the transitive lines
would be things like this this this this
this and this and so I could draw those
in but those extra red lines are implied
by the white lines that are there
already or the ivory lines that are
there already and so there's no reason
to well yeah I mean if we wanted to be
particularly complete we could include
them but in fact the ivory lines are
enough because we know the other ones
must be there by transitivity
example is if you look at it at the
right angle it looks like the hypercube
and in fact if you you know any you can
get a picture of the hypercube of any
dimension simply by taking this the
subsets of an n-element set because as
we know that well so the hypercube is
supposed to have vertices corresponding
to binary strings and those are supposed
to be in one-to-one correspondence with
subsets of a set of an N element set and
so at least they're gonna have the same
number vertices and it turns out that
the way we draw these hostile diagrams
the edges also agree so let's see
there's a lot to say about partial order
sets I in fact in college took whole
class on them so I'm obviously not going
to tell you everything there is to know
about them but the question is how much
to tell you
partly what's partially about it okay so
that now comes back to why so drugs
acting why are they called partial
orderings it sort of made sense to call
the equivalence relations equivalence
relations because they were similar to
equals but this you know what's a
partial well why do we call a partial
ordering so that sort of goes back to
what it means to be a total order a
total order
antisymmetric and and transitive and for
every pair of elements a and B either a
B is in your set or B a is in your set
so in your relation either so either a
assumed antisymmetric and so an example
of a total ordering is less than because
each two elements each pair of numbers
are comparable we can say this one is
less than this one you know 5 is less
than 6 or 3 is less than 5 so so this is
a total ordering
comparable comparable this is a partial
ordering so a partial ordering we sort
of lose the fact that every two pairs
every pair has to be comparable over
here let's see we have one and two three
in this case one and two three we can't
compare them one's not a subset of 2/3
and 2/3 is not a subset of one and so in
a partial ordering we may or may not be
able to compare every pair of elements
so that's where partial comes from Brian
here's another real-world example of a
partial ordering this dates back to
World War Two and this was in fact when
partial orderings were sort of first
studied mathematically and this is why a
lot of funding for common tourists to
study partial orderings comes from the
Office of Naval Research which seems
sort of weird but consider the following
problem so suppose you have a whole
bunch of routes that need to be covered
by airplanes you have to get cargo
you're you're trying to get missiles or
food or whatever you're trying to get a
from island island island you know say
you have five islands and each flight
takes a certain amount of time and well
this isn't a very good way to draw the
problem okay so suppose you you have a
certain schedule of flights so how
should I best draw this maybe this way
Hawaii to god-knows-where somewhere else
in the Pacific and
flight to somewhere else and so we have
sort of all these intervals of time that
have to be covered by a flight so the
question is you know how many well I
mean of course our our our actual order
will be much more complicated than this
because we'd have so we have something
like this and we can we can order these
intervals so this is called an interval
order we can order two intervals if
one's strictly less than the other so we
got a point for each interval so here's
our lowest one and then this was well
there were two more that overlapped it
and so they aren't lower than it and
they aren't higher than it let's call
these one two three so the question is
how many planes do we need to cover all
these routes
question of well you know if this one's
less than this one is there you know is
it possible to get a plane from here to
here in time to cover that route but
that's gonna make our life even more
complicated so let's assume that all the
planes end up and start in the right
place okay so 6 7 that's bad
and none of them are comparable because
no you can't use a plane to cover both 1
& 2 or both 1 & 3 or about two and three
because they overlap each other so one
however is strictly less than four and
it's strictly less than 6 7 5 & 8 and
we're not gonna worry about that for
right now okay so 2 & 3 well they're not
less than 4 so we could put 2 and 3 up
there but that's okay let's see so this
is awfully complicated
what's the race cool yeah right I mean
so destroying some flights so 1 2 3 4 5
let's see 1 is less than 4 1 is also
less than 5 & 4 & 5 are not comfortable
- I guess is less than 5 also and is
that it I think those might be all the
strict lessons because everything else
overlaps it any events so the question
is how many well first of all is it
clear how I got from my intervals to my
pressure ordering so my partial ordering
is
namely this order is supposed to be less
than this one or this interval is
supposed to be before this one so okay
so the interval I is less than the
interval J if the interval is completely
to the left of the interval J and so we
can get all kinds of partial orders all
kinds of hasta diagrams for these
and then the question is how many planes
do we need to cover this you know to
cover all these routes and well first of
all which partial orders can even arrive
arise as interval orders that question
is maybe easier to answer but the
question is so how many planes do we
need and so that's basically just a
question about partial orders the idea
is is we could use because this interval
is completely to go after this one we
could use one plane for these three
flights we could probably use one plane
for this and this and then we have to
use one plane for this and the last
plane for this so the answer in this
case will be four question is you know
if you've some really huge partial
ordering I mean it's obviously much more
complicated than this to move your
troops and your food and your missiles
and everything else around in the case
of a war I really hate to use this
example because I really don't like to
say that I work for the government or
the NSA or anything like that but in any
event some mathematicians do maybe I
should say the event the answer is for a
bigger you know for some really big post
that we can still fairly quickly
determine how many planes we need and
you can't just quickly glance at your
post set but it turns out
biggest number the biggest size and anti
chain I haven't told you what an anti
chain is of course but that's ok so it's
the size of a biggest anti chain an anti
chain is a set of elements that are all
not comparable to each other so an anti
chain in this case would be this guy
this guy this guy and this guy
so no pair of the sets in an anti chain
can be compared to the other they all
overlap and so of course I'm going to
make sense intuitively that the maximum
number of overlaps that we have is going
to well I mean that's going to give us a
lower bound on the number of planes we
need because if there's five routes that
overlaps and obviously we need five
different planes to be flying each of
those routes simultaneously you have
some work to do to prove that that's
enough planes but you can do it so
that's kind of cool
time to start something new are there
any questions about what we've done so
far today no I could have put a box
there but I can't put a box on both of
them because then these two would be
comparable so an anti chain
mean the other theorem that we need here
is that the size of an anti chain the
size of a maximal anti chain is also the
number of chains that we need to cover
our graph a chain is something that's
just didn't think junk go straight up
and so here we have one chain two chains
three chains four chains and so size
number of elements in maximal ante train
our post set and I'm certainly well you
can prove that that's kind of a pain to
proof but it's not terribly hard so and
it's certainly not obvious so are there
any other questions
you want to cover all the vertices Yeah
right right you just we want to cover
the vertices because those are the
intervals that we need to and those are
the planes that need to be or the routes
that need to be serviced so I guess this
question is also relevant in modern days
to Airlines when they have you know
eight million flights they want to not
cancel and they sort of want to minimize
the number of planes that they actually
have to use so they would probably use
some algorithm to find the maximal anti
chain in order to figure out how many
planes they need it in blah blah blah so
it's probably much more complicated
because they also have to take into
account that you know the cities the
ending cities have to be
to each other or the same and I wouldn't
even want to think about the scheduling
problems but in any event this kind of
scheduling problem comes up a lot when
you're looking at post outs or post
that's come up a lot when you're looking
at scheduling problems so