counting we did the addition principle
the multiplication principle the
we've done five principles about
complement principle the notice when two
things are the same principle and the
count things multiple times in a
controlled way principle and then from
there we went through some of the ABCs
that come up a lot in counting
combinations and permutations and now
we're doing the next step which is to go
through some more ABCs that come up and
counting and finishing up those ABCs
we'll move on to the inclusion exclusion
theorem which I taught you back in set
theory and we're going to see how that
connects back to counting problems that
is really a generalization of this
complement principle the inclusion
exclusion principle if you remember how
it works is looking at the stuff that
doesn't intersect but the overlap so
it's kind of a generalized complement
principle and it's a lot trickier but it
lets you solve incredibly difficult
sounding problems so we're going to get
to that today once we're done with that
we're done with what I think are more or
less the basics of counting there's one
more principle which is really all on
its own and it's a really simple
principle called the pigeonhole
principle and it basically means that if
you've got five pigeon holes and six
pigeons that when you're all done
putting your pigeons in the pigeon holes
there's going to be one hole that it's
got at least two pigeons it's like it's
like a no-brainer principle but there
are surprisingly subtle things you can
prove with that simple principle and
actually there are such things as pigeon
holes down in caves these little niches
out and people used to raise pigeons in
them so if you ever saw a cave with
pigeon holes in the wall you'd see why
they call this the pigeon hole principle
looks just like you'd think and when
you're out of room for pigeons right
there right there's a lot of flying
pigeons around okay well very last thing
in this whole unit will be we're going
to take all the stuff we've done in
counting the principles the ABCs the
inclusion exclusion
helper generalization of the complement
principle we're going to take it off and
see how does this connect to certain
kinds of probability questions and
probability is of course you
take independent of a combinatorics
course and when it's typically taught
its taught in a very very widespread way
often getting into statistics often
getting into calculus and continuous
kind of things the probability that we
talk about in this class is a subset of
that course called discrete probability
a very small subset and it deals with
probability that you can actually count
and it's really almost a 10-minute
lecture on probability at most and
really just let's do all the stuff we
did before in counting but related to
probability so it's not going to be
anything new it's just going to be
applications of counting to probability
in a discrete way
so the real principles are really today
and next lecture and then it'll be just
probability as an application any
questions all right so here's here's our
next one of our ABCs we did permutations
and combinations last time and now we're
going to do some variations on
permutations and combinations something
you might call them generalize
permutations or combinations but here's
one that I know you've seen before and
again I'll do it by example we'll call
this a generalized permutation and we'll
talk about generalized combinations what
I mean by generalized is that
permutations of combinations have a very
specific meaning you have a certain
number of elements permutations are you
take some subset out you care about the
order combination is you take some
subset out you don't care about the
order a generalized permutation allows
some extra parameter here you're allowed
to take out an element more than once in
other words it's not just a set of n
elements it might be a set of n types
like you have four kinds of cookies
you're in a bakery you want to take six
cookies how many different ways can you
do that so there you can repeat you can
take the same cookie many times that's a
different kind of problem so if you add
repetition as a parameter you get a more
generalized look at permutations and
combinations okay that's what we're
gonna talk about right now so here's
here's the first example here this
example you've seen before let's say
you've got two different things zeros
and ones and you want to in order
tschüss a bunch of these zeros and
and put them in a list say a list of
five five zeros and ones so here's an
example
to take zeros and ones and put them in a
list of five it's how many binary
numbers are there you could list them
all out start at zero zero zero zero
zero end at 1 1 1 1 1 1 and you all know
that inductively this is kind of a
straightforward idea because if I tell
you how many there are 4 5 then if I add
one more possible thing 0 or 1 I can put
a 0 in front of all the 5 cases and a 1
in front of all the 5 cases and that
gives me all the 6 possible cases so
with doubles every time and we've done
this in a lot of different contexts
we've seen that this is the same as the
number of subsets same as the number of
binary numbers Linkens let me write it
down binary numbers length n equals
number of subsets of a set with n
elements