programs okay in that problem set
there's an analogy that I'll do in a
more simple way here on the board that's
done in a lot of different books you can
find and and you'll get the idea of this
Konan drum so there's a town I always
think of the old Andy Griffith Show
because there's that guy Floyd the
barber and everybody hangs out in
Floyd's shopping and and here's the deal
in this town the barber shaves everybody
that doesn't shave themself
okay everybody got that the fairly
simple idea if you shave yourself you
stay at home if you don't shave yourself
you go to Floyd there's one barber in
town I'm talking everybody Boyd's got a
nice job alternatively the town's all
men but you want to keep it interesting
okay so if you don't shave yourself you
got a Floyd so the question is does
Floyd shave himself or not voice oh my
god let's not go down this road yeah
does Floyd shave himself or not if you
shave yourself are you supposed to go -
Floyd no so if Floyd shaves himself he's
not supposed to shave himself that
possibility doesn't work out but if he
doesn't shave himself what's he supposed
to do he's supposed to go to the town
barber namely himself to shave himself
so you can't answer that question does
Floyd shave himself if you say the
answer is yes the answer should be no if
you say the answer's no the answer
should be yes so this implies that the
statement that I made at the beginning
doesn't make any sense
all right that's a strange little Conan
drum it seems like one of these stupid
little puzzles somebody throws at you in
a bar and you just say please go away
from me I'm meeting a friend right it's
like or can I buy you another drink here
but but it's actually at the heart of of
maybe the most important theorem and in
about in theory of computation that
there are programs that you can't that
you can't write programs that the things
you want to compute that there are no
programs for and I'm going to get back
to the example I did yesterday but this
time we're going to nail it down in a
relatively more rigorous way so let's
say
here's what I want to do I want to
convince you that there's no program
that will find infinite loops and other
people's programs remember I mentioned
that there's no such program that does
it I'm going to convince you of this
today and it will bear a little bit down
on that barber analogy but we're going
to see it in the diagonalization way
you'll see it in your piece set with a
barber analogy but we're going to see it
here in diagonalization so so I tell
Donna Donna when you go home tonight do
me a big favor and for homework when
you're all done with the problem set
because I know you know you'll have
plenty of extra time why don't you go
ahead and write me a program that finds
infinite loops and other people's
programs and bring it in tomorrow all
right and she likes a challenge so she
comes in and she goes I have it here it
is and she gives it to me
so we're going to assume now proof by
contradiction we're going to assume now
that she's done it but she's come up
with such a program and I'm gonna
convince you that she's lying okay is
everybody with me all right so here's oh
well there's a contradiction all right
yesterday we talked about a table where
I number all the programs in the whole
world you know that answer yes or no to
their inputs and I put them here and I
number them one two three all the way up
to infinity there they are
every single program in the world no
programs are missing they're all there
okay there's no program that's missing
all the programs are there there may be
things we want to compute that there are
no programs for but we'll find that out
later right now all the programs are
listed here and we list them up here as
well and we fill in this chart in the
following way we run this program on
this input on this program as input and
we see whether it says yes or no now
yesterday we had a little bit of a fudge
factor the question was well how do you
know if it says yes or no right maybe it
doesn't I said well you could always
check if it says yes because you could
dovetail the computation but then the
issue is well if it never says yes
they'll just be question marks and and
we kind of got stuck and I said there
don't worry you'll see it again and I
said well you know they're just gonna
worry and let me show it let me show you
what really happens today we have
Donna's program right nobody works
program will tell us whether a program
goes into an infinite loop or not all
they do is say yes or no to a given
program like a compiler yes this is good
no it's not good okay should be right
right her program is one of those right
her programs here vie for Donna
Donna's program is here that's a good
point chris is right Donna's programs in
this list it takes programs and it says
yes
do they have infinite loops or no they
don't have infinite loops okay by the
way we hope Donna's program run on Donna
better tell us that it has no one finit
loop right I hope so right otherwise
your program is baloney so we know
there's no one there yeah when I run
down this program and another program
right it's telling me does it ever go
into an infinite loop right right does
it sometimes go in well no what I'm
sorry Rob but her program will take her
program will take the program and any
input at all you want and and tell you
whether it whether it goes into an
infinite loop it'll take two inputs your
program right so I guess it but we can
tweak but we can make tonic we can make
a version of Donna's program in here we
can make Donna's program just check if a
program accepts itself or not and then
Donna's program would be in our list
okay so so some version of Donna's
program is in here Prime and that's not
the main part of this idea so but let's
get to it all right so here's this list
let's start filling it up with the help
of Donna's program will will take
program one run it on itself Donna's
program says this is not an infinite
loop so we let it run for a few years
and sooner or later it says yes or no I
accept or I don't if it says I accept
I'll put a one here if it says I don't
I'll put a zero so let's say it doesn't
accept it it says no I say zero it says
yes to two now what happens here I throw
any program one on input three and
Donna's program said hey this is going
to be an infinite loop so what should I
put in one or a zero we it's just a
choice and we're going to do zero if it
says no we're going to do zero if it's
an infinite loop
gonna do zero but if it says yes we're
gonna put in one okay
we're not going to distinguish between
infinite loops and and saying no
infinite loops and saying no are both
going to turn out to be zeros all right
so in this way I fill in this whole
table I can fill it all in as long as I
go her program does it that's our
assumption I sent her home last night
with this with this job I'm gonna
convince you she's lying but but she
says she's got one that does it and then
we fill in these these values right but
the ones that do we just write zeros in
questions so far
everybody okay all right ready here's
the next step the next step is what we
did yesterday you've seen this before I
am now going to go down the diagonal and
I'm gonna convince you that there's a
row in this table that you missed but
there's a missing program here but this
time I want to analyze what that program
is actually doing here's the missing
program I'm going to go down this
diagonal and I'm going to toggle all the
bits so here's what I get I get one one
one one zero this row could not possibly
be in my infinite list if it was in my
infinite list what would happen right it
would not agree with the if it was say
in the 15th row it wouldn't agree with
the 15th spot in that row this
particular value that I just created is
different than every single row that's
already in the table it's different from
the third row in the third spot it's
different from the 80th row in the 18th
spot so this is a new row that was not
included in a list of programs this is a
computation that we have no program for
well what is this computation doing what
does
this program if I could write it if it
existed what would it accept what are
these ones represented they were the old
zeros right this program accepts all
things that either say no to these
inputs or else our infinite loops to
these enzymes right that's what this
program does and this program doesn't
exist but it wasn't in our list but I'm
going to convince this program everybody
agrees now doesn't exist it wasn't in
our list but what would it do if it did
exist it would say yes to every single
computation that ends up saying no to
that value or going into an infinite
loop now that we agree this doesn't
exist I'm going to convince you that
Donna's assignment last night implies
that this does exist Donna has something
that checks for infinite loops right she
could take any program and any input and
check if there's an infinite loop well I
could just take her program and fiddle
with it a little bit and make a program
that does this here's what I do I take
our program it checks for infinite loops
I'd run this particular program on a
particular input if it was an infinite
loop I'd put a 1 there if it's not an
infinite loop I just run the program
until it's sooner or later tells me yes
or no and then I know what to put in the
next spot I could compute this line if
Donna's program worked I wouldn't have
any trouble writing this program but
this program doesn't exist there is no
way to write this program it doesn't
exist here so the fact that Donna said
she had a solution has got to be wrong
because if she has a solution I can
write that program all right this is a
very subtle tricky idea this is actually
a completely relatively rigorous way of
showing it you need to let it sink in a
little bit here's the moral of the whole
thing if you try to write a program that
accepts all other programs which say no
to themselves or infinite loop that's
impossible you can't write a program
that takes another program and an input
and tells you whether it's an infinite
loop or says no you can't write a
program that does self-hating right
programs are not smart enough to know
about themselves
they're smart enough to know about a lot
of other programs but if you include
themselves in the group they lose their
power Floyd can shave everybody in town
that doesn't shave himself but if you
include him in the town he loses his
great perspective right so this analogy
actually is it's all the programs that
infinite loop on themselves or don't
accept themselves why is that program
one on itself either infinite loops or
doesn't accept itself so I put a 1 here
program 2 on itself either infinite
loops or doesn't accept itself so I put
a 1 here program 5 on itself does accept
itself so I put a 0 here this
computation is trying to figure out
which programs infinite loop on
themselves and which or and which ones
or which ones don't accept themselves
this is a computation of all self hating
or infinite looping programs do you see
where the self thing comes in all right
so if Donna's program actually works I
could build something that does this
I take Donna's program I put a program
into it I run it on itself she tells me
if there's an infinite loop if there is
I put a 1 here if there's not an
infinite loop I just run the program on
itself until I get an answer and if it
says no then I put a 1 there if it says
yes then I put a 0 there so I could use
Donna's program to construct this even
though we know that this particular
program is impossible because it's not
nevertheless yeah
right that's a good question
what if I just took this horizontal room
and I made and I toggled all these beds
and I tried to claim to you that row
does not exist here well if you toggle
one of them it just means that it's
different from this row but it might be
identical to one of the other rows
there's no guarantee it might not be
somewhere else in our list here here's
one that is identical it's identical
except for the first one right so if
you're just so this one is different
from that one right but now I'll have
another one down here which is say this
well the same one this could have been
here yeah if you just concentrate on one
row and you create this say I just
changed the first bit of that row so I
get this new computation and you're
trying to convince me this row is not
anywhere else in the whole but here it
is I just showed you it was number 6 I
just didn't write it in before the idea
of this diagonal argument is that
there's no row that could ever be
further on so I'll switch the whole
thing good that's the next step so how
come how come I can't play this game
with a diagonal idea right it seems like
I'm just cheating here right you say
it's not there because it's different
than that when I say it is there it's
number 8 you just didn't see it
so how come if I go down the diagonal it
can't be number 8
different at that spot so I know that
that I couldn't have been there we are
look if your sense of this proof is that
it's tricky and magical it is it is a
tricky and magical proof and and your
first gut instinct might be not to trust
it but your next instinct would be to
spend a hundred hours thinking more
about it and trying to see how it all
fits in with a Barbara cone and drum of
putting it all together and it really
happens to be a deep proof there are no
flaws in this and it really does work
even though it seems tricky it doesn't
work for row or column but it does work
for the diagonal because if I do this
trick and I say oh it was number eight I
just didn't show it to you you can say
well that's baloney shahi can't be
number eight because when I constructed
this value I constructed the opposite in
this row so it couldn't have been row
number eight but if you just changed
this one I can tell you well it's number
eight it's just the opposite of that
it's when you construct something down
the diagonal that you know it's got to
be different than all the rows that are
already there because it hits all those
rows you couldn't you know you don't
need to diagonally you could do like
night-nights moves would be okay
probably you know and anything that it
would be a little bit uglier to do the
proof but anything that hits all the
rows in unique places would probably be
all right yeah John oh it's not finite
its countable its countable that's
different than finite it's infinite but
it's the same infinite as natural
numbers okay yes right right and and if
you want to say okay well I didn't have
the sorry
I thought I had the list but now that
you mention it I should have put this
one in there then I'll put that in there
and we'll do the whole argument again
and I'll come up with a new one
every possible I'm gonna program and a
lot of jumpers you yes
but typically what you do is you
actually take your characters you make
programs out of and you order them
lexicographically in alphabetical order
and any ones that actually don't make
legitimate programs you just define
those programs to be the programs that
just do 0 0 all the way so you might get
you know lots of rows that are zeros and
that would be the junk you're talking
about but that wouldn't affect this
argument it would still work well
because we're on the diagonal so it's
programs working on themselves and the
idea is that you can't figure out
whether programs accept themselves or
not and the part that falls apart is the
part whether they're infinite loops
because if it always terminated then we
could fill out any of these values and
actually have it as a program so the
only thing that really prevents us from
doing it is that infinite loop idea I
should say that what you do in theory of
computation is you take this problem and
then you reduce it to a gazillion other
problems some of which are very far from
this so one very important problem this
is an extremely important problem that
is completely unable to be done is what
if I give you it's a fancy word but it
basically means the compiler what if I
give you two context-free grammars if I
give you two compilers this is a
compiler for scheme this is a compiler B
for scheme two people did it they're
competing they want to make a good
compiler or a better compiler and the
question is I'm giving you these two
compilers I want you to just make sure
before I test them against each other
that they really do the same thing you
know that they're both compilers for
scheme that they both accept the same
things and reject the same things that
problem taking two context-free grammars
or two compilers and deciding whether
they do the same thing is not decidable
in other words nobody can write a
program to do that that's a really
important program to be able to write
program with the other program and then
run the program through that make sure
you get the same well to check that
you'd get the same input you'd have to
run it on the infinite number of
possible inputs to check that they'd all
be the same that's the brute force way
the same if you run one compiler on a
bunch of scheme programs and you run
another compiler and a bunch of scheme
programs and there's an error in one of
them it's not going to be the same if
you run one compiler through another
compiler then the first compiler if it
has errors is going to have errors when
you run it through the the second
compiler and the second pilot would work
fine
it's that that wouldn't help make any
distinction between the equality here
that one could still work fine and the
other could still mess up even if you're
going to run one through the other so
it's true one can simulate the other but
neither one can know whether those
answers are all going to be the same
Music
say the error is is say it's a there's
no error how do you know there are
always going to get the same answer you
keep running and running and running and
you have to keep trying well nobody
knows any better way in any case so so
there is no algorithm that's guaranteed
to finish that tells you yes or no
through all the cases yeah Rob compiler
behavior is is deterministic but in
order to check whether they're exactly
equivalent we'd have to actually run the
two compilers on every possible input
true there is no automatic way to check
that you have it that you have something
that really works you could check for a
particular compiler whether it worked
but not for a general one there's no
program that will take anything and
tells you whether this really meets the
specification that that another program
is describing okay there are more
specific ways of specifying what a
program should do and you could check
those but you can't just take two
arbitrary context-free grammars and
check whether they actually accept the
same things or not that that's
impossible but this is where we this is
a theory of computation discussion that
we should have like in four months and
not today so we should but but let's
last couple questions yeah Brian and
then Sam in particular cases you might
be able to narrow it down to a finite
number of cases and and you're right but
your program would have to work on any
two compilers and the point is that it
can't it might be able to if you could
restrict your problem to a simpler
subset of compilers it might be able to
work but if it's has to run on any two
it fails so that's a good point
yeah
to count them yeah because programs are
just are just the sequence of characters
every program is built out of characters
and every program has a finite length
therefore I can count all the programs
in any language but you're right it is
dependent on the fact that programs are
countable programs are just syntactic
structures
what isn't countable is what programs
can do the things programs can do is
uncountable
programs themselves are countable and
that in a nutshell is why there are
things you want to do that there are no
programs for okay I want to do something
now that's a little less fun and you
just need to see it because if I don't
show it you in class you'll say did you
do that in class and I'll say well I
didn't do it because it was boring I
wanted you to look it up I'm gonna do it
real quick I'm gonna do it real quick it
talks about functions we talked about
functions yesterday you need to know a
few definitions about functions things
that computer scientists and
mathematicians take for granted and
things that you probably may not know
and I don't want you to take it for
granted so let me go through these
definitions and explanations and it has
to do with the idea of making a
one-to-one correspondence showing that
something is countable and what a
one-to-one correspondence means because
a function is not always a one-to-one
correspondence so I want to talk about
that for about 10 minutes and then I'm
going to shift gears and we're going to
go back to sums I'm going to show you
how to evaluate sums when there's
induction involved how to evaluate sums
when there's no induction involved and
we'll work our way towards recurrence
equations alright so functions functions
and one-to-one correspondence
correspondence first because I hope you
know what this means so one-to-one
correspondence is some sort of a
correlation between a set of things here
and a set of things here where every
single thing here corresponds to a
particular thing here and vice-versa so
here's a one-to-one correspondence we do
this one yesterday the natural numbers
to the positive even integers okay 1
goes to 2 2 goes back to 1 2 goes to 4 4
goes back to 2 it's a one-to-one
correspondence the function that
represents this one-to-one
correspondence is f of X equals 2x
anytime you have a one-to-one
correspondence you have a function that
represents it now what's a function you
all supposed to know this but I'm just
going to review it the only thing that
has to be true to make a function of
function is that it's got to be a rule
it's got to take something and transfer
it to something else but the one thing
that it can't do it can't change its
mind ok if it takes one and decides that
that goes to 2 then it can't take one
and send it to 3 the next time you send
in one so if it was a machine that has a
little hole and you put the input in and
then the output comes out another hole
every time you put a little ball that
has one on it into that machine a to
better come out if you put one on it the
next day and a three comes out then
that's not a function machine send it
back to the company that makes function
machines and say you want it to fix it
ok it doesn't work functions can't
change their minds all right yeah
question sure because it still has a
unique answer for every single input
right you could make it into lots of
different cases if you wanted to right
sure all right if you have a one-to-one
correspondence
then not only is this direction a
function but the inverse direction is a
function that's the forward direction
what's the function that goes backward
we'll call it G of x equals x divided by
2 and we sometimes write that
inverse of f of X okay it's the bits the
backwards it's the thing that sends you
back some terminology if you have a
one-to-one correspondence
then a function has an inverse there are
functions that don't have inverses and
there are functions that are not
one-to-one correspondence and we need to
talk about them and there's a couple
definitions and they'll do some examples
and then we'll let it go okay everybody
okay so far so here's an example when
you talk about functions you need to say
where the inputs coming from and where
the outputs going to that's called
domain and and range mm-hmm months zero
good here's a function it takes ax it
sends it to x squared the domain are the
natural numbers the range is the natural
numbers okay so this function takes only
whole numbers greater than zero and it
sends them to other whole numbers
greater than zero is this a one-to-one
correspondence it is right
yes or no yes I say it is I'm trying to
get you to say yes now I'm saying no
what is it
let's see what it means let's write it
down one goes to 1 2 goes to 4 if I make
this range go to natural numbers then
there are some natural numbers on this
side and if I put them in to my inverse
function or if I try to go backward what
happens when I put 3 in here I don't get
a natural number on the way back right 4
goes back to 2 but 3 goes back to the
square root of 3 and you know that
there's no whole number that's the
square root of 3 so this function
doesn't have an inverse per se going
from end to end if I made this are 2 are
real numbers two real numbers then well
we'll do this well but it's a different
reason
does it have an inverse a one-to-one
correspondence and having an inverse R
if and only if they're the same
and range affects whether something has
an inverse or not it affects whether
it's a one-to-one correspondence you
need to know what the domain is and the
range is in order to answer this
question that's right Tony good all
right so let me do an example and
explain a couple of definitions there
are two definitions for functions that
functions can be and if they're both of
these then they have a one-to-one
correspondence and they have inverses
the two things that make you have a
one-to-one correspondence in an inverse
is when a function is 1 1 and when a
function is on 2 this does not mean the
same as a 1 to 1 correspondence both of
these together imply a one-to-one
correspondence this is a separate idea
and this is a separate idea let me
explain what these are they're not hard
ideas but you have to get the
terminology a function is on to when
every single value in the range has
something that gets sent to it when
there's nothing left out so is this
function on - no it's not on - it's
missing lots of values 3 doesn't have
anything sent to it 5 doesn't have
anything sent to it 17 I like to think
about this in the following way
here's a picture here's a domain that's
that's on - that I just did here's the
range a function sometimes is written
like this where we take something from
the domain and we move it to something
in the range there's a function let me
ask you a question about any function in
the world is there ever more than one
arrow coming out of this dot no that's
what a definition of a function means
one arrow coming out of this dot in a
function is it possible to have dots
here that are empty yes but what about
an onto function no so when onto
means everything in the range has to
have at least one arrow pointing to it
and that's how I like to think of it at
least one arrow to everything in the
range at least one hour to everything in
the range you could have more than one
arrow this guy could go here also it's
possible a function is 1:1 if you have
it most one arrow coming in at least one
arrow to every dot means it's on to at
most one arrow means it's 1:1 I think
that's the easiest way to look at it
it's not the typical definition but it's
virtually equivalent at least one hour
at most one arrow if you have at least
one hour and at most one arrow to
everything in the range what does that
mean that every dot in the range has
exactly one arrow that means you can
reverse the arrow orders and you get you
get a function right if you reverse
these arrows do you get a function no
because you got two things coming out of
here if you reverse the arrows and you
have an empty one then that's a problem
because this is in the domain now and
there's nothing in the range that it
would get sent to know once a one means
there's at most one arrow it hears I'll
give you an example of a function that's
one one and not on to an a function
that's on two and not one one I'll give
you examples of all these things in a
second no you can't because if it's not
on to Chris you've got this empty this
example of the squares that means you've
got lots of dots here that have no
arrows pointing to them so when you go
back from this domain to this range a
function has to tell you what to do with
everything that you throw in the in the
input so when I throw this dot in
it says sorry I'm broken and that's not
a function
one-to-one correspondence and a function
being one one there are two different
things
yeah I know it's a bad choice of words
but that's what it is for a hundred
years so tough luck one one is different
than a one-to-one correspondence a
function is a one-to-one correspondence
when it's both one one and onto okay
yeah fine Anthony suggests that instead
of calling this natural numbers we'll
call this the squares of the natural
numbers in which case this would be on
two and one one in which case you would
have a one-to-one correspondence and
you'd have an inverse that's true and
that's what Tony was getting at before
that you could change domain and range
and fix some of these problems but let
me do a couple more examples so you'll
get more of this so here is a function
that as it's written now is on is not on
two but is is one one right there's no
two things here that go to the same one
on that side so it is one one but not on
to one one not on to let me do another
one
ceiling of X that means if it's a
fraction it just raises it up to the
nearest integer to the whole number and
this goes from the real numbers to the
natural numbers or to the to the
integers will include negative numbers
whole world can go in here and we just
push it up to the nearest integer that's
bigger than it is it on to right because
it gets every possible integer is it one
one couldn't possibly be there's a
gazillion real numbers 1.2 1.4 1.7 1.8
that all go to 2 so this is on 2 but not
1 1
function real numbers two real numbers I
take anything you give me I add 1 is it
on - yes is it 1 1 yes so this function
should have an inverse what would the
inverse be write as an inverse it's a
one-to-one correspondence
when tarah did that countable argument
for pairs of numbers and she did that
diagonal thing you know did she do that
alright so when she did that she came up
with a function that function should
have been a one-to-one correspondence
and it should have an inverse you give
me a number I'll tell you where it is in
the chart you tell me where you are in
the chart I'll tell you what number that
connects to okay questions about this
yes Sharon
there's always for any function and
arrow coming out of every dot in the
domain you can't have empty things in
the domain that are left open that's
part of the definition of a function not
only can't you change your mind
but you can't say I don't know what to
do with this input if you give me the
domain that means you're willing to for
me to put anything in it okay that's
like a candy machine saying insert
nickels and quarters and nickels are
fine and then when you insert the
quarter and you press your Hershey's bar
it says sorry you know can't take
quarters at this time right so yeah
right but that's but that's a bad
function okay that's a yeah well that's
a busted machine here one more example
real fast here's a function y a finite
function 1 goes to 1 2 goes to 1 3 goes
to 3 is it on - no is it 1 1 nope
does it have an inverse nope yeah yeah I
say yeah right here I write finite
functions the domain is the set 1 2 3
the range is the set 1 2 3 here's the
function f F of 1 equals 1 F of 2 equals
to F of 3 equals 3 oh yeah thanks yes so
you can write it I just can't write
write a finite function you can write by
just specifying the things we're used to
writing functions as formulas and you
think of a function as a formula but if
functions on a formula function is any
kind of correspondence between the
domain and a range
and if it's a finite set then you can
always describe it by just listing it if
your range is integers then two is
supposed to go someplace I don't
understand of all the arrows points it -
that's okay
we can do that that's not a function
oh I see then you can write f of X
equals - yes instead of writing f of 1
equals to F of 2 equals to F of 3 equals
2 it's also not 1/1 it's also not on -
right
yeah I'm not erasing it just look like
I'm gonna do it that wasn't what you
were thinking about right it's like it's
like you got to decide if you're punting
or not on fourth down before well in a
kids game before I set the defense you
got to decide what your range is and
specify that and then tell me what the
function is you can't just say oh my
range is whatever I'm going to hit - and
if you do then tell me arranges that and
all exclude 1 and 3 from the range okay
what you just said right oh no no the
range is the thing that's well yeah but
you'll notice I did not use the word
codomain
jeez huh
anyway I'd like to give you a few terms
as you need to actually understand the
idea and sometimes that's zero sometimes
little bit of review in orders of growth
with functions oh we got a lot more
because there's one problem on the
problem set that I think is really
crucial for experimenting with and for
learning about orders of growth it's the
problem where I gave you a gazillion
functions and I asked you to order them
I said if they're big theta of each
other put them on the same level but if
one is actually you know larger than the
other it's a small oh of the other then
then actually put them in order it's a
really really useful problem because you
have a lot of pairs of functions to
compare and it will force you to develop
intuition that you wouldn't normally get
by just doing the everyday typical
examples so here's a simple example of a
kind of thing that might come up on that
problem that I'll do a harder one the
question is how do these compare to one
another and the answer is that they're
the same and they're both X log X
they're both big theta X log X so let me
show you why you all should know this
but I'll show you why anyway vlog of x
to the x equals x log X so it's
certainly big theta X log X because the
constant is just 1 for both cases it's
less than or equal to X log X where the
constants 1 it's greater than or equal
to X log X where the constants 1 that's
one of those log rules you learned in
month one but about this one this one is
x times 2 log X which equals to X log X
so that's going to be big o of X log X
because it's less than or equal to 2x
log X and it's going to be greater than
or equal to X log X for a constant of 1
so you can Big Island big Omega so this
is also big theta X
X intuitively the constant doesn't
matter so X log X + 2 log X are the same
these two functions are the same and you
put them on the same log
alright let me do a more complicated
example you're probably thinking oh gee
I wish I really had absorbed all those
log rules and you would be right the
more of those are automatic the faster
you're going to be able to have a good
guess as to which function is and and
when they're not automatic it's gonna
seem like you're working hard but the
harder you work the more automatic it'll
be the next time so here's a hard one or
a harder one at least X - the log X log
X to the X I just reversed them to
different ones yep I'm going to compare
them which one's bigger than the other
are they the same what are they compared
to so at this point you know when you're
a beginner you're just looking at aw
geez I never saw anything like this do
we ever do anything like this
it's not fair to put this on the exam if
we didn't do anything like this in class
to compare these two things they don't
look very easy to compare if you have
some intuition mathematically you
probably already have a good guess as to
which one is harder but if your
intuition is still at a beginner's level
or even an intermediate level you might
not know where to go so let's try to at
least get this into a better form let me
give you a goal if it looked like this
bigger
exponent is bigger than that and these
are just a factor whether they actually
are you know one's bigger than the other
maybe they're big theta you'd have to
work through the definition I should
mention as a good thing to remember that
when you have exponents that are the
same if this is bigger than this one
normally as a function it's big oh it's
it's a larger specifically than this
then this whole thing is larger than
this as well
and that's something you could prove and
in some of the exercises you end up
discovering this yourself but but it
doesn't look like that we have to make
it look like that we have to make it so
that we have some chance of doing this
so take logs on both sides yeah what
base any base you want what Sam is
suggesting is more or less what I want
to do but I like to present it at a
mildly different way so here's what I'm
going to say I I want to introduce this
in a slightly different way because it
relates to something you'll see in
recurrence equations the idea of
changing the variables changing the
variables and making it look a little
more like what you like and it's
essentially equivalent to taking the
logs of both sides why am I going to
make the substitution of this change of
variable because I'd like it to be true
to the something versus 2 to the
something like I showed you before so
let's go ahead and do this and see how
things simplify and if you think how
would I know to do it well you guess you
try some tricks you get better at seeing
which trick works it's not very
satisfying but that's the best I can do
right now let's try to calculate X and
log X so we can substitute in there and
try and change everything to Y change
the variable access to to the why we
chose that as our substitution what does
log of X going to be take these two Y
now things now the logs are gone you
know logs make you sick so get rid of
them so X to the log X what does that
look like 2 to the Y to the to the Y
comparing it to what's this Y to the
it still doesn't look quite what we want
but if I giving you this to begin with
you probably wouldn't have had a
complete horrible knot in your stomach
just a mild one look at these two
they're different from the two we
started with but they are still
relatively comparable I just changed the
variable how can I compare these two now
- to the Y to the Y is the same as two
to the Y squared
okay two to the a to the B is 2 to the a
times B how can we write this in terms
of two to the something is there any way
this Y let's say I want it to take Y and
write it as 2 to the something it would
be 2 to the what
that's the definition of log Y 2 to the
log of y is equal to Y so I substitute
that for Y and I still have the 2 to the
Y up here so what's this equal to this
is not equal this is a question or two
to the log Y to the two to the Y let's
finish it up it's 2 to the log Y times 2
to the Y so now I've got what I promised
we got 2 to the something equal to 2 the
something and let's compare Y squared -
log base 2 y to the 2 to the Y 2 to the
a that's a good point
2 to the 2 to the a to the B is 2 to the
a times B ok it's the same step we
actually used here 2 to the Y to the Y's
to the Y squared to the log y equals y
means this is exactly the definition
there's no there's no idea there except
the definition log Y is the number that
if you raise 2 to that number you get Y
and that's I just put it in there so the
rule of thumb is you can always get rid
of a Y and turn it into 2 - anything you
want so we did that we forced it I
twisted the arms of these formulas until
they look the way I wanted them to look
and I hope to god when I was all done
that the exponents would be something
that were more obviously compare
than what I started with so let's look
at the exponents now here I have y
squared here I have 2 to the Y times log
base 2 of Y which ones bigger don't take
too long
you did this which ones bigger 2 to the
Y or Y squared 3 to the Y kills y
squared it's a mismatch
no no it's log base 2 y times 2 to the Y
notice this is just like this is like
just bonus this is like take this huge
guy you know and you know I don't know
the Goldberg guy that wrestling guy
right you think a huge guy that's 2 to
the Y put him up against me in the
wrestling ring why square just some
typical average guy and then give
Goldberg like somebody to tag in an
extra log Y is if it wasn't enough just
to have 2 to the Y this just kills this
it's it's there's no match right right
boom right right head into the
turnbuckle ah all right what's the point
therefore this one is bigger and if this
one's bigger that means this one's
bigger 2 to the Y squared versus 2 to
the log Y times 2 to the Y compare this
to this
saying before
said is that this one is definitely
going to be bigger than this one but if
you wanted to put it back into big our
notation we could say that this is you
know order every function is order
itself this is order two to the two to
the Y times log Y but if you wanted to
put it back you'd have to redo this and
we just end up getting this so the idea
of what it really is is kind of like
it's not really a well-defined question
it's not like every function is big-oh
something unique there Big O of all the
other functions that are better that are
larger than that so so you don't look
for some canonical one to compare it to
you just compare it to another one
typically we like to put all functions
into one of typical you know like n or n
log N or N squared or two to the N I
mean these are the ones that come up so
often so we tend to like to take any
weird thing that comes up and figure out
where it sits relative to these but
that's just because these come up a lot
there's nothing really special about
that I want to talk about sums I want to
talk about this some in particular and I
want to connect it back to your problem
sets we're going to talk about sums
we're going to work our way to recursion
back to sums and then say goodbye to
sums and logic and all this stuff and
move on to a different topic as of
tomorrow recurrence equations and
recursion today's going to overlap right
now in this you've done a bunch of
proofs by induction some of you
definitely get the idea some you're kind
of on your way and some of you are like
like hate the idea and and don't get it
yet at all and and you all will get it
but it'll take some time some problems I
say are screaming for induction and some
problems I say are not so natural and if
you get that idea probably know what I'm
talking about it if you don't get that
idea it just seems like what's he
talking about screaming for induction so
I want to give you an example in one of
the problems that's I show you a
particular theorem about cubes
theorem again from that same medieval
math book back in the 1321 leyva been
Gershon proved this theorem and he
proves it by induction and if you look
in your problem set what he discovers
before he proves this theorem is another
theorem which just lends itself to
discovering this does anybody remember
what that other theorem is anybody do
this yet what's up there I mean he he
proves well I believe you know what it
is but the other question is can we can
we state it he proved something like
this what does he say this is equal to
does he do this no this is not what you
mean right
No excellent and that's I think that's
what you were trying to say Chris you go
up to n minus one you square it right
plus n cubed then what does that equal
is that right and he proves this with
algebra he proved it's not so hard to
come up with this let's make sure it's
right before I say it's not so hard to
come up with it that's right good it's
definitely right he proves this he comes
up with this analogy who discovers it
one day when you discover something like
this all you got to do is look at it for
about three more seconds to say oh if
this equals n cubed plus this I'll just
do it again
what is this equal
and you can do it again and again and
what happens this stays on the right
side and this keeps disappearing turning
into cubes one down as you go until
sooner or later you get to the base case
the thing that stops you and you get one
here at the end and that's where this
comes from this theorem is a screaming
induction theorem from the discovery of
this theorem it's just natural it's
recursion it's all the stuff you did
last month you want to figure out you
want to solve this for n do it for n
minus 1 and add n cubed what happens
then recursively you do a friend
lightest one yet n minus 1 cubed you
call the recursion again it's exactly
recursion so he discovers a recursive
theorem or a relationship like this and
that implies a bigger theorem a more
interesting theorem anything like that
is a theorem that's screaming for
induction and anything like this is this
theorem that's kind of screaming not to
do induction there isn't any natural
theorem like this that looks just as
clean for this example so if you
actually look into lady's book and see
what he does he has a long sequence of
other completely complicated algebra
ideas to come up with this formula even
though you can bet he understood that he
could have done this by induction he
just thought it was a terrible way to do
it because it was badly motivated here
he did it by induction because this is
the way he was motivated to solve the
problem here he didn't do it by
induction because he didn't think that
this was a nice way to do it so we're
gonna do this today I can tell you what
the formula is here it's equal to this
we're going to calculate this formula
not by induction although we could do it
by induction it's just some algebra in
fact if you want to practice it it's
another good example to practice
induction on we're going to do it by a
completely different method this method
will not only show us what I mean by by
a different kind of a proof but it will
help you learn a really important thing
how to manipulate sums manipulating sums
is a crucial thing to be able to do in
the analysis of algorithms
and in manipulating sums at some point
the dot dot dot notation isn't quite
good enough or quite helpful enough so
we end up inventing something called a
Sigma notation and in this proof you're
really going to have a need for it it's
just too hard to do this without the
Sigma notation and up till now I haven't
introduced it because I think it just
makes people have a language barrier to
the idea but in this proof we're going
to need it because the language is
really necessary I'm going to avoid it
until we absolutely need it and then
I'll introduce the notation here's how
we start to do this problem I'm going to
motivate it a little bit the first thing
we start to do is we notice this
particular series if you add up the odd
integers up to some point you get square
numbers people knew this documented you
know back 300c e the late greek period
people knew this it's not so hard to
discover this you can discover it
geometrically here's one here's one plus
three here's one plus three plus five
you add the next odd number you just
wrap around the next shell of the square
yeah it's kind of a proof you could
prove this by induction this does scream
for induction let's say that all the sum
of these add up to N squared what
happens when you add one more n squared
Y add one more what do you add yet two n
plus one that's the next odd number and
what is that equal and plus one squared
that was such a fast proof by induction
that I left out all the gazillion steps
that you would really need to put in to
make it completely clear but the gist of
this proof if you would go ahead and
write it clearly which I'm not going to
do right now maybe I'll come back and do
it later you probably could use the
review but the gist of this proof is
adding on the next number to a square
gets you the next square and if you
could write that out clearly
step-by-step with the base case etc
you'd have a proof by induction of this
but let's just assume this is true now
we all know it's true we're going to use
this to get this formula so let me stop
for a second questions so far
all we have is these odd numbers adding
up the squares we're going to come up
with us in a couple of minutes everybody
okay here we go
9 plus 16 plus what does this one turn
out to be N squared let's check to make
sure that's true if n is 3 the last term
is 5 and I get 3 squared all right so
the last term is 2n minus 1 here if I
add up these numbers I got the sum of
the squares
what LaVey did is to add up these
numbers by adding up these numbers but
and I'm up a column at a time
here are the squares just add them up
but change the rows in the columns is
everybody with me so far
stop if you're not questions yes in the
case of 135 7 the N is going to be 4 and
that's equal to 16 4 squared is 16
ok let's add these up let's add these up
here's where not having good notation
gets a beginner to the point where they
give up and having good notation
smoothes the mathematician right Bobby
how many ones do we have here everyone
agree 1 2 3 4 5 all the way up to N so
true
and times 1 how many threes do we have n
minus 1 times 3 how many 5 n minus 2
times 5 and minus 3 times 7 all the way
down to the last case where it is 2 n
minus 1 times 1 how are we going to add
this mess up so here's where we need a
better notation to help us add this up
you might be able to avoid it but I
don't see an easy way to avoid it what I
want to do here is notice how the first
term here is changing and how the second
one is changing here's the notation that
we're going to use this means the sum of
we're going to start with 1 2 and figure
out the first term and the second term 1
n is 1 what's the first term it's n
second term n minus 2 etc what about the
second terms here this is 1 3 5 etc when
I'm up to the ight term what is this one
going to be what's this one gonna be is
that right see what this is
when I left the first term it's n went
up at the second term it's n minus 1
it's always n minus the number that's
one smaller than this so it's n minus I
plus 1 okay if I'm on the fourth one
this would be n minus four plus one
that's n minus 3/4 1 n minus 3
that works here's here's the general
term of the first one what's the general
term for this one when you're at one
you're at one when you're a two year at
three so double it and subtract one
multiplying those pairs as I starts at 1
and goes all the way down to what's the
last one that I goes to starts at 1 and
goes down to or goes up to and so here's
how we write it I starts at 1 goes up to
N and we're going to add up all these
terms n minus I plus 1 times 2 I minus 1
now I could have done this using the dot
notation but it would have been a little
bit uglier this really summarizes what I
just said we have these two pairs of
things that are multiplied by each other
they change their values as I changes
from 1 to n when I is 1 they should be n
and 1 when I is 2 they should be n minus
1 times 3 so if I just want to add these
up I'm adding up this sum and you're
thinking well what's the point of
writing this like this how does it help
it helps a lot if you can think about
what's going on and unravel this so
we're up to here and we're about to
finish up and it gets a little bit hairy
but here's where you have to learn how
to manipulate sums if you can learn to
manipulate these things you'll be doing
great
ok other questions so far before I
finish with this questions questions
good I make some room here so we can
actually manipulate this and I'll keep
our goal up here so we can keep track of
where we're headed here's what we're
going to do with this son we're going to
do what you always try to do even
without any particular good intuition
we're going to multiply these things out
together if we multiply them out
together then we have the sum of the
first plus the sum of the second plus
the sum of the third we can split it up
into separate sums each of which might
be easier than the sum of this product
so let's multiply it out and see if we
can split it up into smaller pieces
- I n - 2 I squared + 2 I minus n plus I
minus 1 minus n plus I minus 1 let's see
if we can fiddle with these things a
little bit make them simpler if possible
and then do the sum of the ones we need
- I'll rewrite it up here ok
EJ simplify this a little for me what
goes together go for that plus 3i yeah
what else anything else you're combining
this one and this one - I in the suit
you're gonna combine this one in this
one oh yes okay why don't we do the
minus n in the 2i n then so that we get
n times 2i minus 1 that'll look ok
else is left
and then we got this ugly thing at the
end minus 2 I squared is that okay yeah
let's double check it make sure it's all
right all right
these pieces can still be a little bit
more combined let's take these and group
them together because they both have
eyes in them three plus two n times I
minus n minus 1 minus 2 I squared and
now let's look at it let's see what we
get what happens when you add up minus n
n times for I equals 1 to N there's no I
in this picture right that means minus n
minus n minus n and times what does this
turn into minus N squared so easy it is
to sum this piece that doesn't have an
eye in it start getting used to the
following intuition if you see something
inside a summation sign and a piece of
it doesn't have this variable in it then
just multiply it by how many times
you're doing it so here's what happens
we still have this piece here I go 1 to
N of 3 plus 2 and I we still have this
piece here the minus 2i squared but out
here we're going to take them and square
it and out here we're going to take what
happens to the minus 1 minus n because
it gets that end times and that stuff is
now out of the summation I took it out
it's all been summed the only thing left
to sum is this thing that has an eye in
it and this thing that has an I squared
in it
should tell you that lady does not do
this with algebra he does this with
words so if you can imagine it's hard
enough to see this in algebra if you can
get through it in word to really
understand it all right before we do
that we are going to do that in just a
second I want you to look at this what
is this whole thing equal who remembers
right removes track
summation of I squared right what is
this it's the same problem but twice
right here's what we got so far the
summation an I squared equals this so
I'm going to take the summation of two I
squared and move it to the other side of
the equation I'm going to pull it out
how many summations do I have here now
3i squared summations and on this side
all I have left is minus N squared minus
n everybody see what I did this is the
most clever spot now guys got explained
it again this is this is the most clever
point of the proof on this side I have a
summation of I Squared's fact I have two
of them they go from I equal one to n
that's exactly what the whole formula
equals so I take this summation of two I
squared and I add it to both sides of
the equation on this side of the
equation it cancels this out and on this
side of the equation I get two more
summations of I squared
good idea I'll split these into two
different Sigma so you can see that
they're both supposed to be some done
this one needs to get Sun that one needs
to get Sun now I'm going to take this
and add it to both sides of the equation
so it moves to the other side and now
this side gets to be three times the sum
of I squared other questions about that
move out right in the front right right
sure that's fair because it's just
getting each term is getting multiplied
by two C is essentially just factoring
it out right yes yes it should remind
you that trick yes that's a good point
right it's very much like that trick
when you do integration by parts you get
the integrals in terms of another
integral that's half the size and then
you pull it back over and then you get
that constant term that's true it is
it's just like that trick all right and
we're almost done here we got the square
root of we got I squared sum from 1 to n
we got three of them here what we have
to do is sum this and then we can divide
by 3 and get an answer does this look
familiar the 3 plus 2 n is like a
constant that gets multiplied by each
one of these eyes every single time you
go from 1 to n so it just can get pulled
out and factor it out it does not depend
on I look at this never see this before
those are triangle numbers adding up I
from 1 to N 1 plus 2 plus 3 all the way
up to n here's what we get
three equals three plus 2n what's the
sum of the numbers from 1 to n n times n
minus 1 over 2n times
1 over 2 thank you
good least my notes are right 3 plus 2n
and times n plus 1 over 2 minus n times
n plus 1 that's the right hand side here
if you put this over a common
denominator what do you get this is 3
plus 2 n times n times n plus 1 minus 2
n times n plus 1 so it's going to be 3
plus 2 n 3 plus 2 n minus 2 times n
times n plus 1 over 2 3 plus 2 n minus 2
is the same as 2n plus 1 and if I divide
through by 3 I get a 6 here so the final
answer is 2n plus 1 n plus 1 and divided
by 6 and that is the same as the way
it's written there alright so that's a
long long long manipulation of a sum
it's a great example of manipulating
sums and there's nothing in this
manipulation that doesn't consist of the
following things if you've got the sum
of lots of things you can split them
into the sums of the pieces when they're
added or subtracted together if you get
a constant or something that doesn't
depend on I on the inside of your sum
you can pull it out in front of the Sun
as if you're factoring it all of these
symbolic things you have to get used to
are just transferences from what you do
in algebra but think about it
intuitively and stop making the
intellectual connection when you stop
making the intellectual connection you
immediately get used to the fact that if
I see peace is multiplied inside the sum
and there's no eyes in those pieces I
can pull them out if I see lots of
pieces inside the Sun that are pluses or
minus together I can split them into
smaller pieces get used to those
manipulation rules and you'll be able to
work faster with these summation signs
send you what with a dot dot dot
notation alright questions about any of
this it has a good question all right
well it's all there's there's actually
no complicated idea here except for
except for the notation of the Sun I
maybe Sam will go over this in
recitation today at 4 or 5 what do we
say for you mean writing it like this
and making this part yeah that's the
hardest part after that you're right
done that's the hardest part is going
from that table to the to the Sun with
vision because if you can't do that you
can't manipulate the Sun at all you're
right that's the most important thing I
think if stander goes over this slowly
at 4 o'clock today anybody who didn't
get it here I think would would benefit
a lot it's important to get good at this
kind of thing so if this seemed like a
lecture from the clouds the last 20
minutes then definitely go see it again
Gary I got it it's on it's online yeah
yeah I can't always say that but today I
can let me think wait did I really do it
I probably did I got to go check on I'm
not sure how far I am and typing my
lecture notes but but they might be
there they're certainly written here yes
yes well thar is going to do a bunch of
infinite sums in the recitation I'm
gonna do well I'm going to do some
infinite sums I didn't get to to where I
wanted to I'm right on time but I didn't
get ahead of myself today the next thing
I want to do is move over to recursion
and recurrence equations and the first
thing we're going to do is that towers
of Hanoi problem that you did last month
and in doing that we're going to come up
with a sum that'll be in
some or at least looks like an infinite
sum and and we'll cut it short at some
point make it finite and I'll show you
how to add up geometric sums and from
geometric sums will do things that are
that are similar to that
so let me big picture this is the sum of
the squares you did try on the numbers
you did divergent and convergent series
two months ago all those things are part
of summations but it's a big big topic
I'm just going to throw in the basics in
the next couple days we're going to do
geometric series and versions of
geometric series which Euclid knew 2,000
years ago
so that's old stuff and then as we move
into towers of Hanoi into other
recursive stuff like your seven rings