all right questions about things yeah
that that's why recursion is such a
powerful tool because you can describe
some such a complicated activity with so
many few words and I guess your question
is really not not a statement but a
question well how do I get a better
sense of what's going on without just
being in the in the forest you know tree
to tree all right so so let me back up
and give you a sense of where that
problem that I made up you know with
fruity Freddy and ditzy dot see I forget
the names I use but something like that
and they came up with these weird
algorithms that don't really work right
and the idea is that you had four you
have four pegs to work with let me give
you a sense of where this idea came from
because you see where it comes from
and and I have to back up my thought was
that you guys have seen so much
recursion in skiing that when you see a
recursive procedure you'll somehow get
the big digital picture and maybe you do
but maybe a dump but let me let me show
you where it comes from and and also if
I just wrote intuitively how it works it
wouldn't make sense I think writing the
specifics is a better way to do the
problem but let me give you a sense of
where it comes from here's an algorithm
for doing towers of a node we talked
about yesterday you do the N minus 1 you
move it here you move the bottom one
here you do the N minus one back and
everybody agreed that worked right so
here's another way remember I told you
it's usually better to cut the problem
size in half rather than buy one you get
faster algorithms cutting the problem
size in half it's better to get a
recurrence equation that looks like this
then one that looks like this and that's
that's intuitive because you've knocked
the problem size down by a lot more
that's binary search and that's that's
slower so the idea is that we're going
to do towers of Hanoi but we're going to
do it by cutting the problem in half so
here's the idea here's a list of disks
and we're going to take half of them and
solve the towers of Hanoi on the top
half and move it over here okay and now
I'm going to take the bottom half and do
the towers of annoying the bottom half
and move it over or say here what half
of them whatever that is with four pegs
presumably yes yes yes yes and and then
we'll do another half problem getting
this put on top of here all right so one
of these steps was bogus and the other
two were okay let's go back and review
where's my eraser this chalk is horrible
they should call it write list chalk
there's just nothing here here's a stack
of towers of Hanoi here's the first step
take half and do the towers of Hanoi on
to another peg now let's assume it's
just three pegs for now because there
you're going to see why it doesn't work
right away with four pegs you might have
the illusion that it works and the
reason it doesn't work is a little more
subtle with four pegs but with three
pegs you're going to see why it doesn't
work right away take the half and
recursively move it over here anything
wrong with that step it's a perfectly
fine step the recursion is fine I'm
doing it with half a size I'm doing it
with three pegs this stuff is like
nailed down to the bottom so it doesn't
affect anything the next step taking
this half of a deck and doing a
recursion on these three pegs to get it
here is completely bogus because I can't
use this peg this peg is dead that's why
I throw the other
well now I'm okay now I got an extra peg
so you think now I can do the recursion
but not really because now this
recursive step is really only using
three pegs and the first one actually
had four pegs so you think to yourself
well the first one didn't need the four
pegs it only really needed three so
maybe now I can get away with three see
a write or recursive program to do it
you're not really sure what's going to
happen but you write it and that's what
fruity Freddy did and the problem said
he wrote it with four parameters with
five parameters the number of disks and
the four pegs and he's hoping that this
idea would work and that he's going to
get some nice recurrence equation that
looks like this three half problems and
that's gonna be a lot faster than the
two to the end that he got this would be
really fast this is actually going to
end up being n to the log base two of
three some like between N and N squared
in two days you'll know why that's true
won't work and they don't work for minor
subtle reasons and you need to
experiment and explore and see why they
don't work and that's really the heart
of understanding recursion is to look at
something that looks like it's working
somebody's trying to do hocus pocus on
you and you figure out why they're
trying to pull your leg and that's
that's the purpose of that question so
so how do you really see the big picture
and these questions it's hard if you you
can it works with some small number of
discs but if you try to put in larger
ones you'll start seeing the flaw so try
eight and you'll see the flaw right
to tell true though that's what you say
this half over using three pegs you can
move this half over using the old towers
of Hanoi method using just three pegs
and then you can move this half over
using the old towers of Hanoi method
alright but that's not a recursive
algorithm because you're not writing it
in terms of yourself you're writing it
in terms of a different procedure and
you can do that you're right absolutely
so it could be to do nothing
yeah well the question is whether the
real question is does an extra peg help
I mean if we just do what Sam suggested
then the extra peg really isn't helping
at all we're just going to do three
problems each of which is n over two and
and they're going to be two to the N
over two minus one you had three of
those up and you still have exponential
time I mean that's at least an algorithm
that would be acceptable by the way as
an answer to how you use four pegs as
long as you analyze it and told me how
many steps it took it would be
acceptable the question is what's the
best you can do with the extra peg three
log 2n and n to the log to three are
identical yeah they're identical I'll
show you this in two days also you just
saw this two months ago but you forgot
that these two are identical here's the
intuition this is n to some constant but
this is three to a log and three to
exponents two logs
tend to undo themselves and get back to
polynomials
this then I don't want to review it yet
but I'll review with them I was just in
the middle though oh the extra peg how
much can you use the extra bag does it
help a little
does it not help at all is it just a
complete waste of time your gut instinct
should be a better help a little right
it's better you might even try to make a
graph out of this picture it doesn't end
up quite as pretty as the other pretty
graph we made there's no answer to that
question that anybody knows and I didn't
ask you that question I didn't ask you
what's the best you can do with four
pegs because nobody knows the best you
can do with four pegs there is a really
good fancy algorithm that actually deals
with a number of pegs and the subproblem
instead of being half the size it
actually relates to triangle numbers you
could look this up in the concrete math
book by Knuth if you wanted to see a
fancy way of doing it with four pegs
that cuts the complexity down a lot but
nobody knows that that's the best way
it's in our book to the fancy way okay
the triangle number way yeah nobody
knows the answer to this question and
it's a really interesting problem and
one day somebody will know what's the
best you can do with four pegs and until
then it's just the mystery this seven
rings problem is a really cool problem I
ventured in a million times and today
we're going to solve it we're going to
come up with a number of steps it takes
to solve it we're going to count those
number of steps we're going to relate it
to gray codes related to recurrence
equations related to induction and
recursion rather than hold this and fill
it with it as I go since none of you
would ever see what I'm doing I bought
you all a copy of this and that's why I
wanted you to play with it you're not
really going to get it unless you have
it in your hand
I sometimes going and give talks about
this and try to say oh this is really
worthwhile to do in class and I once did
it to a group of other professors and I
solved the problem while I was talking
and did it and thought that would be
really worthwhile and all they wanted to
do was grab it out of my hands never had
this give me that thing and I passed it
around the room you know and you figure
they pass it around room in an hour talk
and there's 30 people in the room that's
two minutes a person and they're really
going to get the idea playing with this
in two minutes they won't so so that's
why I bought it for you two months ago
so
you could play with it and hopefully get
some of the gist of it down today rather
than hold this but you got another one I
called one you got another ah that's
right we'll pass it to the next person
and then we have we'll figure out if we
have enough people in class to solve the
puzzle I'm gonna represent this puzzle
this whole day as the piece of steel
that you're trying to represent and
there are rings that are locked up
around it or not locked up around it if
you've played with this for a while
you'll know that you can get the rings
off that piece of steel or the rings are
stuck on the piece of steel and when all
the rings are off the piece of steel and
that piece of steel comes off the nails
through the rings and off the whole
puzzle so it starts off like this one
two three four five six that's what it
looks like when it starts and you'll
also notice when you play with this
puzzle that one end is easier to take
the Rings off than the other right
there's an easy end and a hard end so
let's call there let's call this the
easy end call this the hard end there
are two things that you should notice
about this puzzle after playing with it
for a couple of hours one thing is that
the on/off status of the rightmost ring
that means the easiest ring can change
at any time you can always take this off
and put it back on that's easy the other
thing you should notice is that there's
one other ring whose status can change
and that's it you have two moves in this
puzzle if you think of a configuration
of this puzzle as a list of rings and
whether they're on or off then from one
configuration you can move to two other
configurations and I should mention
before I go on in order to determine
what a configuration is the way I do it
is I put all the nails back through the
center of the steel and I look at the
Rings and I see if the Rings are around
the steel or not around the steel all
right everybody's got a different way of
holding it and sometimes people pull the
nails out in order to determine which
configuration you're in you really have
to have the nails kind of through there
and see whether the rings are
or hanging below or above if they're
hanging below or above they're off if
they're around it and intertwine they're
on and that's what I mean by a
configuration some of the configurations
that you think are different might all
really be the same is what I'm saying
okay so one thing you can do is move to
a configuration where this toggles from
being on to off you can always do that
another thing you can do is the
following from now on instead of making
this picture I'm going to put a 1
underneath each spot if the ring is on
and a 0 under the spot if the ring is
off so we're back to binary numbers so
it starts like this and one thing you
can do is turn it into this ok the other
thing you can do from this position
which other one can you take off from
this position anybody know the second
from the right you can also go here I
want to generalize this to any possible
configuration I want you to realize
exactly given a configuration which two
places you can go and I want us all to
agree on this before we do anything else
because those two things are important
to see let's pick an arbitrary
configuration in this game one two three
four five six something like this 1 0 1
1 0 1 let's see here Blake
what's one position I can get to pick
the easy one this right one can change
so right I can change that right one so
that's one position what's another
position I can get to now here we have
to think a little bit does anybody know
are let's make sure we all know what
these two are and I'm going to
completely describe it rigorously you
could write a program to determine this
here's what you do you start on the
right end and you look past all the
zeros that you find until you hit the
first one in this case there are no
zeros at the right end so you hit a 1
right away
the position to the left of that first
one that you hit can be switched that's
the fundamental mechanical nature of
this puzzle that the second to last one
off the right after the first one can be
switched let's look at it here the
second to last one can be switched the
second one can be switched here's
another example one two three four five
six well for sure we can switch this one
that we could always do one zero zero
one zero one what's the other one we
switch let's do it together run through
the zeros until you find the first one
the position to the left of that can be
switched one zero one one zero zero
these are the two positions you can get
to from here are there questions about
this so far this is completely rigorous
there's no choice as to what the two
positions are one is obvious and one you
have to do a little bit of a calculation
the way of computer scientists would
write this down as they'd say look for
the following pattern on the right end 0
star 1 0 start means 0 as many times as
you want including 0 times either no
zeros or as many zeros as you want keep
looking for that pattern until you see a
1 and then it's this position here that
can be toggled alright this is sometimes
called a regular expression it's just
the way you describe patterns of things
you'll see it in web designing programs
looking for patterns if you go to Barnes
and Nobles and want to look up a book
and see what its price is you'll look
for a match looking for your book and
then look for the price and you pull it
out these are used in a lot of places
they're used in theory of computation
used in text editors these come up a lot
you should have that notation down 1 0
star means 1 with lots of zeros even no
zeros and that's a way of describing
what patterns we can get to one from
another so let me stop here questions so
far all right knowing these two things
is enough to completely solve this
puzzle but we have to flush it out
positions to move to from any one
position everybody thinks so wants a
volunteer that they don't know how so I
can call them them here's a seven ring
puzzle alright who doesn't mind when I
pick on them Heather you're always
polite give me the two things that this
can turn into okay that's one that's the
easy part so you're off the hook make
Mike do the next part good very good
okay these two things okay again look
zero-star here's the first one that guy
can toggle at state and it's built that
way and you can build other puzzles that
have this property and they would be
isomorphic to this puzzle they would
look different but they would have the
same properties here's our beginning
position again the first thing I'm going
to do is not talk about gray codes and
and binary things cuz that I'll do at
the end I'll do that the second half I
want to do the more interesting part
first the recursive part first
I should just remind you though that if
we made a picture of the graph of this
game it would be a straight line it
would be an uninteresting graph and if
you actually were just really careful to
note what configuration you were in you
could solve this puzzle by starting at
this point ending at this point and
following the straight line and a lot of
you did solve it that way without
thinking recursively at all all right
it depends what your what your
background is when I finally solved this
puzzle I figured out a recursive idea
and I did it like neo was saying how did
I see I saw the big picture and when I
actually did it I just ran the recursive
idea through my recursive interpreter in
my head and I had no idea where I was up
to if I got lost like what the bindings
of the variables were in the middle I
didn't realize that I was really on a
straight line I was just lost I would
have to start all over again
so when you do it recursively you might
not see that
really just a straight line you're
traveling down but you are but let's
think about this recursively here's what
we're going to do this is the easy side
remember and this is the hard side and
we'd like to take off all these rings
and as many of you discover and I think
a lot of you do discover this that what
you really want to do is work really
really hard and get this guy off because
once this guy is off you can virtually
just Chuck if you had a big sheering
scissors you could chop this piece off
the puzzle and you would just have a new
puzzle that has five rings in it once
you get the hard one off it doesn't come
into the picture at all it never
interferes with anything it's just hangs
there it's like that seventh ring that
you hang it up on the wall from it
doesn't do anything so what we'd like to
do is step by step this is a lot of
steps
dot dot dot get to here and then the
next step would be to get to here dot
dot dot get to here etc one by one
through a series of steps take the Rings
off from the hardest down of the easiest
that's what we'd like to be able to do
but there's a lot of work to get from
here to here now why am i writing it
this way because this is a recursive way
of doing it it's also an iterative way
of doing it but it's a simple recursion
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
show you how to get the hardest ring in
a puzzle off and then I'm going to solve
the puzzle for n minus 1 let's write
that down I'll call it Chinese ring and
Chinese ring n minus-1 you believe that
if you played with a puzzle you should
believe that get the harness ring off
and then you got the same puzzle with
one less ring if you took the right ring
off you don't have the same puzzle with
one less ring okay you got a very hard
puzzle that's not too much easier than
the original six ring puzzle it's taking
it off the left and that really gives
you a puzzle exactly the same as the one
you started with except with one less
ring when this is off these don't get
affected by it at all when this is off
this is not like a five ring puzzle it's
very complicated much more like a six
ring puzzle so here's our recursion the
question is how do we get the hardest
ring off well you guys know how to get
the hardest ring off because you know
how to change to this state you know the
two binary numbers that sit around here
let's figure out what they are one of
them is this one what's the other one
we just gonna like look at it and get
nowhere you can come up with all sorts
of ideas but we need a nice recursive
idea something that's a big picture
suddenly it doesn't look down at the at
the details here so now let's
concentrate just on that this looks like
a dead end possibility we're backing up
I don't think this is going to help us
get a recursive idea and if you think it
might it might take a day until you
convince yourself that maybe it wouldn't
but it's not good so let's let's
concentrate on something that will help
us we want to go from here to here
this be right before I pull it off that
zero zero zero zero if I get it to look
like this then the next thing I can do
is take this off right that's the real
one I wrote the wrong one before and
that's the real one that goes before
this but this should give you a hint how
do I get it to look like this all I got
to do is leave these where they are in
the puzzle ignore them completely and
solve the puzzle for for four rings okay
if I do that then I take one step to
turn it into this not quite into this
right what does it look like zero one
this it wasn't what we wanted when we
concentrate on just getting this off we
get something that's still isn't what we
want but we can fix it
so let me back up in order to get this
hardest one off we have to make it look
like this then we take the hardest one
off but now we want to make it look like
this so what do we do
if you want to pull the hardest one off
take n minus two or four rings and take
them off the puzzle then take your
hardest one off as you're allowed to do
then put those four back on the puzzle
and you're up to the stage that we want
to be let me write this down I'm gonna
say how to get the hardest ring off
Chinese rings and - to slide off hardest
ring and how do we get to here reverse
Chinese rings and - - this is the hard
part when you do it in your head because
this actually is going from an empty off
ring situation to a non ring situation
so you have to kind of do it backwards
in your head you do the Chinese ring end
- - but then you reverse the order of
how you do things that's the part that's
hard to do recursively in your head and
why it's so easy to lose track of where
you're up to because remember each of
these recursions is calling other
recursions and some of them are forward
and some of them are backward and it's
just like ah how do you remember you get
good at it and you practice and you can
remember let's analyze this this is
going to solve the problem it's really
elegant I mean you could write a program
to do this you could write it in scheme
it is six lines long and it will tell
you which position to move to and it'll
generate these configurations and it's
magic like Neil said before because all
the hard stuff is done behind the scenes
the big picture is the relationship
that's going on here the recursive
relationship but on what I want to do
now is switch gears I want to analyze
how many steps this cakes now that we
know exactly the algorithm let me stop
questions about the algorithm
yeah time
keep changing the target using reverse
chines Frankie we can keep would you
change the operation saying that but it
could be one bit is now that would be
fine if you put an extra parameter in
that says you know what's on and off
then you would toggle that bit
absolutely you could use the same thing
and put an extra parameter or you could
just write a helper function that runs
the old algorithm and just reverses its
order which would also be the same it
would be equivalent you could do either
one that's true agreed right right
instead of a recursive routine you could
also just say check where you just came
from and do the other one and you could
write an iterative program for this
absolutely and in fact you're going to
have to write a program for that in in
one of the problems X or the equivalent
of that let's analyze this who can give
me the recurrence equation for this how
much time it takes
EJ can you do it you're rubbing your
beard you look thoughtful the time it
takes to do the Chinese ring problem
let's split up into pieces how much time
does this take that's a recursive call
TN is too good we got two of those so
I'll make it to TN minus two what else
we have this line slide off the hardest
ring that takes one I'll put that at the
end and what else good
that's the recurrence equation that's
the exact recurrence equation for this
puzzle and you know that it's the only
solution possible so it's the fastest
you're not going backwards here this is
a completely straightforward solution we
need a base case in fact how many base
cases do we need two base cases because
this depends on two smaller values so we
need a base case for the one ring puzzle
and a base case for a two-ring puzzle
how long does it take to solve a one
ring puzzle one step pull off the ring
how long does it take to solve a two
ring puzzle you take the left one
I don't think three I think you can
change it to this and then you can
change it to this okay so I think it's
two that's our recurrence equation we're
going to spend the next half hour so
looking at this and trying to solve it
right now the only technique you have
for solving recurrences and it's not a
bad technique at that is repeated
substitution and looking at the some and
hoping to God you can do something with
the Sun right that's not a bad idea but
there are three or four other methods
that we'll get to tomorrow and the day
after and we'll continue with that idea
of studying methods for solving
recurrences but now I want to try the
only method that we have and see where
it gets us and it's not going to get us
anywhere it's gonna it's gonna be ugly
and anybody who smart enough to see how
to fix that method don't volunteer to
show me now I want to pretend that we're
really at a dead end there is actually a
way to fix it but we're not going to fix
it we're just going to be at a dead end
but I want you to at least understand
why it's a bad way to go or why it looks
like a bad way to go here's our method
our method is to get rid of the T n
minus two and get rid of the T n minus
one by reusing this formula and
substituting it so let's let's do it
piece by piece so let's start with T n
minus 1 TN minus 1 equals 2 TN minus 3
plus TN minus 2 plus 1 and let's put it
back in there and see what we get
TN equals who can do it 2 TN minus 2
plus TN minus 2 gives 3 T n minus 2 plus
TN 2 TN minus 3 plus we're taking this
and putting it in there plus 2 good you
feel good about this we can continue now
we could do two TN like 3 TN minus 2
here and do another substitution but it
looks like things are just getting ugly
for one thing I have no idea really what
these numbers are turning into I don't
see a pattern oh maybe it's the
Fibonacci numbers no that's not
but be cool if it were and what's going
on here am I gonna get like ti- for the
next time I mean I'm trying to get rid
of these things and it looks like
they're growing we could do another step
we could do a few more steps but we
would start to give up this isn't so
helpful so at this point you come see me
and my cubicle or you give up and you
just go on to another problem or and
this is what should always do I don't
have a clue how to do it with my power
method so let me see what the answers
are at least hiking let's do it first
you are in the base case ok so how do
you get t3 t3 is to find through this
through this recurrence right t 3 is 2
times t1 plus t2 plus 1 that's 2 times 1
plus 2 plus 1 which is 2 plus 2 plus 1
is 5 I'll do the next one it's going to
be 2 times the 1/2 before it plus 1
times this so 2 times 2 is 4 plus 5 plus
it's 10 2 times the 1 twice before 10
plus 10 plus 1 all right what's the next
one
not Sam somebody else
one more one now let's look at this
table and see if we can find a pattern
this isn't like I wrote down some
bizarre sequence of numbers there's a
lot of patterns here it doesn't take a
genius to see some kind of pattern here
something's going on that we can write
down so let's write down what it is even
if we don't have a clue as to how to
solve this recurrence equation well
we're going to write down as something
that we will have a clue how to solve
and that's going to actually give us a
solution to the whole thing which is
very pretty yes what relationship do we
see here it doubles I heard it about
eight times good if the number is an
even number it gets doubled and get one
add it to it if the number is an odd
number just doubles maybe that's just
coincidence and the next number that
won't work for it really does how do you
know when you just see something that's
coincidence and when you don't
there's a famous function I think it's
this one every anxiety's if this one or
this one is it is it this one
then it gets your prime numbers and I'm
not sure if it's plus or Mike
there's a function if you put numbers in
the first forty numbers you put in you
get prime numbers and the 41st one
number you put in you don't get a prime
number I don't know if it's this or not
but I could figure out which one and the
41st number you can factor it so it's
clearly not a prime number but if you're
the kind of person that just tries say
10 and that's a good enough sign then
they'll say well there's a formula that
generates prime numbers but it's not so
we have no guarantee that this pattern
is going to continue we have every right
to conjecture as curious skeptical
people that it's true but we're gonna
have to prove it's true right and how do
you know when you've really discovered
something that's true and you can prove
it and something that's just the red
herring well that's you never know and
you get better and better
the more of these you do so here's our
conjecture as you've all said it T of N
equals 2t n minus 1 plus 1 when n is
even or odd when n is odd and when n is
even C of n equals no I think we did it
backwards huh
I think this end should be even now
what's sloping what check it if n is
even then I double I double the previous
one if n is even I double the previous
one and that's all I do I want to erase
the minimum number of sums we had a
right to begin with you were all right
to begin with sorry I switched designed
it let's double check that it's true if
n is 6 it's going to be twice the number
before exactly and if n is say 7 it's
going to be twice the number before plus
1 all right let's look at this
conjecture the only thing we know is
this this for sure is true right this is
not a conjecture this is golden truth
this is a conjecture about the same T
event we're going to prove this
conjecture is true by induction not
because you have to prove it by
induction but because I want you guys to
understand induction and this is a
natural inductive proof and it's really
easy to prove this by induction and
sometimes the easiest inductive proofs
are the ones that you scratch your head
on the most and say I don't get it and
those are the good ones to practice so
if we're going to prove this by
induction this is the first time you've
actually gotten kind of like a double
edged sword with the induction in the
sense that we got a lots of proof here
we got an even case in an odd case and
you'll say do I have to do those
well the good thing about induction is
that you can prove anything by induction
if you want to prove more you get more
in your assumption so you can throw more
into what you want to prove as long as
the assumption to what you want to prove
still works as long as that last
connection still works sometimes the
easiest way to prove something actually
is to prove something harder because
what you gain in the assumption is more
than what you have to end up proving in
the conclusion so ironically with
induction you can sometimes prove harder
things more easily than easy things you
can so here we're going to take this all
as one thing that we want to prove and
we're going to take this induction
assumption that this works for anything
smaller than n I'm going to write down
what we know that we can assume by
induction that T of n minus 1 equals 2
TN minus 2 and that's when the case when
n minus 1 is even and when n minus 1 is
odd we know by induction assumption that
it's 2 TN minus 2 plus 1 this is what I
can use as an assumption this is what I
have is my golden truth and I want to
get to this ok that's our plan I want to
start here get to here use that if I
need to questions so far we'll worry
about the base case later we should have
to show a base case you can show a base
case by checking by the way or enemy you
can just check you can do it if it's not
a hard thing we're just we can do it at
the end ok so here's what we know I'm
going to write this golden truth over
here
copy it down TN equals TN minus 1 plus 2
TN minus 2 plus 1
are going to be true one case and even
one case and odd so let me consider the
case where n is even first I want to get
from here to here I can use these
assumptions how do I do it plug in what
I want this to turn into that I got TN
minus 1 here so wouldn't it be great if
I could just get rid of this and
substitute it with another TN minus 1 I
can look if n is even what's n minus 1
odd that means this is true everyone
agree because that's a smaller case so
instead of TN minus 2 times 2 plus 1
that you see over there I can replace it
with this that equals to TN minus 1 for
the case and even I got that first part
this is one step this isn't a long hairy
proof
this is induction and it's best it's the
slickest proof in the world
boom boom boom we're done all right now
before I go on to the next case and the
people who are making curly Q faces with
their eyes and nose I want to make sure
you're still with me we have this as
truth we have this as an assumption
we're trying to prove this in order to
prove this I try to do it in cases I
said the first case n is even so I write
down my truth again and I notice that if
n is even n minus 1 is odd and if n
minus 1 is odd I can use this step for
my induction assumption and in place of
2 TN minus 2 plus 1 I can rewrite TN
minus 1 and that gives me 2 TN minus 1
done with my proof
start with the same exact truth this is
true that's true for any end even or odd
so we start with the same thing it
equals TN minus 1 plus 2 TN minus 2 plus
1 now if n is odd n minus 1 is not odd
it's even so we can use this as our
assumption so instead of 2 TN minus 2 we
can rewrite TN minus 1 but this time the
plus 1 stays there because we were using
this and what do we get 2 TN minus 1
we started with this assumption we used
our truth we got the next case so show
that this really works you got to show
that it's true for T of say 2 and T of 3
you can start for smaller cases and you
can check it's true because when another
T is 0 so if you want to show that this
is true you just have to show that it's
true for T of 2 and T of 3 right those
are those are the lowest cases that this
means something for and you can check
out works for T of 2 and T of 3 all
right so like ibang induction over your
heads and I tell you how important it is
and maybe you could have come up with a
proof for these things without induction
but if you get good at induction it's
just so slick and so easy that if you're
at a paper by somebody you know what
they'd say they'd say by inspection you
can see these properties and it's an
easy inductive proof that this is true
period and then they're on to the next
paragraph and in that little sentence is
20 minutes of talking right now all
right but that's the assumption people
will have when they're writing things
like this down to a broader audience all
right questions about this so now we've
got that this is true and now we're
ready to move on to the next step and
try to actually get a formula for T
event we still got a long way to go we
still not solved anything
we've just convinced our cell
that this is true and we've gotten out
of the horrible world of this more
complicated recurrence equation and it
turns out that the easiest way to write
the final formula down is to separate
the cases to say that if you have an
even number of discs it takes this many
steps and if you have an odd number of
discs that takes this many steps and if
you try to combine them into one formula
you can do it but the formula looks so
ugly and unpleasant that any
mathematician would never do it they
would just say an odd here's the case
and even here's the case and that's an
aesthetic judgment but you could always
come compose two functions into one
uglier one with negative one to the ends
and all sorts of weird things like that
let's work with this now that we've got
the double n minus 2 and n minus one out
of there and we're down to just n minus
1 things look good but let's think about
what happens here when we did these
repeated substitutions before the
pattern started to repeat why because we
did the same thing every single time
look what happens here we need to
repeated substitution the first time you
double the previous one but then it's an
odd number so the second time you got to
double it and then add one and then you
got to go back and double it so you
might not notice the pattern so what
we're gonna do is try to get it to a
point where you can just use the same
thing repeated all the time and what I
mean by that is the following we're
going to run the substitution through so
that T of n for even numbers depends on
T of n for other even numbers and T of n
for odd numbers depends on T of n for
other odd numbers so the same thing
happens every time through so when it
gets a shift back and forth between
these two repeated substitutions SAN
doesn't like this idea maybe even do
this at your seats Sam I know you've
already done it at your seat so let's go
ahead and run this through once T of N
equals 2t n minus 1 what happens when
you try to substitute for T n minus 1
here's T n minus 1 if we're going to
start with this then TN minus 1 uses
which recursion uses the second one so
TI minus 1 will be 2 TN minus 2 plus 1
take it back in here what do you get
for CN minus two plus two that's when n
is even here's what I did for those of
you who didn't follow that last step I
just took this as a starting point and I
substituted for T n minus one by using
the second one because it switched from
even to I so I took 2t n minus 2 plus
one and put it in place of here and I
got for TN minus two plus two this is
much better because now even numbers
depend on other even numbers and now the
pattern just repeats itself over and
over so I'm going to write that down
for T and minus two plus two when n is
even and who can tell me the appropriate
one when n is on Sam you can tell me you
weren't ready
oh quick somebody beat him somebody beat
him I think it's the same well let's do
it if there's an argument we must do it
let's try if we start with here to n
equal to TN minus 1 plus 1 and then we
substitute for TN minus 1
using this then in place of here comes
in to TN minus 2 that's 4 TN minus 2
plus 1 at the end you get these two
formulas by doing one repeated iteration
either this into this or this into this
depending on whether you start with odd
or depending on whether you start with
even and these two recurrence equations
are true as long as these are true and
now we're going to work with these and
this is what's going to give us a sum
we're going to get more practice doing
Psalms we're going to get an actual
answer and we'll figure out how many
steps it really takes you to solve the
six ring puzzle and how many steps it
solves it takes you to solve a 10 ring
puzzle and things like that who's still
with me nobody
why it's better because then we can just
keep using this one rather than go back
and forth and I guess I can't look it
might not be better maybe you would have
noticed the pattern by going back and
forth repeatedly and we could have just
had one formula but I don't think you
would have noticed the pattern so easily
I think I think I think if you repeat
the same recurrence equation over and
over again in the substitution you have
a much better chance of noticing the
pattern in fact this looks an awful lot
like the towers of Hanoi recurrence
equation instead of 2t n minus 1 we have
40 n minus 2 so if we could do that one
we'll be able to do this one the thing
is John that evens depend on evens so
when I get a TN minus 2 and I want to
substitute for that which one of these
do I use I use this one again and
that'll become TN minus 4 so I use this
one again that's the key thing that I
stay in the same line so you're asking
your so well how would I would have
known to do that you know what you would
have done you would have gone back and
forth here to get one long formula it
would have been just as ugly as you
started and you would have come to me
and I would have given you a hint what
if it's a good idea if we can get even
to even and you would have thought of
this or you would have maybe discovered
it by yourselves to do each of these
separately so this board will be the
even boring even this board over the odd
board alright we want to get rid of this
ni minus 2 the TI minus 2 there stinks
we want just ends on that side no
capital T's no capital T's on the right
side we want a formula for n so to get
rid of the capital T we write down what
it means TN minus 2 equals Andrew all
good morning can you tell me I never
give you a good morning here's a good
morning what does T n minus 2 equal run
it through that formula processing
processing and minus 2 goes in there put
it down minus 2 right into here what do
you get
super what's next what's next the next
step is to get rid of this Tian - -
that's what we're trying to do we're
going to get rid of it so we're going to
put this in its place here's what we get
TN equals 4 and in place of TI minus 2
I'm going to put big brackets for T and
minus 4 plus 2 plus 2 get it ok alright
so so Peter help me multiply this out
and see if we can look for patterns what
do I get here 4 squared plus plus 2
times 4 plus 2 good now if you're
inexperienced with this stuff you're not
likely to see the pattern yet but when
you get more experience you are likely
to see the pattern you'd have to do it
maybe one or two more times if you're
just really learning this stuff to see
the pattern but try to get a sense of
what's happening I just did it twice I
got an exponent of 2 here that's an easy
pattern to notice I did it twice and I
got 2 plus 2 times 4 what's going to
happen next time maybe you see it maybe
you don't let me help you next time all
this stuff is going to get multiplied by
by 4 so the 2 here is going to become 2
times 4 the 2 times 4 here is going to
become 2 times 4 squared and then we got
an extra 2 that we add on at the end so
this will end up having just what it is
now except with a 2 times 4 squared
extra term what happens is we're getting
a geometric series there 1 4 4 squared
with a 2 in front of each piece let me
show you what it would look like if we
did it again T of N
for cubed T and TN - what - six anybody
mind if I write three times - we did it
three times we took two away it's easier
to write it that way because when we do
it R times this is going to be R times -
right right don't write it that way plus
two plus two times 4 plus 2 times 4
squared already changed the order here
so you can see it in ascending order
that's what would happen if you did it
three times and now if you you can
always do this brute force not just
guess if you're not sure do it multiply
it out see what happens don't simplify
it like Sam was kind of kidding before I
think he was kidding it don't simplify
it leave it in this pattern so you
notice the pattern there's no great goal
to square it out and say oh I got the
number like my sixth grade students will
do that's what they do right away and
they be really proud because for them
multiplication and addition is
challenging so for them the goal is to
add this as fast as possible and get the
right answer and the real goal is to see
the pattern right and would make it
harder to son later perhaps but oh maybe
not you could do that we could do that
let's do this R times 4 to the R T and
minus 2 R plus and here's the sum - I'm
going to factor out the 2 if nobody
minds because there's a 2 in every term
1 plus 4 plus 4 squared what's the last
term for the R minus 1 one less than the
number of times we've done it right this
is 4 cubed we get up two squared that's
very common that you get one off thing
doing these kind of substitutions is
that similar things happen every time
and you might wonder and sometimes
students ask
well why don't we just do it for some
general formula and see what happens and
summarize all our results and that's
just what's a mathematician did and
that's called the master theorem and it
summarizes just what complexity you get
if you do this with some general kind of
formula and you see what happens you'll
notice when you do this you get two
pieces this sum piece right and this
piece here that sometimes disappears and
sometimes turns into something sometimes
this is going to be the major part of
your complexity sometimes this is
sometimes they're the same the master
theorem basically looks at the function
in advance and looks at these different
numbers and tells you whether this is
the main piece or that's the main piece
and it only works for certain recurrence
equations it actually doesn't work for
this one you'd have to do this one plane
you can't use the master theorem for
this one the master theorem works for
equations that come out of polynomial
time algorithms equations where you're
dividing we divide and conquer rather
than subtract and conquer so the master
theorem will give you answers so you
don't have ever have to do sums for
those kind of recurrence equations but
there are some you'll have to do sums
for so keep your skills sharp here's
what we're up to there's two pieces we
still want to get rid of this T and the
way to get rid of it is we have to go
ahead and ask ourselves what's the base
case for n even what is it N equals two
right N equals two is the smallest one
and see if two equals one two that's our
base case so we'd like this number here
to turn into a two and we're going to
make our as big as we need to have it be
in order to have this turn into it to
boards we want n minus 2r to turn into a
two what should our be then
of zero equals zero we could do that I
didn't use that as the base case and
that would work just as well I just
didn't do it and this will work just as
well too so let's stick with this and
and but you're right I could have used T
of zero equals zero but I'd never even
use that as a base case I assume there
are no puzzles with zero rings because
they wouldn't sell for a lot
well wait here's another one here I'll
give you it for ten bucks I got it I can
I'm gonna buy the whole world one of
those oh yeah I guess the bar cost money
remove the bar all right let's do this
this T Peter to disappear the way it
disappears is one the inside of the
function here where the parameter
becomes two so I can substitute T of two
for two
and you got it so we just got to make R
equal n minus 2 over 2 and that'll make
that disappear so here's what we got
cm N equals 4 to the 4 to the n minus 2
over 2 4 to the R times what's this
going to be it's going to be 2 TF 2 is 2
so x 2 plus now let's do the formula
anybody remember how to add up this
formula oh it's a mess for to the R
you go up to the next exponent you
subtract off that one and you divide by
four minus one all right let's do it
yeah we're gonna do this together I'm
gonna do this piece together X equal one
plus four plus four squared up to four R
minus one
what do you multiply both sides by five
we're doing our trick we multiply both
sides by four so that shifts everything
down to four four squared four to the R
minus one and four to the r then you
subtract then you have four to the R
minus one equals three X so X our
original formula equals four the RM
minus one divided by three
that's the general way to do any
geometric series we did it last time it
always works it's a good trick and it
works for things that aren't even
geometric series if I put the numbers
one two three four five in front of
these numbers it would work also right
but we'd have to do it how many times we
have to do it twice right so you can you
can do any kind of weird series with
this trick as long as there's some nice
order to it
all right that's review and I was gonna
skip it but I'm glad I didn't I suppose
since too many looks of confusion now
we've got this but we have to plug in
something for our it's got to be an
minus two over two well look we got this
nice answer now for an even but but what
a mess can we simplify it we can
simplify it a lot if you have a number
here 4 to the N minus 2 divided by 2
what is that the same as 4 to the N
minus 2 times 4 to the 1/2 what's 4 to
the 1/2 square root of 4 is 2 right so
what this really is this piece here is
really equal to 2 times 4 to the n minus
2 okay
that piece here
no four to the L minus 2 times 4 to the
1/2 is going to be 4 to the N minus 3
steps
I didn't do what I meant sorry I'm wrong
times B is 4 to the a to the B that's
what I meant to do I need the high
school practice sorry if you have two
numbers up in an exponent you can do
this
it mean the same thing so I took the 1/2
out and I left the N minus 2 up there
and this is a trick even though I did it
wrong two seconds ago this is the right
way to do it and this is a trick which
comes up a lot in simplifying complexity
formulas what's 4 to the 1/2 it's 2 and
that's 2 to the n minus 2 that is right
and we've got another 2 here so T of N
equals 2 to the N minus 1 plus now we
got to work with this piece yeah but
this piece isn't so bad let's make a 2/3
so I'll pull a third out this way and
inside I have this what does this turn
out to be we just did this
- to the N minus -2 so here's what I get
and we're still going to work a little
bit more with this two-thirds 2 to the N
minus 2 minus 1 can I do a little bit
more what if I put I could run the 2
through to make this the same as the 2
to the n minus 1 so I get 2 to the n
minus 1 plus what 2 to the n minus 1
over 3 minus 2/3 everybody check me this
is just where I'm gonna make a dumb
mistake did I do everything ok so far
yes ok so far almost done 2 to the n
minus 1 plus 2 to the n minus 1 over 3
is how many 2 to the N minus ones 4/3
4/3 2 to the n minus 1 minus 2/3 now I
can make this a little better I know
it's been going the going too slow here
mmm too fast here I can put another 2 in
here
one of those twos threw it back in there
and now I got the simplest way that I
can think of writing this this is what I
have in my notes I handed out 2/3 2 to
the N minus 1 6 rings 2 to the 6 is 64
64 minus 1 is 63 63 divided by 3 is 21
21 times 2 is 40 to 42 slide moves to
take this ring off 8 it's going to be
bigger 10 is going to be even bigger my
friend bought these
first class and he bought ten ring
puzzles yikes all right I am I I have
more stuff to do but I'm not going to do
the odd case I'm gonna leave the odd
case for you to practice but I'll tell
you what you get I get 1/3 2 to the N
plus 1 minus 1 it'll be good practice to
do the odd case so I'll just write up on
the board what the answer is the numbers
the the basic recursion that you have to
prove you can't do the formula any
better than we did before right you can
work out photos but this instantly gives
you the numbers and since the ones are
appearing every other stuff you're going
to get through the 1 plus Sam's right
and and what's more this is a classic
example of two ways of looking at the
same thing sometimes when you try to
come up with a formula to express
something you can do it but you get this
big ugly thing when a more natural way
to express it as just a parent looking
at it in a different way and this is a
good example of that
where you just get binary numbers with
alternating zeros and ones and you'll
see things like this come up again and
again
want to know how many steps it takes to
solve a puzzle with n rings just take a
binary number of length N and alternate
the bits 1 0 1 0 1 0 and that'll and
then convert that to binary yeah
means shift over and add a zero or you
double and add 1 which means shift over
and add a one think this would I don't
think it would affect anything we did
we'd still have to do everything we did
to actually get a formula but what Sam's
noticing is that is that you can write a
different program to do this one that
just gives you the answer by generating
the binary number of length N and then
doing you know 2 to the N plus it is a
different way to look at it Peet's all
right these represent binary numbers
zero zero zero zero zero zero 1 is 1 0 1
2 3 4 5 6 7 I just wrote them around now
it does alright and you're playing a
game with with some kid ok either your
own kid or your a camp counselor or who
knows what you spin the style lululu it
tells you how many things to move
alright these kind of spinner things
come up not just in games but in all
sorts of mechanical contraptions and you
need to be able to see where it lies
what number it's over it's fine what if
you wanted to build something like this
electronically this is the this is where
gray coats originally came from I know
you don't know what they are yet but
you'll find out what they are in a
second if the spinner is lying over this
region it's pretty clear that the number
7 but when the spinner gets close to the
edge it's not really clear and you play
these games there's a big argument
whether you should spin again or whether
you know and people bang down you know
that's a tie no it's not it's on this
blah blah blah so but a machine that's
supposed to figure out which side it's
on has the same
trouble you have to build a machine
that's going to do it and sometimes it's
just too close to take the pickup so
here's how somebody builds a machine
like this they have a binary sensor that
sits here in this circle okay and
basically it's supposed to see whether
there's something on top there and then
there's a sensor for the next concentric
circle and a sensor for the next
concentric circle and if they's these
all things light up one then the number
seven and if these light up in the
number zero but here's the thing what
happens if it's right on the line so
that the sensors can't tell whether it's
zero one here what kind of numbers could
show up any numbers anything this could
be a 0 1 this could be a zero runner
this could be a zero one so any number
might show up and on the display it
would say anything from zero one two
three four five six seven randomly
depending on which sensor actually got
some blinked in the details of the
electronics so you'll want to design
something like this so that when you're
on the line and it doesn't know which
way it is you either get the left or the
right but that's the only two choices
and the way to do that is to order these
binary bits in such a way such that any
two adjacent pieces of pizza have the
same two out of three binary bits and
only one differs so if there's ever an
issue that's the only one it could be an
issue on and whichever one it says will
just give you the left or right so let
me show you an example of this
work well this is terrible this is no
good
oh this is bad bad bad right right so
let's let's actually write it down this
is wrong this won't work you can't do it
in order but this does work zero zero
zero zero zero one zero did I do this
right sorry zero zero one zero one one
zero one zero good zero one one
got a 3-ring Chinese puzzle okay what's
the next step from zero zero zero zero
zero one what's the next step after this
zero what's the next step after this no
what's the next I've f2 this next step 1
1 0 1 1 1 0 1 1 0 0 and my back is the
next one 0 0 0
that's a sequence I want to use and
you'll see why in a second pizza 0 0 0 0
0 1 0 1 1 0 1 0 1 1 0 1 1 1 1 0 1 1 0 0
if you look at this spinner situation
anything that lines up on a line if it
can't tell in the 2nd or 3rd ring what's
going on
they're both zeros so who cares it's not
gonna have any trouble the only place
it's going to have trouble is in one bit
and whichever one it picks is either
this or this one this sequence of
numbers guarantees that this machine is
always going to break a tie on one side
of the other that's really there instead
of coming up with bizarre numbers that
couldn't possibly be there and this
sequence is exactly the same as a
Chinese ring sequence that we did before
and this sequence is called a gray code
a gray code is defined to be a sequence
of binary numbers where each successive
number differs by exactly 1 bit and the
last one differs by the first by exactly
1 bit so it cycles around that's the
definition
there's a lot of different gray coats
the Chinese ring one is only one of them
we could come up with a different
sequence that would come back up here
and be okay if any of you are wondering
whether that's possible it is possible
but we kind of make a standard canonical
gray coat to be the Chinese ring one and
this is it and I want to show you where
this comes from in a more mathematical
way let me show you the the official
inductive definition this gets back to
mathematical induction of how you
construct gray codes here it is gray
codes of size 1 are simple 0 1 ok they
differ by one bit and the last one
difference by the first by 1 bit the way
to construct a new gray code of size 2
is to write the old gray codes down
inductively the last step and write them
down again in Reverse put zeros in front
of the first pet pair and ones in front
of the next pair that's the gray code
for two bits the gray coat for 3 bits is
defined the same way it's an inductive
definition right the two case down right
the two case down and reverse put zeros
in front of the top half and ones in
front of the second half and other stuff
the board already this inductive
definition builds the exact same thing
as your Chinese rings puzzle it builds
the exact same thing as what we did here
on the pizza store
this that needs to position right if
there's one position that's funny that
means that when you're on a line
whichever one of these bits at the sides
on it will always represent a number on
this side or a number on this side if
there were two bits that differ here
then you could get like if this were all
as three zeros and this were all three
ones then the display might say one zero
one and that would be someplace way on
the other side so you'd think the thing
was broken and you'd be right
so this way if it's on the line and it
can't tell you're guaranteed to be on
either side so you want them to differ
by one bit as you go around any time
you're building a machine like this I
suppose or whenever you need it of
course it I don't really know the answer
to the yeah oh sorry oh good idea right
that's a good idea yes exactly
now it's not symmetric not at all if you
look at that so it doesn't mean if I
take the shorter path you mean this way
don't I just go backwards this way can
you go from 0 0 0 to 1 0 0 yeah I
understand it right right right right
but what is a really good question about
the particular Chinese ring the Chinese
ring thing does break down in one place
and that isn't well it's not cyclical
you can go in this direction and in this
direction and back to here you can go
from here to here and in fact you can go
forward to here but when you get to here
you can't go to here and you can't go to
here and the Chinese ring thing these
two do not connect right right and the
Chinese ring thing these two don't
connect 1 0 0 is about the worst thing
you can do in the Chinese ring puzzle if
you get everything off except the last
one and you hand it to somebody you look
how good I'm doing they just smile okay
this is this looks like you've made
progress but you haven't made progress
this is the worst thing you can do
this means the hardest one is still on
all the others are off and you cannot
make the next move back to here so so
the actual Chinese ring they're not
perfectly equivalent that's true that's
true absolutely right absolutely right
sorry Rob it's only asymmetrical if you
asymmetrical in the sense that this move
cannot get to this move and this move
cannot get to this move yes yes yes yes
I understand yes that's a way of looking
at absolutely right right that's a fine
way to look at it yes Chris you had a
question yes zero to one one one is the
real goal this is what you want to do in
the gray coat in the Chinese ring
problem and the Chinese ring problem you
want to go from here to here right oh
stated is the way I stated it before you
take the Chinese you take the gray code
for the N minus one case you take the
reverse gray code you write zeros in
front of the first if you if you want to
say in front of the Chinese rings to
generate gray codes then at this point
you just keep going forward you can keep
going when you have it all on you can go
forward in this direction even though
it's bad progress keep going forward
until you are stuck until you have to
back up right so it really is a line
it's not a cycle if there's two ends and
these are the end points that's what
baroque was saying and I really should
mention that and and distinguish it from
the gray codes word cycle in the Chinese
ring puzzle there is no cycle at the end
you know probably build the puzzle so it
would cycle but then it'd be a
completely trivial puzzle the real thing
that makes us a puzzle is that you cut
the link between the top and the bottom
one last thing before I quit today you
should also notice this symmetry did you
notice how you build these these gray
codes you take the previous one
your
the next one and then you double it
that's very much like the recursion we
did right we did the N minus 2 problem
we reverse the process we put them
together so that's not an accident
either you have to formalize what that
really means but there's a lot going on
here there's a lot of stuff going on
with gray codes I ask you to discover a
lot of it and prove a lot of it on the
problem set some of its going to be
straightforward some of its not going to
be straightforward ask me if you have
questions on it last thing today in
recitation tarah is going to explain the
connection between these things and