so we're going to introduce number
theory today the very very rudiment to
read parts of number theory the parts
that are necessary to understand why
public key cryptography works and that's
our goal and we're going to do all this
unit for that one for that one
destination to talk about cryptography
and in order to start out we're going to
talk about a puzzle that I mentioned
last time briefly a puzzle where you
have two jugs one of size say seven and
one of size 17 and you can pour water or
some fluid back and forth between these
jugs and you want to figure out what
various different amounts you can get by
pouring water back and forth between
these jugs so the the classic puzzle
that you that's even in one of these
movies recently is where you have a 5
and a 3 right a 5 and a 3 and you're
supposed to get you're supposed to get
four and in fact with a five and a three
not only can you get four but you can
get one two three four or five you can
get any of the numbers what we're gonna
do here is we're just going to work with
seven and seventeen as a particular
example to understand this puzzle and
we're going to connect this puzzle to
the fundamental first result in number
theory
something about greatest common divisors
and Euclid's algorithm and from there
we're going to move on toward fancier
stuff okay so the question is here 7 and
undefined
what numbers what values can we get
sitting here in the 17 jug well let me
give you the answer in advance so you
know what to look for and then we'll
actually experiment with it and discover
why these things are true and prove all
these things being true the result in
advance is that the different values you
can get in the 17 are any multiples of
the greatest common divisor of 7 and 17
is is one so any multiples of 1 which
means any number 1 2 3 4 5 up through 17
you can get here if I had it this way
six and eighteen the greatest common
divisor of these two is six and that
means the only value is like he gets
sitting in the 18 jug would be multiples
of six which means six twelve and
eighteen okay that's the secret that's
the answer to this puzzle so now the
question is why is that true what does
this puzzle have to do with greatest
common divisors and in solving this
puzzle you will get an understanding of
the proof of why Euclid's algorithm
works and what greatest common divisors
are and how you compute them quickly in
a better way than you could if I just
presented it straight theorem proof
theorem proof so going through this and
making little lists of numbers will
really really help a lot okay questions
so far okay well let's review how we
solve this we talked about this once I
think before Thanksgiving a little bit
the way we saw that basically is we just
started filling up one jug and pouring
it into the other repeatedly doing that
and we noticed how many things how many
units were in the bigger jug so we'll
call that strategy the 7 to 17 strategy
just taking buckets and buckets filled
with seven and pouring them into 17 and
we're going to notice what values end up
in 17 so at the beginning there's
nothing in 17 we'll call that zero and
then we pour 7 into 17 so there's a 7
what's the next number 14 now it's a
little bit complicated now we pour 7
into the 17 and 3 are necessary to fill
up the 17 then we have to empty the 17
out there's always an implicit emptying
anytime anything gets full because if
you don't empty at that point you've got
a useless container and there's nothing
else you can do except empty it you
can't take anything out it's not allowed
alright so you just can empty it or do
nothing so when it hits 17 you empty it
and there's how much left and the 7
there's 4 left in the 7 because we've
used 3 to fill it and now you take that
4 and continue pouring it into the 17
leaving you with I did it right 4
need a longer place to make this list
I'll just continue here eleven what's
next it goes up to 18 right so there's
one left over there's a fast way to
calculate this what these numbers really
are are multiples of seven but when you
get to 17
you subtract off a multiple of 17 so
these numbers are what we sometimes call
multiples of 7 mod 17 mod 17 is means
you care only about the remainder with
respect to 17 so anytime you go over 17
you wrap around so you can get these
numbers quickly without imagining your
head the pouring but just doing the
arithmetic 7 14 21 21 is for bigger than
17 so it's 4 11 18 18 is one bigger than
17 so it's one everybody got it all
right so tell me the next gazillion
numbers oh wait wait hey 15 I got to
check yet 5 I'm going up here 12 to 9 16
6 13 3 10 17 is the same as 0 we there
you go that's the list the list is
exactly 17 numbers long because every
number appears exactly once they're
between 0 and 16 or it should I think it
includes everything
the greatest common divisor of those
numbers so if you believe my result it
really should be every number exactly
once
all right questions so far all right the
only other way to do this problem
there's really only two ways to do this
problem if at any point along this
method you back up you're just going in
Reverse or you've lost all the water in
your pile and you have to just start
from scratch so there's only one way to
really do this puzzle is is keep going
if you back up then you're really doing
the opposite strategy which is a 17 to 7
strategy I'll put that here and in a 17
to 7 strategy the same thing happens but
you get different numbers the same
numbers but in a different order so if
we go 17 to 7 what's the first number in
the 17 jug 10 right you pour 17 into the
7 there's 10 left and 17 job what
happens the next time 3 what happens the
next time all right what's going on here
come
what's going on let me list them out 10
3 13 6 16 just right 9 to 12 5 15 8 1 11
4 14 7 0 to 10 what's happening here
multiples of seven because we keep
putting seven more in the thing of 17
but here what we're really doing is
taking away 7 every time every time we
go into 7 we're pulling 7 out of the 17
jar so these are negative multiples and
that just gives you the same list but in
reverse order it's kind of what you'd
expect from a negative sign in front of
an equation all right so this is this
the beginning we're ready to make the
next step other questions so far ok
here's what I'd like to do before we
move on I want to make the connection to
greatest common divisors here and why
they show up and here's one way to make
that connection while we go through this
procedure from 0 down here to the
greatest common divisor which shows up
here in a seemingly magical way what I
want to do is keep track of how many
times we filled up that 7 in order to
pour it into the 17 and how many times
we empty the 17 in order to accomplish
this task okay so do it do it in your
heads how many times did we fill up the
7 in order to do that how many times did
we take away the 17 the first part is
easy how come just count one two three
four five right you filled up the seven
five times that's what these numbers are
every single time means you've poured
another seven in how many times in that
process did we have to empty the 17 once
here right once going from here to here
and once going from here to here any
time the numbers go back down it means
you emptied out of 17 so we can
represent that in the following way 5
times 7 minus 2 times 17 it's not
surprising that that equals 1 that just
represents what we've done in order to
get to this point in the puzzle we
filled the 75 times we empty the 17
twice and we were all done doing that we
had one left in the 17th
you could do this for any one of the
rows we're going to concentrate on the
greatest common devisor one because i'll
because i'll tell you why in a second
but we could do this for any of the
roads keeping track of how many we
filled up each one questions so far if I
told you in advance I knew a way of
combining 7 and 17 you know with a
positive number and a negative number in
order to get one so I told you 5 times 7
minus 2 times 17 you could have gone
ahead and known that there was a
solution to this puzzle because if
there's a way to combine these things
and there's a way to move the buckets
one way to the other to get that way so
these two things are kind of the same
but how do you come up with these
numbers where does the 5 and the 2 come
from besides doing the puzzle is there
another way to get these numbers the
answer is there is and we'll talk about
it in a second before we do that let's
say I showed you a way to get one how
would you know you could get to do two
of them together do it again
make it 10 times 7 minus 4 times 17
double it how many more times would it
take us in order to see that 2 in the
bucket if we double this then instead of
filling the 7 5 times we filled it 10
times so just count down 5 1 2 3 4 5
there's 2 1 2 3 4 5 there's 3 1 2 3 4 5
there's 4 I will go through these
numbers in order counting by 5's and
make sure I get every single one and
that's in some sense the reason I know I
can get all the things from 1 to 17
because if I can show you I get 1 then
all I have to do is count down 5 more in
my big cycle and I will get to the next
highest number and I will keep doing
this until I get all the way through 16
so from now on we don't care about the
question about how we get all the rest
of the numbers we care about how we get
the smallest one if the smallest one is
1 we can get all of them if the smallest
one we can get is 2 then we get
multiples of 2 if the smallest one we
get is 3 then we get multiples of 3
let's go to this side
combination does this one correspond to
it's different than that what are we
doing here here we're filling up
Seventeen's right and we're subtracting
off seven so it's one one two how many
how many 17s get filled up how many 7s
get subtracted that doesn't count as a
filled up 17 no but let me answer the
second question first cuz I think it's
easier how many sevens get subtracted
minus 7x just count how many times we've
done it one two three four five six
seven eight nine ten eleven twelve
twelve times we empty out seven and how
many times do we fill up seventeen we
said five five anyone else think it's
five go through it and ask yourself how
many times seventeen gets filled five
right it's anytime the the numbers
switch their order so it is five and
that should also equal one 85-84 that's
one these are different numbers in front
of the 7 and 17 this five and five is
completely coincidental okay it is
hardly ever the same number that's
complete coincidence these two numbers
are different than these two numbers two
different ways of getting one as a
combination of seven and seventeen one
with a positive one with a negative and
one from this way of doing the solution
and one from this way of doing the
solution okay questions so far you count
how many times you actually pour the 17
in so the first time when it's full does
count so it should be five altogether
accident whenever you notice stuff like
that you got to wonder if it's an
accident sometimes it is sometimes it
isn't so it's not an accident here and
the next connection to make is once you
figure out these numbers the five and
the two is there a fast way without
going to this chart and actually
counting down of calculating of
and the twelve but before we do that
connection let me go back to this
picture in this picture the same as
before how many times does it take us to
get to this one it takes us 12 times
right so presumably if we went another
12 we would get to two just like over
there 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 and
every 12 will take us up one more
because every time you add in another
copy five 17s and take away 12 7s that
is another one so you add an extra one
into your bucket so same thing here it's
the same idea well if you get one you
can get two and then three and then four
then five and then six okay questions
Joe okay yeah okay
you look good yeah you know you're
handed making sure all right next step
how do we go from these numbers to these
numbers
where's the connection I want to show
you in this example because later on
when you see this stuff in general it's
going to seem too abstract and you'll
lose it unless you have an example to to
to hang on to so here's our example well
maybe some of you can even see how to
get there but here's the idea if you
want to figure out how to move from this
five
number you subtract it from 17 you put
it there you take this number and you
subtract it from seven and you put it
there
want to convince you that it's not magic
that it actually makes a lot of sense
let's take 17 minus 5 and put it in
front of 7 and let's take 7 minus 2 and
put it in front of 17 let's multiply
this out you get 7 times 17 over here
and that cancels with 7 times 17 over
here what's actually left after those
two things cancel minus 2 times 17 plus
minus 2 times 17 what does that equal 1
that's what we started with all this
trick does is in a sneaky way add
something and subtract the same thing so
if the original equals 1 the new
combination has to equal 1 it's actually
easier to see this trick in general
because you'll see the A's and the B's
cancel but let me review the trick again
if you have a set of numbers 1 times 7
minus the other times 17 equaling 1 you
can get a different set by taking your 5
subtracting it from the 17 taking your 2
subtracting it from the 7 putting those
two numbers respectively 12 and 5 in
front of 17 and 7 notice they reverse
the order 1 that used to be positive
becomes negative 1 that used to be
negative becomes positive and it also
equals 1 because what you've really done
is really added 7 times 17 and subtract
7 times 17 to the total you're going to
see this idea again and again but I want
you to see it first in this example are
there questions about it
here and you're gonna you're gonna get
review if you haven't gotten it now
you'll have another chance to grab it
later but but look at it now and make
sure it makes sense questions so far yes
different solutions to this equation
remember a GU ball and the fact that you
could get certain scores with it the
reason why you can get certain scores in
that problem it's exactly because there
are two distinct ways of solving this
and it's going to be crucial in
understanding the solution of that
problem in understanding these two
different ways you need both ways right
and you'll see that when we get to that
problem later today and the actual
cryptography stuff you don't really need
both these ways you need you need a
theorem that builds on this the
cryptography stuff is not going to use
this directly it'll use a theorem that
builds on top of this it'll use a
theorem called firm Oz theorem or for my
little theorem to distinguish it from
his last theorem it's a theorem that
Vermont came up with about modulo
numbers and relates to this but we're
not up to there yeah we got away still
other questions yeah
going reverse there so they're going
forward is doing multiples of 7 here
going forward is doing multiples of -7
doing multiples of -7 mod 17 is also the
same as doing forward well you tell me
minus 7 is what with respect to 17 when
you're doing modulo
zero all the way up to 16 right so if I
go - 7 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 where do I hit what
number is this 10 so going back by
sevens in modulus 17 is the same as
going forward by tens 10 20 20 months 17
is 3 13 23 23 months 17 is 6 16 26
there's a very very regular pattern here
there's not too much going on once you
look at it but if somebody just shows
you the sequence to begin with you might
not notice that pattern okay questions
more questions good questions so far any
anything else before we we shift gears a
teeny bit
Euclid's algorithm but it's not really
shifting gears Euclid's algorithm is
going to get right back to the question
of what does having a combination of 7
and 17 with a plus and a minus equaling
1 what does that have to do with 1 being
the greatest common divisor and Euclid's
algorithm is a way of showing that those
two are identical if you have to number
7 and 17 and you can combine them in a
combination this number times 7 minus
this number times 17 and you can get 1
that means 1 is a greatest common
divisor okay so find the greatest common
divisor just figure out a way of getting
that linear combination so in order to
convince you of this I need to tell you
what Euclid's algorithm really is and
then a way of using it to backtrack up
and get these coefficients in front of
the 7 and 17 so the best way for me to
do this is to show you an example with 7
and 17 you could say algorithm like a
lot of the stuff you end up learning
about Euclid is always kind of the last
thing in one of his books there's 13
books and his elements and this is one
of the last things in one of his books
on on ratios and it shows up again in
one of his books on on arithmetic and
it's kind of a climax so it's something
that he thinks was really cool and it
basically works like this I won't
present it to you the way that he did
because it would be obscure but I'll
present it to you the way you'd think of
it as a scheme programmer in a recursive
way in fact I'm pretty sure it's one of
the like page four of Sussman's book you
must have this example somewhere does he
all right so it's a classic recursive
algorithm here's what Euclid says Euclid
says look if I you give me two number
seventeen and seven for example then the
greatest common divisor of these two
numbers is the same as the greatest
common divisor of these two other
smaller numbers that I will tell you how
to get and here's how to get them take
your smaller number and use that as your
bigger number for the next pair divide
the smaller into the larger and take the
remainder for the smaller number of your
new
so seven into seventeen would give you a
remainder of three
Euclid says and he proves that the
greatest common divisor of these two is
equal to the greatest common divisor of
these two right we're not going to prove
it for a couple of reasons
it'll take away from the flow of the
lecture it will tell you something that
is completely true and has been known
true for thousands of years there are
clear proofs written in your book at
every other book in the whole world on
number theory and you can look it up and
you can prove it so take my word for it
now and we'll just continue if these two
are the same as these two then Euclid's
algorithm suggests the recursive style
so who was the first one to use
recursion you can argue you know till
the cows come home about who did it
first but this is clearly a recursive
idea and it's thousands of years ago so
these two are going to be the same as
three and and one and actually you can
take you could step a step further these
two are the same as one end
what's the remainder of one divided into
three no remainder so at this point you
codes algorithm would stop and he'd say
the greatest common divisor is sitting
right here on the left side of the zero
this method always works so before I
show you what this method has to do with
those linear combinations I want to make
sure everybody gets the method this
works for any two numbers to get the
greatest common divisor it is much
faster than the following method which
your typical 8th grader would think of
understanding greatest common divisors
the typical mean how did you do this how
do you do this even today I mean hardly
anybody does UCO's algorithm if you pick
them off the street you know you can do
the little Jay Leno you know thing you
know which way is north but s people you
know which way how do you tie do you
figure out the greatest common divisor
or two things forget actually doing
Euclid's algorithm they're not gonna be
able to do it at all but let's say they
could do it how would you do it if you
picked an eighth grader off the street
how would he pick out the biggest number
that divides these evenly
right he tried dividing by two try
dividing by three and sooner or later he
got the highest one that divides them
equally and if he were a little bit
smarter than the typical person you pull
off the street then instead of starting
at the low end he might start at sixty
right you got no chance starting over
sixty too big so you can start at
sixteen go down and then the first one
that works that's your biggest one and
when you discover that you know the
average young kid is so pleased that he
doesn't have to start from one and go up
and go all the way to sixty that he can
just start from 60 and stop when he gets
it right that he or she feels like
that's a big breakthrough but from a
point of view of an algorithm that
breakthrough is Squa because let's say
the greatest common divisor is really
one that's the worst case then this
better algorithm sure works better in
some cases but in the worst case it's
going to go all the way to the bottom
and try just as many as you did when
you're on going on the way up
what's more how many steps does this
take let's say you can do a division in
in a microsecond right so you got to do
two divisions each step and you got to
do sixty of them so the time complexity
of this algorithm of the take somebody
off the street algorithm it's time
proportional to the smaller of these two
numbers okay so if I asked you to figure
out the greatest common divisor of these
two numbers well first you'd have to
count all the digits to figure out which
one was smaller right I think this one's
smaller and then you'd have to do
518 million steps okay so even on our
powerful computers this would take some
significant amount of time this
algorithm is not so good it's slow so
how fast does Euclid's algorithm go one
of the interesting things about Euclid's
algorithm they said it's not so easy to
analyze nobody's really thrilled to do
it on these two things but if you did do
it on these two things I can give you a
general ballpark of how
steps it would take a general ballpark
of how many steps it would take more or
less is approximately the number of
digits in the smaller number in other
words about nine steps and I'm saying
about in a very unwritten other words
it's proportional not to the size of the
number but to what to the log base
something of the number it's actually
not log base time that's why I said kind
of fuzzy what I said was log base ten
but my log base ten is fuzzy it's it's a
different log you want me to tell you
what it really is it's a cool theorem
I'm not going to prove it to you but
I'll tell it to you it's also in your
book it's called La Mesa theorem and it
basically gives you a sense of how many
steps you codes algorithm takes in the
worst case figure out all the Fibonacci
numbers until you got a Fibonacci number
that's bigger than this okay count how
many steps that's up what Fibonacci
number that was is it the fifteenth is
it the seventh or is it the eighth the
number of the Fibonacci number you have
to get up to in order to get bigger than
this that's the maximum number of steps
you could algorithm takes so it's
actually more than nine but it's
probably I don't know it's probably like
no more than double nine I don't know
the Fibonacci number that's bigger than
this the smallest one it might be the
20th Fibonacci number it might be less
any of you who know if Sam were here he
would tell us which Fibonacci number it
was all right and everyone understand
that theorem Fibonacci numbers are
exponential growth so this is really the
inverse of the Fibonacci numbers which
means it's a logarithm growth and it
doesn't have a particular day sit sky
now this peculiar Fibonacci base so it's
not really based and it's something else
but it is proportional to the number of
digits in the number not the number
itself so Euclid's algorithm is much
better than the naive algorithm it's
much faster and it really really is a
maybe the first good example of an
efficient algorithm yeah I'll do it on
this pair I'll do it on this pair
well I the truth is it like I said 10 15
steps with this but who wants that let's
do this one this is easier take the
smaller one put it here it becomes the
bigger one of your next pair and divide
60 into 128 and what's the remainder 8
that's the next pair the greatest common
divisor of 128 and 60 is the same as the
greatest common divisor of 60 and 8
intuitively I mean I didn't prove it to
you but intuitively this isn't a big
jump I mean whatever goes into 60 is
going to go into 60 whatever goes into
128 is going to go into the remainder of
something that divides into 60 I said I
wouldn't prove it and now I'm doing kind
of pseudo proving and I'm not going to
do it but it's not such a big jump it's
not such a hard proof here's the next
step 8 goes into 60 what's the remainder
4 not 4/3
greatest common divisor here is 4 all
right now we have to get to the
connection between Euclid's algorithm
and the fact that if the greatest common
divisor of two numbers is a particular
number then you can compute a linear
combination of the two numbers one with
a plus 1 on the - that gets you that
number I'm going to convince you that
that's true by doing it a completely
mechanical way in this example my
mechanical method will be completely
general so it won't be a real rigorous
proof but it essentially is a rigorous
proof I'm going to show you it with
complete generality but I'll show you
what with a particular example so I
don't know if the right a's and b's down
that if these two have a greatest common
divisor of 1 that I can multiply this by
something multiply this by something
subtract those two and get
okay so here's how we do it
let's follow Euclid's algorithm through
and keep track of what actually is going
on after this step we know that 17
equals two times seven plus plus three
okay I'm writing the details the
background details I copied seven I got
calculated the remainder that's how you
calculate the remainder you divide 7
into 17 it goes in twice
you got a remainder of 3 okay 17 two
times seven plus three what do you get
from the next step seven equals two
times three plus one good what's the
last step
step is kind of like the just kind of a
base case it's not even so interesting
so we're actually don't really need this
case to show what I want to show I can
stop right here here's the one that I'm
looking for here is the greatest common
divisor of the two numbers I'm going to
show you how to take this sequence of
divisions oh yeah you're right you're
right you're right you're right you're
right I'm going to ignore it just the
same but you're right time 3 equals 0
times 1 3 times 1 plus 0 right right
that's exactly what I'm going to do but
I'm going to ignore that step so don't
look at it I don't need that step it's
when I get down to here that I can stop
and make something interesting happen
convince you that if I can go through
these steps of Euclid's algorithm and
end up with a 1 at the end of my last
step where I know that there's no more
to go
then I'm going to go backwards now and
come up with this linear combination
equaling 1 and my linear combination is
going to be a combinations of sevens and
Seventeen's now when you see this it's
going to seem really straightforward but
I have to tell you that whenever I teach
this people always look at it they nod
their heads incomplete ok I completely
get it
and then when they look at an example
themselves they always forget how to do
it so so make careful notes when you
look at this because it's a little bit a
little bit tricky and I'll do another
example later too to make sure everybody
gets it here's what we're going to try
to do we're going to work our way
backwards we're going to start with this
equation and write down 1 equals 7 minus
2 times 3 well that's great now I have a
linear combination of things multiplied
by 7 and 3 equal
but what I really want is a linear
combination of things multiplied by 7
and 17 so I don't want 7 & 3 here I want
7 and 17 so what's the thing that I
don't like I don't like that 3 okay that
3 is no good I want that to turn into a
17 so now go back up a stage and you can
get a combination that relates 3 to 7s
and 17 I'll write that over here 3
equals 17 minus 2 times 7 and I'm going
to take that combination that helps me
get rid of my 3 and replace it with 7s
and 17 and I'm going to replace it here
were the 3 is that I don't want and
here's what I get next 1 equals 7 minus
2 times 17 minus 2 times 7 so look what
I have now I've got a longer linear
combination of just 7s and 17 when I
unravel that all I get two extra 7s to
combine with this 7 - sorry not to for
extra 7s minus 2 times minus 2 is plus 4
add to the 7 gives you 5 7s and how many
17s do I have negative 2 so I get 5
times 7 minus 2 times 17 that's just
what we had last time when I showed you
how much we counted each bucket in this
case there were only two steps because
there were only two stages and Euclid's
algorithm but if there were many stages
in Euclid's algorithm you'd have to work
your way back up a number of times so I
want to do one like that to make sure
everybody gets this method because this
method of working backwards to show that
the greatest common divisor can always
equal a linear combination of the
original two numbers is a key method
that explains how greatest common
divisors connect to that puzzle problem
yes
but there's also another solution there
is another solution right right
going backwards here when you go
backwards here you always end up getting
one of the solutions and you can get the
other solution by the trick I showed you
before right
yeah Joe if you do it backwards from
Euclid's algorithm well you're asking if
the seven always comes before the 17
can answer your question and we
understand Joe's question Joe is
wondering which solution do we get do we
always get the one with a smaller number
comes first as the positive and the
bigger number is negative or does it
sometimes change you know is there any
one particular way it works out so I
think if we do another example maybe
we'll get some more data next example
146 okay you guys help me fill in the
chart the greatest common divisor of 146
is the same as the greatest common
divisor of what two numbers forty six
and eight eight is the remainder of what
you get when you divide 46 into a
hundred forty six is copied over so you
all see the recursion here right the the
algorithm for these two is the same as
the algorithm for these two you just
make the numbers smaller and the numbers
get smaller fast they get smaller as
fast as Fibonacci numbers grow all right
forty six eight so the next pair is 8 6
and then 6 2 and then 2 zero let's
follow our method by writing down what
each of these lines mean this means that
a hundred equals two times forty six
plus eight
this means that forty six equals
that eight equals one times six plus two
look what happens the remainder here
becomes the multiplier here the
remainder here becomes the multiplier
here and so finally you get down to your
greatest common divisor at the very
bottom and we're there now so this is a
three step process rather than a two
step process like we had before so we'll
have to do one more iteration back in
substituting to get 2 equals some
combination of a hundreds and 46s by the
way can anybody in their head guess what
these two constants are I mean when I
use small numbers you can kind of do it
in your head right when I did seven and
17 you know if you try long enough five
times 17 minus two times seven and you
get the one but for big numbers it isn't
always so easy to guess these things all
right well let's go ahead and do it
while you try to ponder and see if we
can go backwards here so how do we go
backwards again remember we start with
our bottom case we start with two
equalling a linear combination of eights
and sixes so 2 equals I'll write it here
eight minus one times six and we don't
want that's six there we want to get rid
of the six so we substitute in place to
the six a combination of eights and 40
sixes six equals forty six minus five
times eight so this becomes two equals
eight minus one times forty six minus
five times eight did I do everything
right so far let's rewrite this so it
doesn't get too ugly
Sooey equals what's the combinations of
eight and forty six there hmm who can do
it
six times eight right minus one times 46
but that's not right either yet because
we want just 46 twos and a hundreds so
which number do we get rid of now
no not 46 yet we still have to get rid
of the eight we want to keep 46 in the
end right we want to get rid of that
eight how do we get rid of the eight we
want to turn it into things with 46 and
hundreds in them well there it is that
line tells us the relationship between
eight and forty sixes and hundreds so
eight is a hundred minus two times 46
two equals six times a hundred minus
twice forty six minus one times forty
six so two equals now you can combine
everything together do we do it all
right did I make any mistakes I hope not
- 12 - 13 46 is that right and 600 600
so 6 times 100 minus 13 times 46 that's
better equal 2 and now you've got a
linear combination of 146 equaling 2
which is what I promised you we could
get if it was the greatest common
divisor so what do you think Jo what do
you think about your question before you
ask before when we did 17 and 7 whether
the smaller number always appears in the
positive constant it's not necessarily
true right everyone see that it's
switched here maybe if you have an even
number of steps the smaller ones first
and if you had an odd number of steps
the smaller ones second maybe there's a
conjecture well I'm not going to tell
you if that's right or not but it kind
of seems like it might be right I mean
every time you switch the negatives
become positives a positive because
maybe there's something there maybe
that's just a lot of baloney maybe it's
one more slice off the baloney tree I
don't know I'll leave it for you to
think about but anyway you get one
solution and we can get the other
solution by the method I showed you
before so let's write the other solution
down here to remind you how we do that
who remembers how to get the other
solution instead of 13 here what do we
use use the difference between 13 and
100 use 87 and instead of 6 here use use
that means you jumped right ahead to
what I'm gonna talk about next Kristin
it's a good point but hold off with it
for us for a second the question is what
a smallest mean but the answer is yes
all right questions okay so far all
right so so Chris raised the question
which I want to formalize exactly what
it means and and the question is what
are these numbers is there anything
special about the 6 and the 13 and the
40 and the 87 you know that you'll get
one solution by using Euclid's method
and reversing backwards and you can get
the other solution by this relationship
I showed you before and the question is
both number one are there other
solutions are these the only two you
think there's a lot you think there's
more than two I think there's more than
four
you got a trust Chris right I mean he
never says anything unless he's pretty
sure he's right there's an infinite
number here he's right there's an
infinite number of solutions here how do
you get another one
maybe stop so obvious how'd he get
another one he was kind of chris has a
very good intuition he goes yeah you
double it your triplet you know what
happens when you double this you get
four over here no it doesn't quite work
but he's the good thing about having a
good intuition is that there is
something there you just got to figure
out what it was oh that's interesting
what happens if you do that that'll work
right Doug's got a good idea is there a
more general way I'm gonna write
something up on the board to give you at
the most general way we can write
solutions to those here now we're gonna
do sooner or later I have to resort to
some abstraction here it is let's say
the numbers we work with are a and B
instead of 46 and a hundred instead of
seven and 17 a and B are the two numbers
were giving x and y are the two linear
coefficients that we make our linear
combination in order to get the greatest
common divisor of a and B okay so just
to make sure that nobody's lust let's
make sure that everybody knows that in
this case if say a was 17 and B was 7
then what are the X and the y
supposed to be positive numbers
otherwise I'd have to switch the
negatives around so you got to do the
other solution for me
what is it 5 times 17 minus 12 times 7
right remember we did both solutions
there so here we get 5 times 17 minus 12
times 7 and that equals 1 the greatest
common divisor of 7 and 17 so when I
write this down in general I'm really
thinking of this in particular now let's
write down other solutions in fact we're
going to write down all the solutions
go
look I'm jumping ahead
you multiply through this equation you
get 8 times X minus B times y what's
left over let's let's look at just the
plus situations plus NB a minus B na
they cancel each other out if I add any
multiple of B here and had the same
multiple of a here I get a new solution
let's do an example there's nothing like
an abstraction to take away your
intuition let's do an example over here
just use the abstraction to help you
here we've got 17 times 5 and we've got
7 times 12 well we're going to use this
identity and add on multiples of be here
so multiples of 7 pick any multiple you
want your favorite multiple of 7 don't
pick 1742 times 7 and here we're going
to pick 42 times 17 and I claim that
this is going to also be equal to 1
because it's the same as 17 times 5
minus 7 times 12 plus 42 times 7 minus
40 plus 42 times 7 times 17 minus 42
times 7 times 17 now you can actually
calculate this if you wanted to 17
what's 7 times 42 you Munchkins 280 who
picked this number that's a little
tricky somebody work on this while I
work on the 7 times 42 280 290 for $2.99
help me yeah minus 7 times
419 at 7:19 right-center 19 in this 731
there that better work that equals 1
right so anyway and let's we leave that
for the reader where I messed up good
what's 42 times 17 420 and 299 oh thanks
so this is 726 how's that got a chance
now that's good okay thank you Michael
go now I fixed it alright I'm kind of
teasing I mean you can all do the
arithmetic right yeah it's lucky they
didn't test on that particular thing in
my PhD oral qualifying thing okay here's
the point Chris is right his intuitions
right you can get multiples but it's not
multiples of those equations that we
first saw it's multiples of bees add it
to this X and let's say multiple of a is
added to this X and what's more you can
do subtractions the same way this
actually gives you all the solutions
there aren't any others I'd have to
prove that to you but that's true there
aren't any others
so what's true are we getting when we
get these Chris had the sense that they
were the smallest what does that mean I
want to convince you that smallest has a
meaning
look at this since we can add or
subtract multiples of B here let's say
we want this whole thing to be positive
you can subtract or add multiples of B
until it's the smallest positive number
possible right if it's negative add
multiples of B if it's positive subtract
multiples of B just up until you go
negative you can add or subtract
multiples of B until this combination X
plus or minus NV is going to be the
smallest positive number that works
there let's figure it out here what's
the smallest positive number and that's
going to work here well if we subtract
off a multiple of seven where negative
if we add multiples of seven we're
bigger than five so five is actually the
smallest positive number of the form 5
plus or minus seven
multiples same thing here if you
subtract off a multiple of 17 you go
negative here so five and 12 in these
examples in this example here really are
the two smallest positive numbers that
would fit here in this form where you
don't ever want to get negatives just
keep subtracting off multiples of be
here and multiples of a there so in that
sense 5 and 12 are the smallest numbers
at work so I'm going to write this out
rigorously here you can always you can
always pick say W and you wear a W minus
B u equals the GCD and I'm going to give
you restrictions now on W and u they're
both positive W is positive and smaller
than what smaller than any multiple of
seven in this example smaller than any
multiple of B and U is bigger than zero
and smaller than any multiple of a
specific about the two solutions that we
want to get we want to get X and y or U
and W in such a way that the W is
between 0 and B and the U is between 0
and a and we can always do that we can
always do that because of this identity
we can always subtract off multiples if
we're too big or add multiples if we're
too small so write that down maybe I
need to do an example cuz up till now I
think everybody was kind of with me and
now I get like huh whoa what's going on
let me tell you since I I don't want to
spend too long not thinking of this
example I can always do it in recitation
later but let me tell you what will
always happen if you use Euclid's
algorithm you will get one of these
solutions with these restrictions these
restrictions will always hold if you use
our method of switching to another
solution
you know what that method really is it's
a special case of this and you'll always
get the other solution what special case
is it it's this special case if ax minus
B Y say equals 1 then here's the method
we did we did B times a minus y plus a
times B minus X and we said that that
equals 1 remember that's how we got the
other solution
we took this we subtracted it from a
it from B if you add these up you get
the same thing you get here and the BA
and the a B the BA and the AV cancel
identity is what's going on here what's
happening here
had a X here I have minus a times B
minus X that's the same as a times X
minus B so all I did to go from here to
here is take off one multiple of B and
since what I had before was the smallest
positive number that worked when I took
one multiple off I went into negative
land and then I wrote it on the other
side here because it was negative and
now that's the smallest positive number
that works on the other side of the zero
I'm toggling around 0 I'm hovering
around there as close as I can once on
the right side once on the left side so
all we did in that other method I showed
you is a special case of this where the
N is actually equal to 1 and it's a
subtraction what happened with the B
here we had minus B why what do I have
here minus B times y minus a that's what
this is so I took my Y and I subtracted
off a the same way I took my ex and I
subtracted off B what we do here is a
special case of this more general method
subtracting off one multiple of a and
one multiple of be taking our smallest
positive numbers and putting them into
the largest negative numbers then we
reverse the order of them and they
become the smallest positive numbers
again right if you get that great and if
you don't look at it later don't worry
it's not going to kill the flow that's
coming up you can use this method to get
any other solution but you wouldn't you
wouldn't reverse the two necessarily it
wouldn't reverse the the 7 and the 17
from 17 and 7 but you'd still got
another solution
it would just be smaller positive
numbers with a 7 and 17 in the same
order
ad you bottle is a problem that I gave
you on who knows what problems that one
probably right at the beginning of the
of the year and there's a lot of ways to
analyze that problem you can do it by
induction you can just take a particular
example and
throw it at people who are first
learning to do proofs without knowing
any kind of induction just what's the
best can you do with this and now we're
going to completely solve that problem
and it's going to use these tools that
we just learned okay and that will kind
of complete this whole unit on Euclid's
greatest common devisor okay and then
I'm then I'll quit today what we're
going to do next time is add from Oz
little theorem on top of this move on to
cryptography all right so let's let's do
this example today here's the Adu ball
problem you're given a game where you
can score seven points or you can score
four points and the question is what are
the possible total scores that you can
get and get multiples of seven plus
multiples of four right what are they
and it turns out that if the two
possible scores are given have a
greatest common divisor of one if they
have a greatest common divisor of one
then here's the solution to that problem
completely the number of different
scores you can get is anything from
seven minus one times four minus one and
up anything equal or bigger to this
number you can get so this is a what is
this six times three which is eighteen
you can get 18 and any number higher
than 18 you cannot get seventeen
otherwise we'd say you can get seventeen
in any number higher than 17 so you
can't get 17 you might be able to get
some of the other numbers lower than 17
but you're not going to get a continuous
sequence of numbers from 1 point to
infinity until you hit 18 from 18 and on
your safe that may be true yeah Sam has
some other interesting problems like for
example for the numbers bigger than 18
how many different kind of scores can
get each number that's a different
question for the numbers below 18 how
many of them can you actually achieve
and Chris says that Sam proved that it
was half of those numbers okay
I imagine that's true but I don't see
why right away we're not going to
concentrate on any of those
generalizations we're going to
concentrate just on the straightforward
problem
how do we know we can get 18 and above
and we're going to do two things here
part of which will be good review for
those of you who still feel I don't get
mathematical induction and for those of
you who feel that you do get it it'll be
good review anyway I'm going to try to
go through a proof by mathematical
induction to show you that I can always
get any number with seven and four so
it's going to be a phony proof and you
got to figure out where this proof
breaks down I'll show you where it
breaks down but in this case the place
where it breaks down is going to give us
a real clue as to actually figure out
where it doesn't break down and when we
try to nail down where it doesn't break
down that will bring us back to Euclid's
greatest common divisor that we just
finished talking about so it's all going
to come together we'll solve Adu ball
and I should tell you in advance that if
you add one more score here that this
whole method doesn't work anymore and it
becomes a much harder problem so two
scores we can handle it but three scores
it's tricky yeah question Chris it's one
minus one less than this one less than
this multiply them yes yes this theorem
is not true if the greatest common
divisor is not one the greatest common
divisor must be one no not well not that
I know of I don't know the whatever
theorem is true for when the greatest
common divisor isn't one I'm not sure
what it is but I bet you can come up
with a nice generalization but we're not
going to do it today so let me write the
theorem out if you're given a B where
the GCD of a B is one then for every N
minus one there exists an X and a y such
that ax plus B y equals n will call us
the Adu ball theorem and now you know
why I never write theorems in the board
because all you do when you see stuff
like this is write it down you lose
track of what we're thinking about and
most people aren't used to seeing things
like this and making sense out of it
this is the way you'd write it down
given a and B where the greatest common
divisor is 1 then for every end greater
than or equal to a minus 1 times B minus
1 there are two numbers both greater
than 0 such that a time's the first plus
B times the second equals that end ok
that's what we're trying to prove
gonna do a phony proof by induction then
I'm going to fix it
here's my phony proof by induction oh
base case I'm going to show this is true
for N greater than or equal to a okay so
my base case is use 1a and no B's okay
so my base case is a check okay so I'm
gonna I'm gonna stress anything that
isn't true I'm going to show you can go
from a all the way up to anything you
want and here's my proof my base case is
a and now I'm going to assume that N
equals some combination you know what I
think it's better if I don't do it with
a z' and B's I'm going to do it with
what did I start with four and seven so
my base case will be four and I'm going
to assume that n is four X plus seven
one you know what X's and Y's are going
to confuse people because I use them
before for greatest common divisor so
I'm going to use R and s
true that you have some number equal a
combination of our fours and s 7s and it
equals N and we're due yet we have to
get to n plus 1
everybody with me so far
base case is just for use one for we can
score for R equals 1 s equals 0 so N
equals 4 R equals 1 s equals 0
check mm-hmm Heather what I would I
would but I'm making a phony proof that
starts from 4 and I want you to show me
at what point here I make a phony step
right I'm not going to prove this by
induction the right way we're not even
going to fix it we're just going to make
something that doesn't work and leave it
that way
that I'm doing this you'll see it'll
make it'll make the way though it does
work make more sense okay I got an as a
multiple of fours and 7s and I want to
get n plus 1 big question mark well
here's where you clubs greatest common
divisor comes back into play if we know
that the greatest common divisors are 4
& 7 is 1 then we know two things 2 times
4 minus 1 times 7 equals 1 right
remember we can write those I did that
fast I did that in my head I didn't go
through the whole algorithm but you'd
get that from the algorithm what's the
other pair what's the other solution 3
times 7 minus 5 times 4 remember how do
you get that some of you do how do you
get it
four minus one gives you the three seven
minus two gives you the five okay so
there are two solutions we know they're
true well I'm going to use these because
they're going to be really helpful I'm
going to add 1 to N and I'm going to add
say this part to the 4r plus 7s so I'll
get what I'm adding to fours here so I
get 4 times R plus 2 plus 7 times s
minus 1 right 7 times s minus 1 and
there's n plus 1 whoo-hoo I'm done right
4 times something plus 7 times something
this he says it's only if you can score
negative points what does that mean well
this is definitely positive right I
added 2 to our R is positive that's our
assumption s is positive that's our
assumption R plus 2 is positive s minus
1 is that positive not necessarily
because s could have been could have
been 0 could have been 0 and then that
would be negative so this is a complete
phony proof this is a proof which
started with an assumption that N equals
4 times R plus 7 times s where R and s
are bigger than or equal to 0 and then
prove that n plus 1 equals 4 times
something plus 7 times something where
the two things are not necessarily equal
to 0 so you went from your inductive
assumption to some other thing which was
not what you were trying to prove we
didn't get a strong enough proof here
this is has to be positive for this
induction to work otherwise we haven't
proved the n plus first case we've
proved some other here so I'll say ok
well that didn't work I'll try this one
there it also equals
seven times s plus three and what do I
get here four times R minus five over
here I get the same annoying problem
this one's fine but this one might not
be fine
right so we can't fix this proof unless
we could guarantee that either s was
bigger than or equal to 1 or R was
bigger than or equal to 5 so now we've
gotten a big hint as to what number this
is going to work for this is going to
work as long as s is bigger than or
equal to 1 or R is bigger than or equal
to 5 maybe that gives us some kind of
clue we're gonna stop here to try to fix
it and we're going to work in a
different direction
to actually see which numbers will have
this criterion working for them ok so
we're almost done here let me stop for a
second other questions we're gonna fix
this proof this proof now stinks and
it's not true and you can't get every
number just from a or four all the way
on up so what's the smallest number that
you can do this trick for then you can
do this inductive idea and that you can
use Euclid's algorithm for we're going
to calculate exactly what that number is
and that number better be in this case
18 and in general it's going to be a
minus 1 times V minus 1 let's say I have
a number for R plus 7s instead of going
our way up which we realize doesn't
always guarantee us that we get numbers
bigger than 0 let's try to work our way
down I mean we know that this works for
say I don't know 20 right R equals 5 s s
equals 0 let's work our way down from 20
and try to figure out the first place
we're working our way down doesn't end
up giving us a legitimate answer the
first place where that happens that's
going to be our base case otherwise
it'll always work fine on the way down
let's find the first place on the way
down where it doesn't work ok so instead
of working our way up and getting some
open-ended kind of thing let's work our
way down and figure out the first place
where it messes up working our way down
will correspond to taking away 1 instead
of
this is not an inductive proof anymore
this is just logically trying to find a
spot that works trying to prove this
theorem so how do we take away one now
let's we can use either of these again
right we can use this one or this one
let's use the top one then we'll use the
bottom one who can tell me what you got
you're going to take away one from both
sides so you're going to take away this
be four times R minus two plus seven
times s plus one everyone agree put onto
the next one
oh it's not four times or it's four
times then I get it right I + 5 mine
plus 7 times s minus 3 that's right
don't you get that right
everything's fine good all right I was B
right
coefficients these two are fine these
two are not necessarily fine okay when
are we going to have trouble we're going
to have trouble when either this is
negative or when this is negative agreed
so when won't we have trouble when this
is bigger than or equal to what if this
is 2 we're fine and if this is three or
more we're fine so the only time we're
in big trouble
is when this is less than when R is less
than 2 and and both these have to be
true for us to be in trouble
we're in trouble in trouble when R is
less than 2 and s is less than 3 of r is
less than 2 and s is less than 3 let's
take the smallest situation or the
largest situation where that can happen
that means s is 1 and R is 1 and s is 2
if R is 1 and s is 2
what's the end four times one plus seven
times two is 18 that means if you're at
18 and you try to go down one step you
are in trouble but if you are above 18
then you're completely fine this is not
a proof by induction but it proves the
theorem it says you can go from any
number down one as often as you want
until you get to 18 and then you are
dead and then you cannot in general do
it you might get lucky once in a while
but you can't in general continue now we
can do the whole argument here with a z'
and B's and well I feel like let's see
I'll just Xerox it and let you see the
argument with A's and B's
the argument with A's and B's is the
same as what I did here with fours and
7s but it's got A's and B's in place it
looks a little more abstract I'll Xerox
it right away so let me stop here are
there questions about what we've done
we've done greatest common devisor we've
shown the connection to that water
puzzle we've shown the connection to the
Adu puzzle we've shown a connection to a
proof by induction that doesn't work we
fixed it