this is just for the analysis of
algorithms that's right I mean that's
yeah thumbs that use recurrence
sure exactly so if we use recursion or
algorithm we can write down some sort of
recurrence relation which represents the
amount of time it takes to do each step
and then we can get a bound on the order
of growth we can compare two algorithms
and their running time and so forth this
is the major application of using a
computer science so okay so we have all
these words we're supposed to look at a
linear homogeneous recurrence relation
means I have a recurrence of the form
and equals C 1 n minus 1
oops and I guess I should put a degree
here degree K so C 1 an minus 1 plus C 2
and minus 2 plus all the way down to C K
and minus K and in this case the C is
are constants
that's where constant coefficients comes
from it's linear because everything is
linear in the previous terms there's no
and squared or anything like that and
it's homogeneous that means that there's
no plus 2 out at the front or anything
like that how much it is just
mathematically means that everything has
exactly one term of degree one and and
that's it so there's no an x am minus
two or anything like that and then
degree K means that we go all the way
down to degree K and so we better have
CK not equal to zero
down so linear means that there's no AI
squared for example so everything's
linear in the a is homogeneous means
that there's no everything's multiplied
by exactly one a I it's constant
coefficients this means that the C is
our real numbers they're just constants
and what else degree K this means that
CK is not zero does this make sense
are there any questions so far Rob
something the the CIS don't have to
equal each other we could have well for
example I can put a 3 here and then this
first example is a linear homogeneous
recurrence equation with constant
coefficients of degree 2 because I go
down 2 steps
although we don't necessarily some of
these constants may be 0 so for example
recurrence relation with constant
coefficients of degree 3 because the
final guy is this three oaks yeah you're
right sorry so does this vocabulary make
sense degree three is this last the the
it's the pardon its degree so this is
degree 3 because we've gone down three
steps for me and minus one this depends
from and this depends on something
that's three removed from our starting
point so in theory this depends on and
lenox wanna n minus 2 n minus 3 even
though I mean these these sort of don't
appear but we have to
go all the way down I guess maybe the
point is is that when we're solving
these if we have something like n equals
an -3 and we have an initial like we
want to get a unique solution we sort of
have to have base cases and in this case
we'd have to have three base cases in
order to be able to continue our
recurrence so we have to start out
knowing what a 0 a 1 and a 2 are once we
know that a 3 is just going to be 5
times a 0 a 4 is going to be 5 times a 1
and from that point on we'll know
exactly what the rest of the sequences
oh sorry
base cases they have to be consecutive
and you could start anywhere along but I
guess today mostly I'm gonna be starting
at a zero because mathematicians like to
start at zero as opposed to everyone in
the rest of the world who likes to start
at one the question then is when can we
write down a formula that simply tells
us the nth dance number not using this
recursion so what's a a closed formula
some some equation like this and and our
best guess is going to be well suppose
and is just some number to the nth power
often our order of growth is you know 2
to the N or something like that so this
is sort of a first guess
in an equals R to the end into our
recurrence relation so then R to the N
is equal to c1 R to the N minus 1
have already done minus 1 plus c2 are to
be 1 minus 2 all the way down with CK R
to the N minus K so I get this equation
in R and now I want to solve for R so to
solve for R well first I'm going to
divide through by R to the n minus K so
I get this guy down to just a constant
and then all these exponents go down by
1 so this becomes R to the what's the N
minus n minus K and Lord of the K then n
minus 1 minus n minus K is K minus 1 K
minus 2 all the way down the CK times R
to the 0 so I get this equation in the
arse or in our I bring our ode of the
over I bring all this over to the other
side and I get art of the K on a c-1 or
the K minus 1 plus whoops - - okay
equals 0 and so what I end up with is
that our must be a root of this
polynomial which comes from here so
as a solution this is gonna be my first
guess
then I plug an equals R to the end or
you know a to the N minus 1 a sub n
minus 1 equals R to the N minus 1 that's
this is going to be true for I'm
assuming this is true for all n then I
plug this into this equation and I get
this equation here well it seems like a
reasonable guess because we've sort of
seen things popping up like this you
know we've often seen things that look
like a constant times a you know 3 times
2 to the N or something like that that
often seems to pop out when we've done
some of these examples by substitution
maybe let's do an example and we'll see
why oh but first I should tell you this
guy is called the characteristic
equation associated to our to our
recurrence relation and the roots are
the characteristic roots
if we do find a root to this equation
then it's actually going to be a
solution but it is should we prove that
maybe let's I mean let's do an example
first
so suppose we just have this recurrence
relation and suppose we have the initial
conditions a 0 close to then well we can
just solve this by substitution we just
sort of repeat and we get well this is
equal to 2 times 2 n minus 2 equals this
is 2 squared n minus 2 equals 2 squared
times
to a n minus 3 equals well let's see
this is 2 cubed and minus 3
finally if we continue we're going to
get something that looks like 2 to the K
a and minus K now to get down to 0 I
have to let k equal n so when I get is 2
to the N a sub 0 and sub 0 is just 2 and
so this is just 2 to the N plus 1 so
this maybe wasn't a terribly
enlightening example but I mean it does
give us something that ends up being
some exponential thing and so maybe it
gives us some reason to hope that yeah
really we will have an exponential up
hearing in our solution so here's the
theorem the theorem says that this does
really work like we really can take the
roots of this characteristic equation
and find the right answer ok so what
does that mean well so if I have my
characteristic equation here and this
has roots r1 up to RK and these guys are
distinct
sequence a n is a solution to this
recurrence relation if and only if as
you put an alpha 1 R 1 to the N plus
alpha 2 R 2 to the N plus alpha K R K to
the N where alpha is our constants
and I claim that if I write down this
polynomial so my polynomial is going to
be R to the N equals R the on - 1 plus 2
R to the N minus 2 oops - 2 and so now
if I subtract these guys over to the
other side and divide by our the N minus
2 this turns into R squared minus R
minus 2 equals 0 and let's see so this
guy has roots are minus 2 R plus 1
equals 0 so when we do these problems we
have to remember how to factor
polynomials hopefully the ones in the
homework don't factor terribly badly
let's see so so this guy's okay so now
what I claim is oh I guess we better
have initial conditions to anyone's
favorite initial conditions
so now my solution is going to be
different from what I wrote in your
notes but that's too bad
okay so claim my solution is going to be
of the form and equals alpha 1 times 2
to the N plus alpha 2 times minus 1 to
the N now I have to find out what out
for 1 and alpha 2 are so to do that well
fortunately I have these two starting
conditions so I can say let's see so if
I look at a 0 if I look at my formula
well a 0 is supposed to be alpha 1 times
2 to the 0 that's just awful 1 plus
alpha 2 times minus 1 to the 0 so that's
just off the 2 and this is supposed to
be 17 and then a 1 is supposed to be 23
and that's also 2 alpha 1 minus alpha 2
linear algebra we learned we have to
solve these two equations and two
unknowns
more generally I guess we'd have K
equations and K unknowns because we
would have had to start with K initial
values so let's see if we add these two
equations we get 3 alpha 1 a plus 40
subtract twice this from this I get
this from here and so alpha 2 is 17
minus 40 thirds let's see 30
this is 51 thirds so I get 11 thirds so
my final answer is and equals alpha 1 so
40 thirds times 2 to the n plus 11
thirds times minus 1 to the N does this
work I mean that seems like this really
convoluted formula first of all second
of all we have at least thirds I mean
are they really gonna cancel each other
out they're supposed to cancel each
other out because I should get integers
I mean this this recurrence equation is
nice enough and I started with integers
and I'm always just multiplying by 2 and
adding things so let's work out a couple
of terms so let's see it goes 17 23 and
then it's the first the the one previous
plus twice the one previous to that so
yeah I can't add very quickly today 57
okay and then let's see 46 plus that and
then to 114 so that's 217 206 423
mushroom volts I don't want to go any
further so let's check this one since 0
a 1 2 3 4 5 ok so a 5 is supposed to be
423 and over here I claim that it's 40
thirds times 2 to the fifth so 40 or 3
times 64 and -11 thirds
going to be a really big number yeah
okay so yeah so 1269 and I can do this
so from here to here yeah oh I just well
I didn't make I guess I assumed that our
was not zero so what I did first I I
should write this out better than I did
so I had R to the N equals R to the N
minus 1 plus 2 R to the N minus 2 so now
I just bring these over to this side and
I get R to the N minus 1 minus 1 minus 2
R to the N minus 2 equals 0 and now I
divide by R to the N minus 2 and so this
cancels out all the two of the ARS here
although one of the RS here and all of
the ARS here so I'm left with R squared
minus R minus 2 I'm not exactly sure
what's going to happen right now but
let's try and solve this recurrence
equation by substitution which is the
only method we know of so far maybe this
is gonna be a mistake well you know we
make mistakes in that sometimes so I'm
gonna start out with maybe some nicer
well I guess it doesn't matter okay so
want to try tacking it with substitution
and end up with well let's just
substitute it for a n minus one right
now so this becomes n minus 2 plus 2 a n
minus 3 and I have to carry along my 2
and s 2 so I get 3 n minus 2 plus 2 a n
minus 3 now if I go to substitute in for
n minus 2 I'm gonna get 3 x + -3 plus 2
a minus 4 so this ends up being 5 and
minus 3 plus 6 and minus 4 this is kind
of nice
ok so let's do it again five times and
that's 4 plus 2 and minus 5 plus 6 and
minus 4 well what I get is let's see
right it's not like attagirl
done that rising at 3 a.m. - 3 + whoops
this is 6 okay so I was hoping we'd see
a pattern at this point and I don't at
this point of course I saw a pattern but
then it went away
so that's too bad well yeah I mean
certainly this I mean certainly this
shows us why this is a better method
than just sort of substitution and
trying to figure it out I was hoping we
would be able to see why why we would
guess some power of our or some
combination of powers of our using this
I guess I guess it's not obvious from
here it might be obvious once we start
doing this linear algebra method so if
you suspend your disbelief until the end
of class then maybe we'll get some nicer
answers
coefficient is the it's gonna be 21 and
then it's right so how are you getting
the second coefficient you're getting it
from oh I see I see that's 42 yeah so so
your so what's am saying is he thinks
the pattern is you add the two
coefficients to get the next lead
coefficient and then you add the two
coefficients and add or subtract one on
the right side is actually double the
previous term on the left side oh yeah
right so here to here doubles yeah if we
have some constant here
next term is going to be CK plus CK
minus 1 and minus K minus 1 and 2 CK and
minus K minus 2 so this is a claim how
the coefficients are building up and can
we solve it from here
so right right yeah so so now we've seen
the pattern in the coefficients I don't
see exactly how we would solve this
equation for the general K other than
we'd get well go and write this down no
I don't think I want write this down so
pattern here is if we if we know what
our constant is on a and minus K and on
n minus K minus 1 so if we've you know
done K steps or K substitutions then the
claim is that when we make the next
substitution what we're going to get on
a times a sub n minus K minus 1 is is
the sum of these two constants and the
the what are what's going to be on the a
and minus K minus 2 is going to be 2
times this first constant and we could
see that simply by substituting in this
formula for this
this yeah that's what we're that's we're
trying to go oh so what we end up
getting rather than just getting
something are to the end we get so we
have all these roots can I erase this
since it didn't really lead us anywhere
this characteristic equation and this
has some roots R 1 R K and in fact any
well in fact the the solution given our
initial conditions is going to be some
linear combination of powers of these in
fact so our solution is alpha 1 R 1 to
the K F 1 R 1 to the n plus alpha 2 R 2
to the n plus alpha K R
a linear cut linear combination of these
roots no right you need to find which
combination and you can find which
combination by looking at your initial
conditions so you have some initial
statements you know we if we we know
what a 0 up to a k minus 1 are so you
know if a 0 is 5 then we can say okay is
your as 5 but it's also supposed to be
alpha 1 times our 1 to the 0 plus alpha
2 are 2 to the 0 plus alpha K R K to the
0 and so we get some equation in the
alpha k's in the alpha eyes and we'll
get K of these one for each of these
initial conditions and so then we have
to solve equations which we in theory
know how to do so are we reasonably
happy with this should we do another one
so an example
arbitrary yeah you'll get I mean what
Constance cannot you have to be sure to
make the right constant go with the
right route at the end but other than
that it's completely arbitrary which
order you choose yeah let's do an
example that us three okay so I claim
that if I take the following recurrence
equation okay so here we have a
recurrence equation and hopefully I
multiplied right and we want to solve it
so we do is well we say first what's the
characteristic equation that's when I
substitute an R to the end for these
guys now I pulled them all over to the
left-hand side of this equation so I get
R to the N that's 2 R to the n minus 1
minus R to the N minus 2 minus 2 R to
the N minus 3 is equal to 0 plus okay so
now I divide through both sides by r to
the n minus 3 the reason I'm doing this
is I want to end up with a constant term
out on the end I want to end up with a
polynomial so I get R cubed minus 2 R
squared minus R plus 2 equals 0 so this
guy is my characteristic equation
the end otherwise I just have you know a
whole bunch of powers of are out at the
front and so I guess I should assume
what's going on
sure okay so the N minus three it
divides through each term and I just
subtract n minus 3 from each term so you
know X to the K over X to the J is X to
the K minus J so n minus n minus 3s R
cubed etc ok so I have this equation and
unfortunately I cooked it up over where
the video couldn't see me and so I know
what the roots are there this factors is
how do you solve them if you don't
already know the answer
they're integer solutions which they
should be because hopefully Shai was
nice on the problem set then all you
have to do is look at this this constant
term because the constant term is going
to be the product of this this and this
oh yeah yeah yes yes I mean certainly if
our recurrence relations come from
algorithms we're not going to do Oh
point three times you know the previous
step and so yeah all these guys are
really going to be integers and so we
should be okay so what Sam said Sam's
hint for trying to factor this if you if
you come across some horribly messy
equation is that if you have a one out
here and well then you can look at your
your constant term here and your
solutions must be factors of this
constant term they must multiply
together to give you this constant term
so just look at a factorization of that
constant term and figure out which
possibilities work in this case we have
one two and minus one which multiplied
together together that doesn't look
right
not equivalent it's just an equation
that you've derived from your your
original recurrence relation
to the N minus 3 that guy would have
given me a solution R equals zero I'm
assuming that doesn't happen because I
guess well I guess when we write down
our final solution here if we have an R
equals 0 here that's not really
contributing I mean that's not
contributing contributing anything at
all
that's right so okay so now we have our
characteristic equation what let's have
some nicer initial conditions I'm not on
exam seven so one two and minus one so
our solution is supposed to look
something like constant times 1 to the n
plus second constant times 2 to the n
plus 1/3 constant times minus 1 to the N
so now we can we can find out what our
constants are in this particular example
because we know what our base cases are
so our base case will we say a 0 that's
0 but it's also if we plug zero in for n
here we get alpha 1 times 1 to the 0
that's 1 plus alpha 2 times 2 to the 0
that's also 1 plus alpha 3 times minus 1
to the 0 that's all put 1 so we get off
on 1 plus alpha 2 plus alpha 3 equals 0
our next equation is going to say okay
let's figure out what a 1 is well 1 to
the 1 is just 1 to the 1 is 2 so I get 2
off of 2 and minus 1 to the 1 is minus 1
so I get minus alpha 3 and then lastly
they get 2 is equal to a 2 which is
alpha-1 plus for off a 2 plus alpha 3
of linear equations and yeah I do
Gaussian elimination so yeah the first
subtracting the first from the third
gives us what a 3 is I mean in fact I
you don't have to use Gaussian
elimination you can use whatever your
favorite method for you know whatever is
so a let's see a 2 minus a 0 is equal to
3 off of 2 which is equal to 2 alpha to
support a 2/3 and then right if we add
if we add these two then we get 1 is
equal to 2 alpha 1 plus 3 up a 2 and so
so alpha 2 is minus 1/2
such 4 and then finally we can plug that
back into the first one and so we have
2/3 minus 1/2 plus something is equal to
0 so alpha 3 bitter of you - is 6
positive 6 right yeah so what is our
final answer look like well our solution
says that a n must be and must be a
minus 1/2 times 1 to the N that's just 1
plus
1 to the N and so if we did out you know
100 terms of this sequence we could
check that indeed this was the right
formula so I'm a little afraid to do
that because I'm a little afraid of my
multiplication out of these so that's
four plus one is five minus zero so a
three predictors did I say five yeah and
so now if I plug in three here I'm gonna
get minus 1/2 plus 2/3 times eight plus
minus 1/6 well plus is 6,000 NRP because
there's a minus 1 to the 3 let's see
what this adds up to this is minus 2/3
plus 8 times
oh right minus minus 1/3 no yay it's 5
so we actually did the right thing for
the first iteration you know for if you
if you do this algorithm on on zero
things then it takes zero time if you do
this algorithm on one thing then it
takes one step if you do it on two
things it takes two steps so we have to
have some initial conditions once we do
that we say well you know here we have
this formula for am let's see what
happens when we plug in zero to this
formula when I plug in 0 I put a zero
here so this is 1 to the 0 plus a 2
times 2 to the 0 plus alpha 3 times 1
minus 1 to the
things out one of the 0 2 to the 0 minus
1 of the 0 1 and also I assumed from the
beginning that this is equal to 0 so I
get the equation 0 equals alpha 1 plus
alpha 2 plus alpha 3 and that's from I
from one of my initial conditions for my
second initial condition and I say ok a
1 well by this formula that's supposed
to be 1 to the 1 that's 2 to the 1 plus
minus 1 to the 1 times these constants
and also it's supposed to be 1 by my
initial condition so you know I get this
I could also if I you know if well I
know now that a 3 is supposed to be
equal to 5 simply by plugging into here
I can now set up another equation that
says 5 equals a 3 equals well alpha 1
times 1 cubed plus 2 cubed 10 South to
plus minus 1 cubed times alpha 3 and
that would give me a fourth equation and
of course it would be dependent on the
other three it's not really relevant but
I guess you could choose the equations
that look to the prettiest and solve
those for your alphas the book explains
how to prove this theorem and so that's
exactly you know that'll exactly tell
you why it is that you take these
combinations of roots it turns out it
turns out what we're doing so when we
were studying linear algebra and I let's
talk about this at the-- and maybe when
we were studying linear algebra we had
and we wanted to look we looked a little
bit of recurrence relations and what we
did was we got a matrix that sort of
described our current relation and then
we got a closed formula by diagonalizing
that matrix and then taking it to some
big power and multiplying by the initial
conditions and essentially what we're
doing here is the same thing
except for hiding all the linear algebra
so if you think about what it meant to
well now we'll talk about it you know in
in 15 minutes what happens if our
characteristic polynomial is R minus 2
squared so this would come from the
recurrence relations and equals 4 a and
minus 1 minus 4 and minus 2 so I get
this recurrence for right you know I'd
say okay now I have R squared equals 4 R
minus 4 so R squared
it's for our plus 4 equals 0 and so i
factor this I say okay this is our minus
2 squared and I'm in trouble my theorem
doesn't apply I don't have two distinct
roots what actually happens in this case
is something that's going to remind us a
little bit of partial fractions so
that's really like I'm pulling this out
of nowhere but what happens is in this
case my answer looks something like
alpha 1 times 2 to the n plus alpha 2
and times 2 to the N
fractions when we had when we wanted to
factor when we wanted a factor when we
wanted to factor this we ended up with
something that looked like like this
squared nope nope that's great and so
the same thing is going on here
I sort of repeat my factor each time but
every time I repeat it I add a copy of n
so if I had a if you don't River partial
fractions then you know don't worry
about this what okay so the same thing
happens you know if we had R minus 2
cubed we'd end up with something like
alpha 1 times 2 to the N plus alpha 2
times n times 2 to the n plus alpha 3
times N squared 2 to the N so the the
rule is if you have a repeated root then
what you do is you you have some
constant times that root to the nth
power plus another constant times n
times that root to the nth power if it
were cubed well then the same thing
happens you have a constant times 2 to
some power plus a constant times n times
2 to that power plus a constant times N
squared times 2 to that power
2 to the K what my solution looks like
is alpha 1 plus alpha 2 n plus alpha 3 n
squared plus alpha 4 and cubed plus all
the way up to alpha K minus 1 into the K
minus 1 times 2 to the N so I the
general polynomial of degree K minus 1
times 2 to the N Jo good question so
that's the next thing you know this so
generally if we well if we have R minus
2 squared times R minus 1 we have well
ok so this 1 minus 2 squared gives us an
alpha 1 plus alpha 2 n times 2 to the N
and this guy gives us an alpha 1 times 1
to the ants whoops
alpha 3 times one of them so what you do
what you end up doing is if we have is
the most general thing we can write down
if we have roots r1 up to RT and these
have multiplicity and ones up to Mt so
that's how many times each of these
roots occurs so these are roots how many
times they occur
so we could have you know
2 2 2 3 4 6 6 8 9 9 and so how I would
write this here I would say okay I have
2 with multiplicity 3 I have 3 with
multiplicity 1 4 with multiplicity 1 6
with multiplicity 2 8 with multiplicity
1 writing down these arrows isn't really
important but you just have to keep
track of the multiplicities and the
roots okay so this will be really
complicated but you know we could still
write down the general solution and
solve for a general solution using our
initial conditions if we god-forbid
needed to what the general solution in
this case is going to be is exactly well
you know take take this guy this is
going to give us a general polynomial of
degree M 1 minus 1 times R 1 to the N so
we get
contributes this much so everyone see
how that guy how that's the right thing
what's going on as I said well let's say
this occurs five times then I'm gonna
have a term for the zeroth term and n
for the first time it occurs all the way
up to five times n to the fourth and now
I just replaced my v with the general
multiplicity and then I multiply it by
this root to the nth power so is it real
clear on this term so far then I just
add to it exactly this for each of the
next couple terms and this is this just
looks awful you would never well yes we
write this down for the next term etc
etc yada yada yada we write it down for
the last term
so my handout there's probably a typo
because you know yuck
okay so let's do it any less let's write
this out for this example just to be you
know prettier whatever okay so we have
two occurring three times so that means
that two gives us an alpha yeah Sam's
right we should be using constants
because these subscripts get really
annoying but sure sure so what's Sam
saying is we can abbreviate all of these
polynomials to be you know this has to
be a polynomial of degree 4 this has to
be a polynomial of the multiplicity
minus 1 etc so here let's see I'm
supposed to go up to multiplicity 3 so
this was enough
this is just some polynomial times two
to the annum and it's a polynomial of
degree 3 minus one so piece of three
minus one of N and I guess I should what
I should what I should say is that this
polynomial depends on something you know
this isn't going to be the same
polynomial as the polynomial for and in
these others so yeah we have to have all
these subscripts that mean whatever they
mean but so in any event you're never
gonna have to use something this ugly so
let's do something slightly prettier
let's say we have our minus two squared
times R minus one this is Joe's example
and this is probably the worst we'll see
it so so what's going on here is I have
to write something like C plus D n times
two to the n plus I can't use e now
all constants I got sick of the Roman
alphabet and I moved to the Greek so so
this is what my solution for if my
characteristic equation is this this is
what the form of my solution is going to
be are we clear on this is this okay
okay right and so in this case we have
something of degree three
so I need three initial conditions and
then we could solve for alpha and beta
and gamma that's right so yes that's
exactly right
so this is these are all corresponding
to route 1 and then they go up to the
number of the multiplicity and I guess I
should really go up or guess yeah
absolutely
and probably I did in the notes oh I
didn't okay then I didn't so are we
reasonably happy with this okay we
haven't done anything like this yet
today and that's too bad I mean you know
this well we know something from the
Masters theorem about the order of
growth of this
solving this kind of recurrence relation
so I'm going to quickly go through
relations and we'll get to one example
and then hopefully we'll have five
minutes at the end to talk about linear
algebra and the Fibonacci numbers okay
so so what's going on with these these
recurrence equations look like this they
look like and it's C 1 times n minus 1
plus C 2 times n minus 2 plus all the
way down to C ka n minus K and that
part's okay this we know how to solve
mostly from the linear homogeneous stuff
and then we add on some function of an
and this is exactly so equations of this
form are called linear non homogeneous
recurrence relations with constant
coefficients and maybe I'd call this one
degree K so all the words are the same
except now this is non-homogeneous what
makes it non homogeneous well exactly
this extra function out at the end ok
so great we want to solve these the
Masters theorem tells us how to find the
order of growth depending on how fast F
of n grows but it doesn't tell us
anything about how to find a closed form
for the for the recurrence relation so
how we do that well we have to make use
of a couple theorems the first one isn't
very useful but it tells us something
interesting what it says is if we have
any like if we can find one solution and
that's the hard part I haven't told you
we don't know how to do that yet so if
we can find one solution
up here that means it's a particular
solution then every other solution is
going to be of the form and a peak plus
some other a 7h where this guy is a
solution to this homogeneous part so
we're and H is a solution to the
homogeneous part C 1 and minus 1 plus
blah blah blah plus CK n minus K so this
is something like when we were solving
equations in linear algebra we had the
solution of an equation is some
particular solution which we find you
know who knows how right now plus some
other solution which is supposed to be
in the null space so we had somehow a
particular solution plus something that
depended on these free variables that we
had floating around right now we're
supposed to think of this part as the
free variables and so any solutions to
those we can then add on to a particular
solution to get an overall solution if
you if you have seen anything about
differential equations and if you
haven't you can sort of do this right
now for the next two minutes or 10
seconds this is very similar to how you
would solve a system of differential
equations and
if you've seen that then maybe you'll
see the connection and if you're
interested to hear more than you know
come talk to me after class it turns out
that you solve systems of differential
equations using linear algebra in the
same way and so the solution arises as a
particular solution plus some solution
of the free variables or some solution
from the null space so so great I mean
this this theorem doesn't this theorem
tells us that if we have one solution
then we have a whole bunch but it
doesn't tell us how to find one solution
so the question is how do we find one
solution we can only do it when F of n
is the form a polynomial times an
exponential so let's assume F of n
equals a polynomial times an exponential
of screwed I mean when when we have the
Masters theorem we could sort of deal
with things like this we couldn't deal
with things when we had you know and log
in there and we still can't you know I
mean if you can solve it another way
great but this theorem doesn't allow us
to solve it that way so so far if our
polynomial for our function looks like
this then the claim is a solution is
well there are two cases if if this s is
a root of our characteristic or is there
two cases so s could either be a root of
the characteristic equation that comes
from this homogeneous part or it could
not be we're sort of happier if it's not
so s is not a root in the characteristic
equation in that case a particular
solution is
this guy this is a polynomial of the
same degree as this polynomial both
possibly different coefficients we have
to figure out what those are and this is
just the exponential to the N and if it
is a root then what we do is take the
same thing but we multiply we multiply
on the front by N to the M where m is
the multiplicity okay so we have these
two possibilities and the reason we're
multiplying by N to the M is just to
push this solution out past the possible
solutions that we would have gotten from
the characteristic equation so this
makes the degree of this solution higher
than the degree of the solutions coming
from the characteristic equation so it
just sort of forces the solution to
exist
that's not one that we already would
have known about so let's let's sort of
apply this theorem I mean it seems
confusing and abstract and let's do an
example
numbers so I'm in trouble because this
isn't a recurrence relation right I
better make it into a recurrence
relation how is it right so I have n
minus 1 plus n I can define the triangle
numbers recursively and now let's go
find a formula for the triangle numbers
using this recurrence relation stuff and
I guess my initial conditions were that
a 0 was 0 and a 1 was 1 okay
so let's see so I can think of this as n
times 1 to the N now I have to and in
fact you also you you you have to be
careful when there's no exponential here
you have to think of this as a 1 to the
N and be careful exactly when 1 is a
root of this polynomial and I hope it is
so this guy gives us the homogeneous
part that looks like a nice simple
homogeneous part so we get R minus 1
equals 0 as the characteristic equation
questions so so what I did was I said
okay this is the same as R to the N
equals r to the n minus 1 and so now I
subtract so R minus R to the N minus 1
equals 0 now I divide through I take out
all the copies of our to the end and our
I take out all the copies of our that I
can and divide them out and then with R
minus 1 equals 0 so I divide this guy by
our this one to give that so step clear
ok so now we really do have to be
careful about the particular solution
because one really is the root of my
characteristic equation and I have a 1
here so I claim that a particular
solution is going to look like I have to
multiply by an out in the front because
this has multiplicity 1 so I supposed to
x + 2 that multiplicity that so that's
just n to the 1 now I get a polynomial
of the same degree as this guy so p0 +
p1 n and then I multiply it by s to the
n there's everyone clear how we went
from here to here okay so so in this
theorem we had two cases when s was a
root and when s wasn't the root of the
characteristic polynomial in this case
when you have this polynomial sitting
out in the front you have to be careful
yes so this one is s and so now we're in
the case when s is a root and so we're
in the second case
multiplicity is 1 so we multiply by an N
to the M and to the 1 so so great now I
have something that I think is a
particularly those constants again using
my initial conditions so I know that a 0
is supposed to be 0 on this side I get n
to the 0 is whoops now 0 I don't want to
use these initial conditions I want to
use what oh right right right
solution I've just now multiplied
through by the N squared and I want to
ensure that this satisfies my recurrence
relation and equals n minus 1 plus n for
all in so so in the one hand it's p0 so
in one hand it's p0 and times p1 n
squared on the other party yes oh sorry
on the other hand it's supposed to be
and minus 1 P plus n and this according
to the formula is n minus 1 times p0
plus p1 and the N minus 1 squared plus n
right
hand this is supposed to be equal to
this by this formula on the other hand
it's supposed to satisfy the recurrence
relation it's supposed to satisfy and P
is equal to a n minus 1 P plus n right
understand yeah so this we're just
finding a particular solution it's a
superscript n or a sin so we're doing
the so now we're playing the second term
which we haven't proved and so yes I
guess this is a leap of faith that says
here this is one way to find a solution
figure out yeah these are constants
constants today and if you can keep
track of them then your step ahead of me
probably that was just multiplying this
out yeah we have to find constants such
that this works yeah this has to be this
is ass yeah which is yeah which is this
one to the end that's right yeah so now
we're trying to find constants so this
works here too here
yeah this is just substituting in this
formula now for n minus 1 it's saying
p0 times n minus 1 plus p1 times n minus
1 squared is everyone clear on this
algebra there's a lot of algebra here
and if you get lost in a step then it's
very confusing so I want to make sure
everyone's with me ok so great I have
this p0 n plus p1 n squared and I have
this other one let's simplify this
equation where a minus 2 n plus 1 and
then plus another end I'm gonna have to
go over to the other board now and put
these all together
n squared - 2 p1 + + p1 + n and now this
is supposed to be equal to p0 n + p1 n
squared this and we have this and
they're supposed to be equal yeah so
great so we can do is subtract this P 1
N squared over this side and subtract
the p0 n and it cancels out this and
what we're going to be left with is
minus p0 minus 2 P 1 and plus p1 plus n
is equal to 0 is equal to 0 so so what
I've done was I've said okay cancel p0 n
+ p0 n and cancels p1 n squared + p1 n
squared we added the end that's I mean
that was that was the difference so we
applied so so I mean we're sort of doing
this inductive thing or something right
I mean we assume the formula works for n
minus 1 so therefore plug it in now set
them equal to each other and then figure
out what your formula must have been to
begin with so is everyone okay from here
to here
sides are equal these two sides of the
equation and so I just cancelled out
this p0 on this PC rollin and I
subtracted from this side to the side
and they went to 0 and I subtracted this
one off from this one that's what I'm
left with is this term this term this
term in this term ok so what I have now
when I when I do this all out let's see
the constants on the ends are going to
be 1 - 2 P 1 times n and then plus P 1
minus p 0 this is supposed to be equal
to 0 this has to be true for all n and
so what this means is that p 1 minus p 0
i better be equal to 0 and 1 minus 2 P 1
better be equal to 0 as well
solve this equation to get P 1 equals
1/2 and this equation tells me that p1
is equal to p0 so PZ are also equals 1/2
to be true for any n and so well if I
think of this side if I think of this as
a polynomial in N on this side I have 0
and plus 0 so the constant term on n
better be 0 and the constant term itself
better be 0 so that ok there's some
skeptical looks ok great so I get p1 and
p0 equal to 1/2 what does that tell us
you know now I've done all this algebra
we're all confused
where are we what have we gotten well
what we've gotten is we come back here
and we have this formula now for a n
this particular solution what it is now
I can plug in my p0 on my p1 let's erase
all of this so my particular solution is
when I plug in 1/2 for each of them so I
get 1/2 n plus 1/2 n squared
what does that mean well right now let's
rewrite this this is N squared plus n
over 2 that's the same as n times n plus
1 over 2 thank God we got the right
formula you know I mean that's that's
our for me right right so Sam's right
we're may be jumping the gun we have a
particular solution we have to find the
general solution the general solution is
supposed to look like well we have to go
back to our characteristic equation and
the general solution is any solution to
the characteristic any solution to this
homogeneous equation
plus our particular solution okay so our
homogeneous equation is just this a N
equals n minus 1 well we could solve
this using the methods that we talked
about at the beginning of class but on
the other hand if if we know that a 0 is
0 which it is by assumption then a
solution to this guy is going to be
equivalently 0 right I mean if a 0 is 0
then a 1 is 0 and a 2 is 0 and a 3 is 0
and so we could find figure out what the
solution is but what it's going to turn
out to be you just because this is sort
of a silly recurrence equation is just a
N equals 0 right so I've cut a step out
so so great now we have this is a
particular solution the general solution
is going to look something like this
solution plus a solution to our
homogeneous our Associated homogeneous
now we have a little more work to do we
have to go back to the beginning of
lecture and remember how to solve a
homogeneous system this we just said
well you know this was a really easy one
we only had one root and it only had
multiplicity 1 so the solution to it
looks something like alpha 1 times 1 to
the end and in particular if we go to
solve this well 1 to the N that's just 1
so an equals alpha 1 and also we happen
to have the equation for our initial
solutions did that from our initial
situation that a 0 is equal to 0 so 0
equals a 0 which is also equal to alpha
1 therefore alpha 1 is 0 and
this is the same as alpha 1 equal zero
so you know what we wanted to say right
if we know so I mean if we've started
with a sub 1 equals 1 we know we'd end
up with um
about it I mean there's there's
something we're doing wrong there and I
you definitely you have to be careful
about your initial solutions and you'll
you know that you'll get those as part
of your as part of your initial data or
whatever right
so what Sam saying is actually we're
okay
the the particular solution is computing
what's going on really far out and so
you just have to be careful about where
you're starting and you know this sort
of takes care of that and so if we're
starting at one we'd have to subtract
one off from from this initial solution
and then how to pack on because it was
the solution to that particular solution