myself what if I were a person who was
completely fine in every way except I
was always afraid of sports my whole
life never ever played during recess
never got chosen for a team and I go my
life otherwise completely normal but
with a mild phobia of ever accidentally
you know getting chosen into sunlight
like pickup game you know like like oh
we're all going to I don't know throw a
frisbee you know no no obviously and to
me this is all fun but to some people
this might be like a nervous point in
their lives that routinely comes up and
they get used to it I mean this
everybody has all these things I'm
thinking what if there's somebody like
that and I go around thinking oh this is
just a lot of fun today throwing common
times and then they get over nervous -
Clementine cousin put in a box with a
crate of fruit into the Clementine box
yeah I'm waiting to see if we got a
audience that's larger than this what do
we got here a one two three four five
six seven nine times 1 in 20 we're
missing like a like a third or something
all right well we'll try to do it I got
a good lecture today - it's good
it was prepared late last night Late
Late Late
oh geez so long after I was watching
myself uh-huh all right ready to go
here's what we're gonna do today is the
last day we're going to talk about
counting per se it's the last day we'll
talk about recurrence equations after
today starting Sunday Monday Tuesday
Wednesday we've got four more lectures
we're going to shift topics toward
number theory and items related to
number theory that relate eventually to
cryptography and that'll be the goal is
to prepare you with enough number theory
so that when we get to cryptography and
you understand how credit cards get sent
back and forth over the Internet in a
secure way that you'll understand the
RSA cryptography algorithm and what's
behind it you need to know a lot of
number theory before you can really
appreciate that or understand
so that's our goal and we got plenty of
time to do it there's one other topic
that I don't think you need to know too
much about but you should certainly know
the definitions about it and it's a
topic which is really separate you know
a lot about it already it's about trees
and it's about something called partial
orders and something called equivalence
relations I haven't talked about it up
till now because I think it's really
something that just needs one long day
so here's how I'm going to do it I'm
gonna have that happen on Sunday I had
it planned for the last day of the class
in case we never got to it it wouldn't
matter that much because we've done all
the important counting in the number
theory and the logic and the recurrence
equations but I'm gonna have it done on
Sunday because tar and I are switching I
was going to do Sunday in which case I
was going to go on to number three but
she's going to do Sunday so she's going
to do my partial order equivalence
relation that day which normally would
have been done at the end and I'm going
to do her recitations today okay
recitations today are going to be review
and discussions of problems of six and
various things like that so I'll do
these two today tar will do that Sunday
Monday Tuesday Wednesday is going to be
talking about number theory and
cryptography okay everybody got that
schedule so what we're going to finish
with today is generating functions I
introduced it last time we talked about
how to add them and multiply them what
happens to the coefficients we talked
about their connection to counting we
talked about how generating functions
can help you solve counting problems and
now we're going to talk about how they
help you solve recurrence equation z'
who just came in Doug I don't remember
you here a few minutes ago Erica well
Toni anybody else
be sitting he missed it he plays tennis
all the time the chance of him missing
this is like with some top spin on it I
was going to teach you can eat how to
juggle but we didn't have enough time
this morning enough some shots will do
recitation we'll do juggling mathematics
of juggling yeah Ron gran gave a talk
about mathematics of juggling he's one
of the authors of the concrete math book
one of the premier discrete mathematics
experts in the country and he published
an article in Scientific American about
it maybe about five or six years ago or
so it's a great topic actually for for a
grade school in high school classes
because you can do it at a lot of
different levels but up until and he's
he's a juggler he juggles pretty well he
goes to juggling conventions but up
until he wrote this paper I don't think
there was much really rigorous math
about juggling and what you do is you
basically look at a juggling pattern and
you come up with a sequence of numbers
that represents that juggling pattern
and in doing that you've converted
juggling to another language of numbers
and then you can start with a sequence
of numbers and ask yourself what
juggling pattern does that give me so it
gives you a way of creating juggling
patterns by creating sequences of
numbers and certain sequences of numbers
are juggling patterns that you can't
really do because the two balls land at
the same hand at the same time some
people can do that right but not mortals
well the greatest the greatest juggler
is a long time what are we going to do
today so we're going to do two examples
two examples I'm going to warn you in
advance that there are some details in
these examples and I don't want you to
lose the the big picture because of the
details so I have in order to prevent
that carefully worked-out every possible
exponent and constant and know that it's
right so I don't have to like put this
down and say oh check me because you'll
be tired and you'll lose track
everything I'll put up here I'll be
right with regard to details but keep in
mind a lot of it is the tails there is
going to be quadratic formulas
okay back from high school there's going
to be Taylor series back from calculus
there's going to be partial fractions
back from calculus if we get to a point
where I have to remind you of the
technique I might just say well go
remind yourselves but here's how it's
done I might skip some steps if I feel
that I'm going to lose the the stream of
how things are going but I won't skip
any of the big picture all right so
we're going to do two main problems one
is the Fibonacci numbers that you've
seen only about a dozen times this
semester semester and the other one is
the binary trees balanced parentheses
and matrix multiplications when we get
to this example this is the one I'll do
last I'm going to remind you what these
three are and remind you that they're
really all the same that the number of
different ways to make end pairs of
balanced parentheses is the number of
different ways to associate n plus one
matrices when you're multiplying them is
a number of different binary trees with
n nodes these are all three the same
we're going to come up with a recurrence
equation like you did in the problem set
I'll remind you where it comes from and
we're going to solve it this solution to
this recurrence equation is the only one
that absolutely seems to require
generating functions to make any headway
on you all know how to solve this
recurrence equation using linear or
homogeneous techniques right this is
just the recurrence equations right you
could probably solve that in a number of
different ways but we're going to look
about solving it with generating
functions this would be a good start
it's a lot more complicated than the
examples we did last time but a lot less
complicated than this one okay questions
so far okay you know let me call these
small apps of nobody minds because I
want to distinguish it from the
generating function which I'll call
capital X the small s will be the
coefficients that show up in the
generating function and the capital F
will actually be the generating function
itself there's a distinction one is the
function with all the X's in it
and one are the coefficients that appear
in that function so in particular f of X
is going to equal F 0 plus F 1 times X
plus F 2 times x squared plus F 3 times
X cubed etc okay everybody see the
difference between this capital F in the
small F right and the small F is the
recurrence equation for Fibonacci
numbers I'm going to start off with F of
0 equals 1 and F of 1 equals 1 that will
be my two base cases ok questions
everybody knows this stuff already right
these are Fibonacci numbers here's the
recurrence equation let me write it out
you all know what Fibonacci numbers look
like so what do we get we get somebody
read it off to me 1 plus plus X plus 2 x
squared plus 3x cubed plus 5 X to the
fourth plus 8 X to the fifth dot dot dot
that's what it looks like that's the
generating function for Fibonacci
numbers you guys have to do this in the
in the pset on streams right did you
have to do Fibonacci numbers or just
sine and cosine and stuff did you do
Fibonacci numbers there well you could
you could you could write a program in
scheme to start off with this definition
and these two kind of seed values and
have the thing kind of bootstrap itself
and generate this stream of numbers you
could have done that in that pset if you
didn't we start with 0 n 1 some
Fibonacci it depends
sometimes it starts with 0 1 sometimes
it starts with 1 1 the formulas at the
end are going to be the same modulo and
enter an N plus 1 so let's let's work
this way this time okay here's what I
want to do I want to fiddle with this a
little bit and get some kind of equation
that relates capital f of X to other
capital FS of other things and then
solve for capital f of X
get a closed form for this function
instead of having a big dot dot dot I
want this to show up and be something
like you know the square root of x plus
3 and then if I can analyze what the
coefficients of that generating function
are I'll get a formula for these
coefficients instead of just the numbers
themselves like let's say I could show
you and it's not but let's say I could
show you this is exactly equal to 1
minus 2x then what would the
coefficients be remember that they'd be
2 to the N right it's not equal to that
it's going to be equal to something else
which will be similar to that it's going
to be equal to 1 minus 1 plus the square
root of 5 over 2x times you'll see it'll
be equal to something much much more
complicated but in that kind of a form
so that's my goal in order to do this
here's what we notice this depends on
the recurrence depends on two numbers
one less one - lies how do you make a
recurrence or a sequence of numbers or a
generating function shift by one what do
you do to it multiplied by X right let's
do this and see what happens even if we
don't see where we're going
just get that intuition in your head
what does X f of X going to be somebody
write it out for me or yell it out X
plus x squared plus 2x cubed plus 3x to
the fourth 5x to the fourth fifth thank
you etc 8 X to the 6 right how do I get
shifted 2 over I multiply by X again so
x squared so this ends up being
the one I just did by X x squared
to the right this is the same sequence
as the one on top
shifted one to the right this is the
same sequence as the one on top shifted
two to the right except for one thing
five there's one difference it's not
exactly shifted over because as I shift
over I lose these earlier terms so it's
not exactly shifted over but that's
actually going to help us we're going to
get now an equation for f of X we'll do
this stuff later what does f of X equal
look at it G's add these two together
that's not an accident this is f little
F sub n this is little F sub n minus one
this is little F sub n minus two if you
add these two generating functions
together you are adding the coefficients
representing these two generating
functions and that's going to give you
the generating function representing
these this sequence except for the one
let me say that again look at that
that's the whole power of generating
functions we make a generating function
for this sequence we make a generating
function for this sequence we add them
together and we should more or less get
this generating function except for this
little detail about the one that does
mentions so let's add them together we
get X plus two x squared plus three X
cubed plus five x to the fourth
everything works out so let's write this
out X f of X plus x squared f of X plus
one
back to the realm of high school we're
going to do a solution for f of X using
the quadratic formula and then we'll
actually get a function for f of X just
like the one I promised we get a few
minutes ago all right our questions so
far from now on we're in detail and and
I'm going to try not to lose you in the
detail so here's where we're headed
here's the big picture we're going to go
from this equation to a closed form for
f of X this is kind of like a recursive
generating function equation in terms of
itself we're going to get a closed form
for capital f of X we're going to look
at it we're going to fiddle with it so
that it looks like 1 divided by 1 minus
something plus 1 divided by 1 line is
something else so we can turn it into
functions that we know what the
coefficients are and then take those
coefficients and get a closed form for
the small apps which represent those
coefficients that's the big picture so
don't lose me now in the details let me
stop for questions we've got a question
John all right so you didn't hear
anything I just said for the last two
minutes
all right so what I said the big picture
is what we're going to do is we put this
equation up on the board ok then I get a
beat going on the fourth beat everybody
starts dancing when I stop the beat
you're freeze
if I see something if I see somebody
moving after I say stop I point to you
and you have to sit down you're out know
what you guys laughing about he just
missed it no I'm sorry Jeffrey if it was
really easy something like this we want
to get a formula for capital f of X
that's going to require some algebra and
some quadratic formula once we get this
if it looks like this or something
simple like this we can interpret the
coefficients of this because we know
that in this case they're all ones in
another case say this was a two would be
true to the end the coefficient we'll
take that and that will tell us a
closed-form for this small apps because
those are the coefficients of this
generating function does that make sense
all right so you you're out now because
you didn't say you liked Simon Says or
something well maybe oh yeah you're
right we got to use quadratic formula
the next one and the next step you're
right you're right smartypants
you're right no your honor is that right
let's let's let's fix this all right
yeah let's just do it
yeah after that now we're doing algebra
you're right Michael I prepared you for
the worst and it won't come okay we want
to get an answer for capital f of X so
Michaels right we can just factor out
the capital f of X here what do you get
F of x equals one divided by one minus X
minus x squared
oh well that's close to one over one
minus X if it were one over one minus X
we would say the coefficients are all
ones but instead it's one over one minus
X minus x squared it's this thing we
didn't have the slightest idea what the
coefficients of this what we do we know
they're the Fibonacci numbers but we
don't have any formula for generating
the coefficients of this general
any function but we could if we could
turn this into something that looked
like this
would be alpha to the end this would be
BAE to the end yeah them both together
you get alpha to the n plus beta to the
N because adding generating functions
adds coefficients so can we put this in
this form and the answer is yes we have
to be able to factor this so now we need
the quadratic formula we have to factor
this and in factoring it we're going to
come up with some some details factor
and partial fractions right because
actually we're not going to be able to
make it one over something there's going
to have to be some numbers on top of
here so here's our goal step by step boo
boo boo we'll start with this 1 minus
alpha X 1 minus beta X this is a good
form to start with because we can
definitely take this and factor it into
this we just have to figure out what the
alpha and beta should be and once we get
this we can turn it into two pieces that
are separate by doing partial fractions
so everything from here on in is details
so don't lose me in the details we are
going to get a final version of this and
we can just add the two exponents
together but right now we got lots of
details questions so far all right how
do we factor such a thing and get alpha
and beta well one times one gives you
one if you multiply these things out you
get minus alpha X minus beta X has got
to be equal to two minus one right so
what does that give you
middle term is the foil the outer inner
negative alpha X negative beta X
together has to be this coefficient in
front of the X negative alpha negative
beta is negative 1 so alpha plus beta is
1 what else do you know alpha times beta
has got to equal negative negative 1
right we have to solve these two
equations simultaneously
it's simple Sean says that's sin Chi
it's sin Chi I had an eighth-grader with
a really high voice it hadn't changed
yet and he was a smart kid and every
time he ever did anything he'd say
that's sin Chi actually he didn't really
say it but I would tell everybody he
said it because he just had that kind of
a voice all right I got home too late to
tell any stories about you guys all
right let's see I'm gonna avoid the
details here what does alpha and beta
turn out to be anybody do it leaving out
details you can all solve this
simultaneously or if not go ask anybody
who thinks it's sin Chi what do you get
disguised if you try to solve these
simultaneously you'll get a quadratic
formula and then you'll have to solve
that I mean why don't we just use the
quadratic formula on this because the
quadratic formula gives you roots of
this equation and then we'd have to
reinterpret what the roots mean in terms
of putting it in this form and there'd
be that intermediate step where
everybody would would get all confused
about a plus or a minus and we are
about it for ten minutes and lose the
big picture you could just go ahead and
do it if you were really careful about
taking your routes and knowing what they
meant see this implies a route of what 1
minus alpha X equals 0 it implies the
route that alpha that that X equals
minus 1 over alpha right it would be a
little bit uglier if we did it that way
but you could do it that way so I just
wrote down what I know needs to be true
and this creates a quadratic equation
all on its own where when we get the
solution I've got alpha and I've got
beta and I just plug them right in there
because that's what I really want to
figure out ok normally the quadratic
equation lets you get X minus something
times X minus something but I don't want
that I want 1 minus something times X so
I doing it this way to avoid the
transformation later okay smarty-pants I
got this and I got this you guys got
these two things
squared okay but let's is this one of
the solutions at least we only need one
solution to this we're going to have
this come up actually again later when
there's a plus or a minus and we have to
figure out which one it is
and at that point I'm also just going to
pick one arbitrarily and act like it was
no big deal that I did it
it you kind of have to pick it carefully
and sometimes if you pick the wrong one
things don't work out later
except my hand waving on that alright so
this is one solution to this equation
let's check it add these two together do
you get one you do multiply them
together do you get negative 1 1 minus 4
1 minus 5 gives you minus 4 minus 4 over
4 is minus 1 it works
details notwithstanding you can get from
here to here so here's what we got we
got alpha equals this beta equals that
there is we've got a formula for capital
f of X the only thing is it's not a
formula that we can pull out the
coefficients of the generating function
we can only do that if we have these two
separate it out with an addition between
them so we have to go ahead and use
partial fractions here we have to say
this equals something times 1 minus
alpha X plus something times 1 minus
beta X alpha beta are these numbers I'll
leave them here I'm not going to write
them into that equation I'll just leave
them here and we'll plug them in at the
very end
partial fractions because if it looks
like this when we're all done then we
know what the coefficients are there
going to be powers of alpha and powers
of beta and if it looks like this one
we're all done we didn't have a
slightest clue what the coefficients
that will be so we want to make this
change and the way to get this change is
to figure out by partial fractions
what's C and D should be who remembers
how to do this anybody remember how to
do these things I'll give you a brief
refresher a brief refresher
but I'll kill the details and show you
what happens with a dot dot dot here's a
brief refresher if you multiply these
back out together to go back to this
what you get on the top is C minus beta
C X C minus beta C X plus D - Thank You
D Alpha X and that's going to be all
over this all over this there it is
that means there's X terms here and
there's constant terms the constant
terms have to add up and equal 1 so C
plus D equals 1 and the X terms have to
add up at equal 0 that means beta C
equals negative D alpha ok these two
equations need to be solved for C and D
we know beta and alpha those are numbers
again two simultaneous equations two
unknowns give it to your favorite
ninth-grader
and they'll solve C and D in terms of
alpha and beta you got a lot of algebra
dot-dot-dot here's what you get for C
and D when you're done
times one plus the square root of 5 over
2 and D equals minus 1 over the square
root of 5 times 1 minus the square root
of 5 over 2 I have to tell you that that
dot dot dot is a really annoying long
dot I it's a pain to solve these and do
the algebraic manipulation with this and
get C and D it will take you five or ten
minutes it would take us five or ten
minutes so believe me that it's worth
not showing the details and just going
from here to here and I sure that's
right so the C and D depend on the
alpha-beta which i've written in there
explicitly and here are the values now
I'm going to substitute it all back in
there and write it all out in the tail
one is square root of five 1 plus the
square root of five over two
over 2x Plus everybody with me I'm just
plugging it back in and writing it out
so we can look at it plus sorry it's a
minus here right minus 1 over the square
root of 5 1 minus the square root of 5
over 2 over 1 minus 1 minus the square
root of 5 over 2 X this is our f of X it
equals that whole big mess but this is
not so bad it's not so bad at all
almost done by by algebra this piece
here will forget this constant the one
over all this will give us coefficients
of this generating function equal two
powers of this right I'm taking those
coefficients and multiplying each one by
this number on top so if the coefficient
here normally would be 1 plus the square
root of 5 over 2 to the N in front of X
to the N let me write X to the N here
the coefficient from this part would be
1 plus the square root of 5 over 2 to
the N but that gets multiplied by this
so this n turns up to be n plus and we
get a 1 over square root of 5 this is
the coefficient in front of the X to the
nth term of this function the first part
here 1 plus square root of 5 over 2 to
the N came from 1 divided by this and
the multiplied part is just this
constant that sits on top because
there's no X there that's not that
doesn't do anything except multiply each
constant term through by this similarly
over here we have another X to the N
term in this generating function
and what is it going to be 1 minus root
5 over 2 to the N multiply it again
because it's there so n plus 1 and
subtract and negative multiply 1 over
the square root of 5 let me let me do it
again maybe I should have written it
like this I think it might have been
more clear we want to get the
coefficients for this generating
function okay Gary now if you just have
this the coefficients are going to be 1
plus square root of 5 over 2 to the N we
proved that yesterday that if this was a
2 would be 2 to the N if it's a 1 it's 1
to the N if it's a 1 plus square root of
5 over 2 it's 1 plus square root of 5
over 2 to the N but now I'm multiplying
this whole function by this constant so
all the coefficients in front of the X
to the ends all these coefficients get
multiplied by this therefore the actual
coefficient in front of the X to the end
looks like this an extra 1 plus square
root of 5 over 2 factor times 1 over the
square root of 5 okay you believe it
you're not just making me feel good yeah
all right this is the term in front of
the X to the end of this first function
that's the term in front of the second
function so if you want to know the term
in front of this overall capital f of X
you just subtract these two and here's
what you get here's the coefficient in
front of X to the N in capital f of X
it's 1 over the square root of 5 I'm
going to factor that out now I get 1
plus square root of 5 over 2 to the n
plus 1 minus 1 minus the square root of
5 over 2 to the n plus 1 this is equal
to this number is equal to what
capital F of the X to the N term and
that's the same as being the nth small F
term here is now a closed form formula
for F sub n now we've seen this formula
before you proved it by induction you
figured it out from a linear homogeneous
recurrence equation you can get it from
linear algebra God knows you can make a
little you know pamphlet eighty-nine
ways to derive you know the the closed
form formula for the Fibonacci numbers
and this is just one more all right
you're yes we slam this problem with
generating functions today and there it
is and that answer is right what Chris
mentioned before if you start with a 0 1
instead of a 1 1 then this n plus 1
turns into an N and that's another way
you sometimes see the Fibonacci numbers
so if you ever see the formula with an N
instead of an N plus 1 and you say hey
which one is right they're probably both
right and one starts the Fibonacci
numbers at 0 1 and the other starts the
Fibonacci numbers at 1 1 there isn't a
completely rigorous standard for which
for where you start alright questions
another example now the next example is
really really more technical but more
interesting because the next example we
cannot solve the recurrence equation 89
different other ways with the techniques
that you know here the only techniques
that you know to solve the next
recurrence equation are the techniques
we're going to use right now is
generating functions so it's kind of
we've left this and we've seen it in
problem sets and we've gone back to it
many times and today we're fine so I'm
going to I'm going to do a little review
and a little intro for two purposes to
remind you what this problem is all
about to refresh your memories and to
let your brains cool off from the
previous boring algebra part ok here we
go
problem number one binary trees how many
are there with n nodes we'll call this V
sub n how many binary trees are there
with B nodes here's another problem
mean by balanced parentheses sequences
of parentheses with nothing inside them
that are balanced in the way that we
normally think of being balanced you can
alright the inductive definition you
know what I mean if you don't know what
I mean then you need to define them but
I think you know how many are there how
many with n pairs of parentheses the
answer to this is the same as the answer
to this last questions matrix
multiplications how many ways to
technical way you have to multiply the
matrices left to right you can't flip
them around matrices are not commutative
but going left to right you can start
anywhere you can start in the middle and
do that left to right and then move over
and do another one left to right you
don't have to actually do the first two
and then the next two and then the next
two in other words if you have three
matrices you can do this these two a 2
times a 3 and then do a 1 times that
result or you can do a 1 times a 2 and
then do that result times a 3 always
going left to right for any particular
multiplication but where you start you
can associate any pairs you want so the
question is how many ways
to associate pairs with n plus 1
matrices so this is not identical
because there's an N plus 1 here and
there's N and the other two but if you
ask it for n plus 1 matrices it's the
same as having n pairs of balanced
parentheses and the same as having n
node binary trees yes these are all
Catalan numbers every one of these the
answer is C N equals the Catalan numbers
have 3 of them 3 out of 17 poor Sam is
17 all right well cool you should get an
idea why three matrices is the same as
two balanced parenthesis at least
intuitively because there's only two
sets of parentheses here but you all
know that there is a one-to-one
relationship between this problem and
this problem which is an obvious at
first glance and you did that on one of
our problem sets you associate the
multiplications with the open parens
here and the closed parens here with the
closed parens here and you can get a
one-to-one correspondence so these two
problems we have shown before are
identical what we haven't talked about
is this problem and what I want to
remind you today is what is the
recurrence equation for each of these
what is it remind you what it is and why
it is that way and show you that the
same recurrence equation holds here so
this problem is one of our group it
joins the collection okay all right
let's look at this problem
if you're trying to figure out the
number of ways to associate pairs and
you've got three matrices then the issue
is where does the last multiplication
happen this case it happens here the
last multiplication here happens here
you can either associate two to the
right and one on the left
or you can associate two on the left and
one on the right what if I had four
matrices I could associate 1 3 2 2 3 1
so if I want to figure out the total
number of ways to associate pairs of
matrices it's going to be how many ways
are there to associate this single
matrix combined with how many ways there
are to associate these two in this
particular case it's a simple there's
one way to do this there's one way to do
that there's one way to do this there's
one way to do that altogether you get
two ways here it's a little different
there's one way to do this there's two
ways to associate these three that be 1
times 2 there's one way to associate
this there's one way to associate that
that'd be 1 times 1 there's two ways to
associate these three one way to
associate the last one so if you work
this one through you'd get 2 times 1
plus 1 times 1 plus 2 times 1 so here's
what the here's what the situation's
look like you'd either get a 1 combined
with 3 matrices and that you know
there's two possibilities for so that
gives you 1 times 2 and then 2 and 2
there's one each that gives you 1 times
1 this is 1 times 2 1 times 1 and then 2
times 1 so to associate 4 matrices you
get 5 I want to make a chart of this
information then I'll write down the
recurrence equation here's a chart we'll
put it let's put it here Catalan numbers
and and C n 1 2 3 4 5 6 ok if you have
one matrix sorry if you have N equals 1
that means 2 matrices or 1 pair of
parentheses how many different ways are
there to do it I got a cup at 0 in here
too huh if I got no parentheses how many
ways are there to do it there's always
bugs people there's one if there's no
way right so I'll put zero in here too
that's also one if I got N equals two to
balance pairs of parenthesis or three
matrices three matrices there's four
matrices that means N equals three
there's five that's three pairs of
balanced parentheses let's write down
the recurrence equation here it is let's
call this let's call this balanced
parenthesis P sub n let's call this
matrix multiplications a sub n plus 1
I used a to represent the actual arrays
before now I'm using a for a different
purpose so be aware of this it's a bad
choice of letter here but but I'm using
it anyway because I want to use a I'm
using a here to represent the number of
different ways to multiply n plus 1
matrices this does not represent one of
the matrices itself ok so if you have
your notes make a note of that the old
A's are different from from this a here
let's try to get recurrence equations
for each of these
recurrence equation going to look like
you got to add up a lot of possibilities
a four for example is going to be a 1
combined with a 3 a 2 combined with a 2
and a 3 combined with a 1 so if I'm
doing a n plus 1 I'm going to start with
a 1 right so I is going to start at 1
and what's the other a that I use what
is it going to be if I pick if I pick
cake well if I pick I equals 1 and minus
I let's write it out a 3 equals what a a
1 times a 2 plus let's make sure that
that fits this a 1 times a it should be
a 2 right so n minus I minus I that work
out I is n is 3 3 minus I is 2 so 1/2
and then how high should I go
San is only 2 here 2 minus 1 is only
going to be 1 so this needs to be n - I
know plus 1 that's right these are the
details which I know this is right so so
think about it for second a 1 is the
number of ways to multiply 1 matrix
- n is 0 but it's the number of ways to
multiply 1 matrix together ok there's
one way to multiply one matrix together
how do I go up to 1 less than this which
is and this is correct
equation with a z' in it into an
equation with with balanced parentheses
in it we know that this is true you
prove this in a pset and plus one equal
P sub n let's convert these A's to these
peas okay and see what the summation
turns out to be here's what you get I
equals 0 to n minus 1 P I P n minus I
minus 1
1 here that corresponds to p0 so this
should start out at p0 if you have a 2
here that should correspond to p1 so
when I equals 0 that and N equals 2 this
should turn out to be P 1 so 2 minus 0
minus 1 is P 1 you can check this I work
these indices out before this is
actually right this equals this equals
this if this relationship is true which
you proved these are details that you
can check on your own or you can just
take my word for it we can also use drop
in the conversation this is the same as
P n n plus 1 is this recurrence equation
we know it's the same as P n so we came
up with this son and that's the same as
P n because it's all and plus 1 so all
these four are the same we've got two
different recurrence equations they both
have this kind of convoluted product in
them with the sum of each of the pieces
and they represent things like this yeah
Theresa
maybe I'm spending too much time on it
I'm just trying to review the recurrence
equations I'm trying to convince you
that these two problems really are that
if they are the same if these two things
are true like you proved in the problem
set that you get these why am i doing
this that's that's really Theresa's
question I'm doing this because I want
to convince you that binary trees is
also the same problem the way I'm going
to convince you this is I'm going to
convince you that the recurrence
equation we get for binary trees is
identical of this one for parentheses so
first I started with the only recurrence
equation you knew the one for matrices
and I reviewed it and I put it here then
I transformed it to what it would look
like if you had come up with a
recurrence equation for balanced
parentheses on your piece that you never
did this one you never analyzed the
balanced parentheses directly you
analyzed the matrix one and you did a
one to one correspondence between that
and the balanced parentheses what I'm
showing you here is what the recurrence
equation would look like if you took
that one-to-one correspondence and you
applied it to the formula it would look
like this and I'm going to show you
today is that binary trees have a
recurrence equation that also looked
like this we're going to use this
recurrence equation the BN and the PM
which are going to be identical yes and
we're going to need it yeah Tony yes
sorry Tony but I also changed this I
change the indices here and that's why
that's off by an extra one I started
these out at zero so so I know what you
mean I also when I first calculated this
took a double look at this and said huh
what's the deal but but do some examples
and you'll see that it's really right it
really does generate the the peas the
way you expect I could do that right but
if I did that it wouldn't look exactly
like one I'm going to get here and then
I'd have to do another transformation
later so I threw all the difficult stuff
into what I just spent time on rather
than the difficult stuff later it's like
the it's like
it's like the cuts you don't see on the
movie floor I there's other ways I could
have done this I decided I decided to
leave all the I'm not sure I get that
stuff right here so that when I talk
about the stuff that I think is more
important you'll definitely get it but
this stuff is just algebra and don't
worry about it
if you don't see why this and this are
the same take my word for it that it's
an algebraic calculation we can still
move on EJ you got that face that that I
hate to see it's that you know what I
meant you have a question is what I
meant
para let's let's try that again EJ any
questions you look pensive the last time
EJ looked like that he completely
corrected me on something that Andrew
had corrected me on previously which I
didn't quite understand but then finally
I got it
so whenever I see these faces now I have
to look with with much more care that
maybe I said something that was
completely wrong but I think I'm okay
here ya know I have to say I was really
careful about this it's pre-thanksgiving
I want to go home with a good feeling
that I didn't like lose you in the
middle of the lecture so I I nailed this
down through many late shows many Li
just how many binary trees are there
with one node one
nodes one
how many binaries are there with two
nodes 1 and 2 when we're talking about
binary trees they differ they differ if
you go right and you go left okay you
can't just rotate them and say they're
the same they're really different with
three nodes how many do you get you all
know you get five you can fill in this
chart a little more with these two
recurrence equations let's do it
how did the recurrence equations work
you're interested in four you go back to
the zero case and you multiply this one
times this one this one times this one
this one times this one this one times
this one you go down and you multiply by
the kind of the the compliment on the
other side so in other words to get five
you do 1 times 2 1 times 1/2 times 1 1
times 2 1 times 1/2 times 1 that gives
you 5 to get the next one you get 1
times 5 count it in your head plus 1
times 2 plus 2 times 1 plus 5 times 1
what's that I know what it is because I
did it before you were supposed to count
14 next one 1 times 14 1 times 5 2 times
2 5 times 1 14 times 1 just tell us
that's what you get yes of course here's
one there's two here's three here's four
and here's five okay Chris yep not yet
not until you said that
okay let's figure out how we figure out
how many binary trees there are forget
these things for a second new problem
binary trees when we're done figuring
out a recurrence equation I want to tell
you what it's going to look like it's
going to look just like this one exactly
the same as a parentheses 1 so that
connects us back to this world here's
how it works let's go from the hi Sarah
let's go from the 3 to the 4 case I want
to make now a binary tree with 4 nodes
so I start off with a note on top and I
can connect at I can continue to the
left and the right with binary trees
which together have to add up to 2 what
well this is we're doing four so
together they have to add up to 2 3
because I got one on top that I started
with so what are my choices I'm gonna
put nothing on the left and put all
these three on the right right I can you
make a right turn and connect it to any
of these 5 can I say three I'm in five I
can put all these five on the right
let's call that the zero three kings
that's when I put zero on the left and
three nodes on the right this gives me
five okay if I put one on the left I can
put how many on the right how many
different are there with one there's one
with one and there's two of two so that
gives me two possible combinations I can
put two on the left and one on the right
that gives me another two combinations
I can put three on the left and zero on
the right that gives me another five
five seven nine fourteen look how we did
it we took the number of binary trees
with zero nodes we multiplied it by the
number of binary trees with three nodes
because we wanted to combine every
possible left subtree with every
possible right subtree as long as the
sum of the two sub trees added up to one
no less than the number I need because I
used one node at the top so I added
these up and made them three everybody
get that should we check that again if I
want to make a four node thing I can put
zero on the left three on the right
there's five combinations one
combination four zero five combinations
four three one times five gives you
three let's say I was going now that we
know that there are four binary trees
are equal to 14 say we know that now I'm
going to five here's my top I can go
left with zero and I can go right with 4
or 14 let me write this out I'm going
I'm doing ce-5 now or b5 I can go right
with zero and left with four and that
gives me 14 14 possible binary trees of
size four I can go left with 1 and right
with 3 that gives me there's one way to
do this there are five ways to do that
that's five I can go left with 2 and
right with two there's two ways to go
left with 2 there's two ways to go right
with two altogether the number of
combinations is two times two so I
multiply the be zeros and the be fours
and the be ones and the be threes and
the b-2s and the b-2s I keep going I get
B 3 B 1 multiplied gives me 5 and B 4 B
0 gives me 14 I
I'm up I got 28 38 42 so now I know b5
is 42 all right other questions about
these examples this gives you all the
possible binary trees of one new height
and notice the induction here we make
one new node at the top and we go left
and right we do it top down not not from
the leaves we don't have the new one at
the leaves that wouldn't give us
anything really nice so here's the
recurrence equation
tell me what it is we start at b0 we go
up to B for I equals 0 to n minus 1
here's B I so the first one of our B
term starts at 0 goes to n minus 1 the
next one starts at n minus 1 it goes
down to 0 so if I equals 0 how do I get
n minus 1 and my B and minus I minus 1
here's our recurrence equation as I just
described it in general and if you look
at it you'll notice it's the exact same
recurrence equation as we got here and
this recurrence equation is the one for
parentheses and this came from the fact
that it's equivalent to the 1 for
matrices so all these three are exactly
the same B sub n P sub n a sub n plus 1
are all identical they will all be the
same number for any given n alright this
is intro questions so far
that's all I need to know yeah yeah I
brought a couple of chocolate turkeys in
on Thanksgiving I love a Learning Tree
him
I like Thanksgiving it's a good holiday
he's going crazy no problemo
under control okay here's here's what we
want to do
we've got these recurrence equations for
B sub N and they're all and P sub n + a
sub n plus 1 they're all equal to the
Catalan numbers we want to get a closed
form for the Catalan numbers I don't
want to just be apt to compute these
recurrences all the time I like to fill
in a chart and know exactly what it is
if it's n I can plug it into a formula
and figure out what C sub n is in order
to do it we're going to come up with a
generating function for the Catalan
numbers and work our way backwards to
the coefficients the generating function
for the Catalan numbers that we're going
to use is called C for Catalan and it
starts out 1 + X + 2 x squared + 5 X
cubed + 14 X to the fourth + what was in
X 142 X to the fifth etc where the
coefficients let's call the coefficients
bees we might as well use bees the
coefficients are the B sub ends B 3
equals 5 for example we are trying to
get a closed form for the B sub ends
defined by that recurrence relation over
there assuming that this is the
generating function called C of X so the
capital C here is like the capital F
before and the capital B here is like
the small F before but the recurrence
equation for the bees is more
complicated than the recurrence equation
we had before when we had F sub n small
F equals F sub n minus 1 plus F sub n
minus 2 we shifted things over once and
twice added them and we got an equation
that way what are we going to do now
with something like this if we shift
this over nothing's going to add up we
can shift it over to our hearts content
nothing's going to add up we have to do
something else now here I'm going to
motivate this by what I taught you last
time I taught you that if you take two
generating functions and you multiply
them together I taught you how to figure
out what the new coefficients are based
on the old coefficients anybody remember
how to do that let's do an example with
this if you forgot I'm going to take two
C of X's and I'm going to multiply them
together everybody with me
I'll put them right underneath each
other for those of you who forgot how to
multiply generating functions here's a
refresher C squared axe what's the
constant term when you multiply this
times this the only constant term you're
going to get is 1 times 1 what's the X
terms 1 times X plus 1 times X gives you
times 2x squared 1 times 2x squared x
times X that's it 2 2 and 1/5 what's the
let's do a couple more what's the cubed
terms it's 1 times 5 X cubed 5 X cubed
times 1 that's 10 2x squared times X
that's 12 x times 2x squared that's 14
that's it does that sound familiar if
better sound familiar geez that's
exactly what this recurrence equation is
doing this recurrence equation the
definition of these constants is based
on a multiplication of the generating
functions for the set of constants one
behind think about that all we did here
that when we multiply these two together
is the exact same thing we do when we
calculate the next constant here but
when we calculate the next constant here
we do it with just the X cubes and back
so that should give us the following
intuition if we want to get an equation
of C of X in terms of itself let's
factor out an X to shift everything back
one and then square it and see what
happens
something like that we've already
squared it so we're on our way all right
let's go
let's do this because what let's take
one of these C of X's and pull the
constant thing out see X minus 1 and
factor out an X from here I pull the
constant term out so now I can factor an
X out now I can shift everything down by
1 what do I get when I factor an X out
of this somebody read it off where is
that what is that that's the square of
my two generating functions how would
you notice this when you were playing
with on in your own you wouldn't unless
you got that intuition that multiplying
two generating functions and looking at
the coefficients is the same as
generating these coefficients on their
own but these coefficients are generated
from the coefficients that come
previously so let's first take what we
have and factor out an X so everything
shifted over then let's multiply them
together taken away the constant term to
begin with and when we look at it all it
equals what we started with whoa where
am i heading here's where I'm heading
see X minus one equals x times C squared
X this is C squared F we just did it
this is the coolest thing in the world
now instead of having recurrence
equations that are just shifted over we
are leveraging the power of algebra to
do something really cool with accounting
right we are we're yanking down on
algebra when you take what we know about
how to multiply algebraic things
together it corresponds to this very
very interesting recurrence relation on
the coefficients sometimes called a
convolution here's our equation we got
to solve C of X get a closed form for it
and then fiddle with that and somehow
God knows got the coefficients for those
things because it's not going to be as
easy it was as it was before so now
we're on a narrow on a straight path
hopefully we won't get stuck
we're done with the combinatoric part of
it in the counting part of it
we're in calculus land here bless you
ones that buy anything who else has a
pinkies up that's what I'll ask for
pinkies up let's make an equation here x
squared sorry X C squared of X minus C
of X plus 1 equals 0 I took that
equation and I'm making into a quadratic
equation in C of X now I can't just
factor like I did before remember
Michael said I could just factor before
and get C of X but now I can if I want
to solve for C of X I have to use the
quadratic formula think of this as your
variable C of X as your variable and X
here is your constant think of this as
like 2 x squared minus X plus 1 where
the 2 is the X I shift your focus here
foreground/background so let's get the
quadratic formula and get it to work C
of x equals minus B what's the B part 1
so that's 1 plus or minus the square
root of B squared is 1 minus 4ac 4 times
1 times X minus 4 X divided by 2a
divided by 2x
and the C is one in our quadratic minus
B minus B plus or minus the square root
of b squared minus 4ac all right it also
gets negative you're saying hmm yeah now
we have the stupid plus or minus again
right we have two functions we can deal
with here this is kind of this gives you
kind of the power and the danger of
leveraging right what are we doing here
we're creating a function that has
integer coefficients if we wrote it out
as something plus something times X plus
something times x squared right but
somehow now it's a function that you can
graph and that has imaginary values and
what are those mean with respect to our
counting and does it matter we never
plug any X's into this anyway looking at
the coefficients we're just playing with
these functions to see what the
coefficients are we don't give two hoots
what happens when we plug X's into them
it opens up a new world of exploration
which we will do a different day not
today all right so here's the only hand
waving that I'm going to do today I am
NOT going to deal with this plus one I'm
going to use one minus this and it works
out if I do that and it doesn't work out
so nicely the other way so I get to
choose one of these I'm going to choose
the one with - so
evening well as long we know C of X say
presumably can equal either one so
presumably the functions should be the
same so I just pick one that's gonna
make my calculation easier I don't know
there might be some other good
explanation but I know that this one
works at and gives me the numbers I'm
looking for so let's use it now here's
the thing this doesn't look anything
like one divided by one minus something
this isn't even close we're just dead
meat here right I mean in the other case
we had 1 over 1 minus X minus x squared
we could factor it we could use partial
fractions we had some chance here is a
typical place where if you don't have
more tools you give up if you take out
your regular old toolbox and you apply
it to this you just say well I don't
know what the coefficients of this are
this is as far as I get I worked really
hard I'm done but we have to pull out a
better tool that's all we're gonna pull
out us from calculus it's a tool called
Taylor series I'll remind you how it
works we're going to use it to figure
out the coefficients of this function
and here's how it works
the hard part of this is not the 1 over
2x that's just going to end up dividing
everything by X and shifting everything
over one spot one way or the other so
the 1 over 2x is no trick is no sorry
the dividing by 2x is no trick it's the
1 minus square root of 1 minus 4x that's
the trick and of that it's this part
that's the trick this is the hard part
we don't know anything about this
function of what the numbers on it look
like so we're gonna concentrate on this
figure out what the coefficients here
look like put it back in here and figure
out what the total coefficients look
like so that's our sub goal and here it
is something plus something times X plus
something times x squared plus something
times X cubed what are those something's
for square root of 1 minus 4x so do you
remember that in calculus we routinely
like to write things as polynomials we
don't like sine X we prefer 1 minus x
cubed over 3 factorial plus X to the
fifth over 5 factorial minus X to the
seventh over 7 factorial we don't like
e to the X we prefer one plus X plus x
squared over two factorial plus X cubed
over three factorial we write everything
out if we can in a polynomial makes it
easier to analyze makes it easier to do
certain things with it we'd like to do
the same thing here so I'm going to
remind you what we learned two months
ago without reviewing it as a separate
topic here's what we learned two months
ago let's call this G of X our function
if you want to write this out as a
polynomial then Taylor series tells you
you can write it out like this you can
approximate it around zero and do the
following G of zero plus the derivative
of G at zero times X plus the double
derivative of G of zero times x squared
over 2 factorial plus the triple
derivative of G at zero times X cubed
over three factorial
etc ding-ding-ding ring that bell okay
so we can figure out the constants for
our generating function all we got to do
is take derivatives and plug in zero and
then divide through by the right
factorial it's just mechanics we can do
it it just might take a little bit of
time
stop questions so far I'm leaving this
up here we're going to come back to this
spot later to plug this in but now we've
got to take a route through Taylor
series to get these coefficients and
they're not going to be so pretty but
though at the very end simplify to
something really nice who remembers how
to take a derivative
second derivative third derivative
fourth derivative fifth derivative
anybody remember I will do this for you
if you don't remember 1/2 1 minus 4x to
the negative 1/2 times negative 4 yes
and I'm gonna need more room so I'm
going to rewrite that I'll rewrite it
nice and cleanly 1/2 1 minus 4x to the
negative 1/2 times negative 4 that's the
first derivative let's do it again I'll
just do it for you minus 1/4 1 minus 4x
negative 3 halves negative 4 squared 3/8
positive 1 minus 4x negative 5 halves
minus 4 cubed I'm going to do two more
because we're going to need enough to
see a pattern - 15 16 1 minus 4x to the
negative 7 halves minus 4 to the fourth
and the last one I'll do and then we'll
have to look for a pattern a hundred and
5/32 1 minus 4x to the negative 9 halves
minus 4 to the fifth those are the first
1 2 3 4 5 derivatives of this function
should I do that to the Internet to sit
and scratch this stuff down I'll do that
and then you can get them just sit and
look I can always do that what's our
next step now that I've gotten all the
derivatives what goes into these
derivatives zero goes into them I'm
looking for the pattern after the zero
goes in its get a lot better once I put
the zeros in not a lot better gets a
little better it's important because you
won't notice the pattern if if I if I
had simplified it well you might have
but I might not it so I'm gonna make
these arrows to show what happens when X
becomes zero when X becomes zero and
every one of these parenthesis what
happens you get one line is zero zero to
some power is 1 1 to some power is 1
thank you all these become one so the
only things that last are the
coefficients in front and these powers
of four now you'll notice and this is
annoying the powers of four alternates
sign right here it's negative here it's
positive here negative here positive
here negative but watch and this is nice
when it's negative the coefficient here
is positive and when it's positive the
coefficient here is negative so the
overall sign is constant and it's going
to be negative you really notice that
that's helpful for our pattern so here's
the pattern it's going to be hmm
and means the nth derivative let's come
up with a pattern we get minus because
there's a minus sign all around we get 4
to the 4 to the n then we got this
annoying fraction and we got a top part
to this fraction and a bottom part to
this fraction who wants to do the bottom
part Micah what's a bottom part two to
the N is the bottom part it gets
multiplied by two every time that's
pretty straightforward that's why I
didn't I didn't stop here I didn't want
you to think that it's always one less
than a power of two to the N so I went
one more to show you this number gets
uglier so there's a two to the end on
the bottom
what do we get on the top four to the N
minus one
no how do you get the numbers on the top
let's go through them here
well actually the beginning it kind of
takes a little while to get started but
once you're here one times where did
this three come from one times that
three where did this 15 come from one
times three times one times three times
five times it's all the odd numbers
multiplied by each other up to a certain
point up to what point one times three
times five times seven
what's the last one the last one in the
case of five was seven two n minus one
would get us all the way up to nine here
and we only went up to seven so it's 2n
minus 3 right because when you go up to
five you only go up to seven 2n minus 3
this is the actual coefficient in front
of this square root of one minus four X
there it is we can simplify it a little
and we're going to dhaniya tired
like this class is like one one long
date gone awry alright how does this
simplify shop that's better
I got no denominator now bye-bye that's
okay right but now what else am I
missing these are the F n of zeros you
know where my I guess GN sorry GN of
zeros I called him G naught F but I need
the N factorial on the underneath right
I got to put that in so I'll put that in
right now
coefficients that sit in front of the X
to the N in this function square root of
1 minus 4x there they are they look bad
but now we're almost done we're almost
at the end and it won't be so bad
get and then look at this and hope maybe
we can make some sense out of this right
now that's too much abstraction let's
get to some real numbers let's figure
out what the numbers are that go here
here here and here
you can do it by plugging in ends from 0
to 1 to 2 let's see what they are what
is actually G of X gonna be G of x
equals let's do it put in 0 what do you
get it's a little tricky right because
if you look at our list this 2n minus 3
stuff doesn't really kick in until after
the first 2 you kind of need a base
taste to get you started all this stuff
only works for n bigger than or equal to
2 for N equals 0 and n equal 1
you have to just calculate it directly
what is G of 0 put 0 in here square root
of 1 it's 1 what is G prime of 0 you end
up getting 1/2 times negative 4 which is
negative 2 now you can start plugging
into your heart's content
any numbers bigger than 2 here because
now it works anybody do it let's get a
couple more terms 1 minus 2x minus I'm
going to force you to do this and I
won't tell you what's on my paper until
I get at least two more terms 4/3 for
the next one G god I hope not
let's but you tried all right guys so
let's do it together
but what N equals 2 here 2 squared is 4
right if N equals 2 this goes up to 1
right so it's minus 4 over 2 so it's
minus
next one or third no Rosie Eric is
really smart she does things a thousand
times more complicated than plugging in
the number two to this and getting four
thirds apparently so
I'm giving you another chance give me
the next one oh all right I'll write it
out like this you won't simplify it
let's leave the pattern agreed two cubed
times one times three times three
factorial times X cubed minus what's the
next one - to the fourth one three five
four factorial times X to the fourth
etc now we've got some actual numbers
there remember this G of X is this thing
that I boxed out here okay right that's
what it was G of X square root of one
minus four X so now we're gonna go take
this whole long thing and put it back in
there subtract off from one now we've
got C X finally an hour and fifteen
minutes later one minus one is zero and
then subtract all this out all this
stuff becomes positive and then you
divide through by 2 X so 2 X into 2 X is
1 plus 2 X into 2 x squared is X 2 X
into X cubed 2 squared 1 times 3 3
factorial x squared next 1 2 cubed 1 3 5
for a pattern here we're going to look
for a pattern we're going to come up
with a closed form formula you look at
it and we'll do it together and I got
exactly five minutes and we are finished
five minutes you can do it you can do it
you can do it
to the end what is that coefficient what
is the pattern here who wants to take a
stab at it some of its I think straight
forward some of its not what does it
look like to to the 2 to the N right
because we divided through by 2 so 2 to
the N then I'm doing all the odd numbers
up to what point if it's squared we go
to 1 times 3 if it's cubed we go to 1 3
5 so to say Chun good good 1 3 5 odd
numbers all the way up to 2 n minus 1
very good and then divided by n plus 1
factorial there we go yeah we're going
to get rid of it in a second we're going
to make this a little better takes two
minutes to do this do you guys remember
the stuff I did with with world series
going all the way and and we got to n
choose n at the numerator remember that
something like this 2n choose n divided
by 2 to the 2 to the N and it ended up
equaling 1 3 5 up to 2n minus 1 divided
by 2 4 6 up to 2 ends
remember that we did that the other day
that should give you a big big hint as
to how we're going to simplify this here
when you see sequences of odd numbers
multiplied by themselves you can almost
always get it back to 2n choose n as
long as you have enough choose to go
around I'm going to show you how to do
this it's it's simple algebra although
it might not dawn on you're just playing
with it but we're going to turn this
expression into something with a 2n
choose n in it Heather
you have a question you got that multi
neuron look like
Heather here we divide it through by 2x
so that got rid of one of the twos in
each of these terms so now I'm here some
plus one yes yes yes okay okay here's
what we're gonna do we're going to do
something that isn't quite obvious what
we're going to use this as intuition to
motivate we're going to try to turn this
into something that looks like this
and here's how we do it first we'll
factor out a 1 over n plus 1 so I got 2
to the N times all those odd numbers
big deal you're saying
normally don't do I'm going to
unsimplified I'm going to add a term to
the top and bottom because adding a term
to the top and bottom is going to make a
top disappear into something simple what
is the top need to turn into something
simple it needs an N factorial I'll show
you this in a second - to the ends all
the odd numbers it's a 2 N minus 1 Chuck
an N factorial in up here and put an
extra one down here okay we've done
nothing but add an extra n factorial on
the top and the bottom but there's a
really important reason for this okay
they're pairing up and going out to
dinner every one of these twos goes with
one of these values from the n factorial
so the 5 4 3 2 1 becomes 10 8 6 4 2 10 8
6 4 2 boom everybody see that so what's
the top now the top is 2 and factorials
the bottom is n factorial times n
factorial so now that dot dot dots are
gone whenever you see dot dot dots with
odd numbers between them look for this
trick look for lots of powers of 2 all
over the place
you can throw in n factorials and fill
in the gaps it's a good algebra trick
last step what's 2 n factorial divided
by n factorial times n factorial this is
a counting thing I got to in fact 2 n
things I want to permute them any way I
can
half of them are exactly the same type
the other half is exactly the same type
it's the same as taking 2 n things and
choosing an event ok 2 n factorial
divided by n factorial times 2 n minus n
factorial this is the same as this this
is the cattle number that's what I
promised you originally now if you want
to know what the how many binary trees
there are with
50 nodes you can do one over 51 times
100 choose 50 and boom get your answer
close form binomial coefficient divided
by n plus 1 all right very last thing
just a little exclamation point to the
very end of this whole lecture let's say
I gave you I'm not going to give you
this on a test but let's say I did I'm
really not there's gonna be nothing like
this on the test but it's a kind of a
question that you could see in a problem
set or a test I said here's a number 2 n
choose n prove that it's divisible by n
plus 1 right that's a reasonable
question to ask not obvious that it's
the bizzle by n plus 1
maybe it's obvious there's a lot of ways
to prove it and here is probably one of
the most convoluted twisted ways to
prove it well I just proved after an
hour and a half that this is the Catalan
number and the Catalan number has to be
an integer
therefore 2n choose n has to be
divisible by n plus 1 all right
that's like taking a jackhammer to kill
a fly there's a lot of other ways to
prove that this number is divisible by n
plus 1 in a more straightforward way and
part of what mathematics is all about
and part of what you should get out of
this whole course is you are getting a
huge set of tools sometimes you're not
going to have the experience to know
which one is the best one to use and
you're going to look like to an expert
somebody with a jackhammer trying to
kill a fly and sometimes you're going to
pick just the perfect tool and I want to
give you guys an example and compliment
you since I'm always I'm always offering
ridicule but I got an offer compliments
the this last exam I gave a combinatoric
problem this Pizza problem right I was
sitting there writing the exam and Tara
said let's order pizza and I said fine
and she goes what do you want I said
good and then I'm thinking I'm thinking
I probably go what kind of County
problem what kind of County farmer go
hey give me that
you know menu and I looked at and I say
oh they really have 23 toppings and this
I made up a pizza problem I had to fix
it a little to make it a legitimate
problem the first problem I came up with
I thought was too hard the next one I
came up with was too easy
I got no that was just right but I got
to tell you that when I gave that
problem
I saw one way to do it a way that I
thought was straightforward more or less
if you got the basics you'd have a
decent chance to get that answer you
might go wrong a little bit but but
everybody had a decent shot at it and
then I didn't grade that problem Terra
graded it but she showed me some of your
solutions no less than say 30 percent of
the class solve that problem in a way
that not only I didn't think of but even
after I saw it I wasn't sure it was
right like oh I don't think that's right
and I checked it and I double-check that
and I triple checked it and then it was
right and it was really a much more
elegant way and a much better tool to
use than the one that I thought to use
the one that I thought was just like the
Nutcracker for nut but this one was like
like some slick way of just sliding the
nut open and and a lot of you did this
without mentioning any names not to
embarrass anyone or either positively or
negatively but but it was very
impressive to me to see that you just
took the set of tools and used it in a
way that I would have never predicted
and didn't predict on my own and that's
really what you should be getting out of
the class when you see these things in
other ways in other forms and algorithms
and in Java and software engineering you
should at least have a vague memory of
this technique and go back and be able
to refresh your memory from these super
textbooks and and make good applications
of it all right done thank you for
staying light