we're moving on to a new topic
but the Segway is really natural we were
talking about sums and now we're
segwaying into recurrence equations
which are usually solved by coming up
with some sums that we have to
manipulate and how it relates to
recursion and induction mathematical
deduction that you learn so far and
recursion that you learned that you
learned last month so we're going to
move into this slowly there's one little
topic that will come up today that
really belongs in the last problem set
and that's geometric series and
variations of geometric series you'll
see that in about 15 minutes there's one
problem on the last piece set that you
need to know how to do that for and you
can hand that in today if you haven't
done that yet in case you you were
waiting for me to do it so we'll do that
soon okay the way we're going to begin
on recurrence equations is to start off
with the most I think the simplest
recurrence equation I can possibly think
of and also maybe the most common one
you'd see in your day to day of
goings-on in life and that is you put
some money in the bank and you get some
interest back on it okay so say you have
a hundred bucks and you put it in the
bank and they promise they'll give you
ten percent interest at the end of the
year
so at the end of the year you get one
hundred and ten dollars okay and you can
take it out and leave or you can let
your money ride go for another year
right and they'll give you another ten
percent so let's write this out in math
talk here's the amount of money you have
after a certain number of years we'll
call it money money zero is how much
money you have after zero years and
let's say that's a hundred dollars and
money one assuming it's ten percent is
going to be one hundred and ten dollars
how much do you have after the second
year just to make sure everybody gets
this one hundred twenty one dollars
right you don't just get another ten you
get ten percent of this ten percent of
this is 11 so you get one hundred and
twenty one in general if you want to
know how much money you have in the ight
here you can write that down with
respect to
much money you had in the bank after the
year before in particular it's
everything you had the year before plus
10% of what you had the year before and
you get that by multiplying by 1/4 what
you had before plus 0.1 plus 10% so 1
point 1 times M I minus 1 that's a
recurrence equation it's a equation that
tells you the value of something in
terms of itself on a smaller index it's
just like recursion every time you write
a recursion a recursive program using
recursion you say I'm going to do this
program and in the third step I'm going
to do the program again for a smaller
input ok so a recurrence equation is a
mathematical form of recursion in some
ways and a lot of recurrence equations
end up being equations representing how
many steps your algorithms are going to
take so if you have an algorithm that
calls itself and you want to figure out
what's the time complexity this
algorithm
it'll end up being a recurrence equation
and you have to learn to solve that
recurrence equation in order to figure
out the time complexity of that
algorithm and that's probably the place
where recurrence equation to show up the
most in computer sciences and analyzing
algorithms ok questions so far so here's
the way a recurrence equation usually
looks it gives you the relationship
between one case and some other smaller
cases and it gives you a base case so
let's solve this so that instead of this
recurrence relationship we get what
sometimes people call a closed form a
formula here that just has I in it that
doesn't have any dot dot dots I want to
find rigorously what a closed form is
but it basically means something that
you can just plug in the number and
compute quickly without having to worry
about loops or computation or anything
so some of you probably can see what
what this is but what I want to do is
pedantically go through a method which
will be useful when it isn't so obvious
to see what the answer is here so here's
here's one method and it's a brute-force
method of solving recurrences and it
will help you solve a lot of recurrence
equations but when they get complicated
this method will break down and we'll
need some fancier techniques
and later on a couple lectures down the
line I'll show you some fancier
techniques and I should mention in
advance recurrence equations are from
discrete math the continuous version of
a recurrence equation is a differential
equation ok differential equations are
like continuous recurrence equations to
some extent and a lot of the techniques
that you can use in differential
equations you borrow for recurrence
equations so with that said those of you
who have taken differential equations
and maybe hated it
recurrence equations are anywhere near
as bad they are discrete and you can
usually get a better sense of what's
going on without just mysteriously
following rules so that's we're going to
do right now we're not going to
mysteriously follow a rule we're just
going to logically figure out what the
solution is and here's how we do it we
know that this relationship is true so
what we're going to do is we want to get
rid of this M on this side and just get
something like an I squared you know
something with a formula there so if we
want to get rid of this we'll just
figure out what it equals and substitute
for it well what is M I minus 1 equal
well the good thing about a recurrence
equation is that it tells us what M of
anything equals M I equals 1 point 1 mi
minus 1 so mi minus 1 equals 1 point 1
mi minus 2 okay in place of I I put I
minus 1 so Y minus 1 minus 1 is I minus
2 and now I take this my whole goal was
to get rid of this M and now I put this
back here and here's what I get as my
result which I'll Circle M I equals 1.1
1.1 times 1.1 1.1 squared times M I
minus 2 all right we got that process
everybody with me All Right see ya ever
caught anybody crab a question
everybody's ok good
sharing question yeah I just missed that
last step you just substitute it back oh
I see that so in place of M I minus 1 we
get 1 point 1 mi minus 2 so I get 1
point 1 1 point 1 mi minus 2 it's one
point 1 squared so what if I did this
again the whole process again get rid of
mi minus 2 and put it back in there what
does this look like the next time
point one cubed because we really want
to do is see a pattern what if I do it
our times I do it as many times as I
like because you really want to get rid
of this right now what am i doing I
still have this this M here goodbye I
want to get rid of it bye-bye
when can I get rid of it when it's M
zero when I hit the base case so I want
to do this as many times until the base
case shows up so let's see what happens
when I do with our times when I do it
our times I get one point one two the r
times m i- r and what should our be so
that that mi minus r becomes M zero R
should be equal to I so if I do it I
times let R equal I then I get M mi
equals one point one to the I times M
zero which is a hundred so there's a
formula for how much money I have after
the I here and that's why if you go talk
to some financial investor who memorizes
some of these numbers in their heads if
you figure ten percent a year which is
what the stock market's been doing for
the last 50 years on the average per
year more or less and you're going to
leave your money in long term then how
long does it take for one point 1 to the
I to end up being 2 that means your
money's doubled and I'd like to tell you
when your money's doubled because it
makes it feel good yeah so between 7 & 8
years something like that 1 point 1 to
the 7 something ends up being 2 and it's
a good thing to keep in mind 1 point 1
squared is about 1 point 2 square that
again
1 point 4 square that again 1.96 so it's
more or less 8 years that's enough
percent so it's a good approximation
good all right well that's a formula
back interest you might remember this
from two months ago when I was
introducing the the letter E or the
number E right and we cut this day
and we did it every half year every
month every day every second and then
out of that came this very complicated
formula for e that had a limit involved
in it we're not going to go down that
direction today but it should remind you
of that this is just a simple recurrence
equation we solved it but what by the
method I call repeated substitution it's
just a logical method follow it to the
end you almost always get some success
but when the recurrence equation is a
little bit uglier you got to get fancier
techniques or you got to give up on this
completely alright questions so far if
you did take this to the exponential to
these continuous interest FN is no
longer a discrete problem or could it
still be no if you take it if you take
it and you know when you compound it say
every moment then it becomes a
continuous problem right right then it's
no longer discrete let's do another
problem like this set up a recurrence
equation but this time the problem we'll
do is an algorithm that all of you
probably know and we'll create a
recurrence equation that's the time
complexity of the algorithm how many
steps it takes in order to solve the
algorithm will solve the recurrence
equation by the same method and then
we'll move on to towers of Hanoi which
you've seen before and which is a
classic example of recursion it will
take us to the next stage alright so the
next example is sometimes called binary
search and I like to just think of it as
a game to play with kids so I'm thinking
of a number you have to guess the number
and you're allowed to ask me a question
make a guess say seven and I have to
tell you whether it's you know higher or
lower than my secret number okay
that's equivalent to if I give you a
list of names in a big long array and
they're all sorted and you want to find
a particular name you go into the center
of that list and you check if the name
that you're looking for is bigger than
or smaller than the name in the center
of my list and depending on the answer
you go to the right half of the list of
the left half of the list so we're going
to do this with with numbers all right
so everybody knows how to play right if
I pick a number from one to ten you're
going to guess five and if I say it's
too big you're going to guess right
halfway between the other all right
so let's analyze this algorithm we're
not going to write it out in scheme you
could write it if you wanted to but
let's analyze it how long does it take
we'll say TN is the amount of time it
takes if you have the biggest number
being n or the length of your array is n
so every time I make a guess I'm going
to do binary search on a smaller problem
how small is the problem that I do it on
the next time half the size and let's
not worry too much about whether it's
even or odd because it'll just make the
analysis a little ugly will approximate
and over to okay
how many steps does it take before I can
turn this into a problem where the
recursion works on half the size what do
I have to do I have to ask one question
and get an answer right one step we'll
call that so here's the recurrence
equation one plus T and divided by two
and how long does it take me to solve
this problem if the person says I'm
thinking of a number between 1 and 1
guess because we just believe everybody
can I'm thinking uh between 1 and 1 do
you all know what it is all right so T 1
is 0 and here is the recurrence equation
for any other n why did I use end this
time instead of I it doesn't matter what
letter you use don't use 17 use a letter
yeah alright let's solve this the same
way we did before but this time it won't
be quite as simple but almost as simple
the next time it'll be a little more
complicated the time after that a little
bit more until we say well this method
isn't working and we come up with some
new methods all right
the method before works like this we
want to get rid of TN over 2 so we write
that underneath here and that equals 1
plus 4 and over 2 takes the place of n
so it becomes T half of n over 2 is n
over 4 and if we take this and
substitute back in there we get T and
equals 1 plus 1
tn over 4 okay
now we're going to do this a whole bunch
more times say I do it R times instead
of writing for here I could write 2
squared and that might give you a hint
every time I do it this exponent here
pops up by 1 every time I do it it gets
multiplied by a factor of 2 so the
exponent goes up by one and I get an
extra one here in the Sun so what does
it look like when I do it R times R plus
T and again I want to get this down
until it's a base case so I get to
choose how many times I want to do it
until I hit that base case and that
means I want this n divided by 2 R to
equal what T equal 1 because that's my
base case alright so that means n has to
equal 2 to the R and R has to be log
base 2 of n for me to get rid of this T
on the right side I need to do this as
many times as the log base 2 of N so if
my end started out 64 I need to do this
6 times 64 - 32 - 16 - 8 - 4 - 2 - 1
see what I get here I get T sub n equals
log base 2 of n plus T of 1 and T of 1
is equal to 0 so here's my closed form
solution for this recurrence equation
and we say that binary search is a big
theta log n algorithm it's a very fast
algorithm my questions about this I
you don't have any other information
about this stuff you're searching
through yeah we aspire to this yes the
answer searching for more to 1024 you
have to better we can't you can't unless
you know something else about the
numbers unless you have some more
information
yeah because I want this index here to
turn into a 1 so I can get rid of it so
I have choice over R R is how many times
I do this iterative repeated
substitution and I just going to want to
figure out what R should be so that n
divided by 2 R turns into a 1 so I set
it to 1 and I calculated what our should
be so I chose this because I want to do
it that many times until T 1 shows up
that makes sense
other questions here's a baby toy this
puzzle has some kind of legend or
folklore associated with it you know
that some group of monks were hanging
around in a basement and found a secret
piece of paper and the secret piece of
paper described this puzzle and it said
there's 64 these doughnuts on a big post
and if you follow the rules and transfer
them all from this post to this post
then some grade apocalyptic vision will
look blah blah blah it's just a made-up
folklore and it's a fun story but I
don't think this puzzle is actually more
than 100 years old in fact and I don't
think anybody really knows the real
origin of it but
but I think as far back as anybody is
tracted it only goes back a hundred
years and here's the puzzle the puzzle
is you want to move this set of
doughnuts from here say to here and
there's a middle spot in between that I
can use to help me and the rule is I
can't just pick up all four things I can
only move one at a time and I'm not
allowed to put bigger ones on top of
smaller ones so only smaller ones can go
on top of bigger ones I'm just fooling
around those are legal moves in this
puzzle so how do we move all these four
from here to here doing those rules you
can get lost in the jungle of solving
this puzzle especially if you had 64
doughnuts and not have any idea where
you are but if you organize your
thoughts recursively this becomes a
three line program and all the details
are behind the scenes in the recursive
stack that your program does for you and
that's why it's such a classic example
of recursion so I think you've all seen
this example before but I'm going to
review the recursive solution write it
up in pseudocode on the board we'll do a
couple examples make sure everybody gets
it then we're going to analyze its time
complexity see how long it takes a
geometric series is going to show up so
that's when I'll show you how to solve
geometric series in versions of them and
then we're going to discuss possible
variations and I'm going to show you a
graph of this picture a graph of the
computation which will give you a bird's
eye view and an understanding of a
problem that most people never get from
just thinking about the recursion and
that will show you the power of graphs
how graphs sometimes give you exactly
that an incredible perspective on a
problem that you otherwise miss
completely all right so that's our plan
and the first step is reviewing this
algorithm here pseudocode means it's not
in any real language but if you know any
language you could probably turn it into
that real language it'll be kind of a
half way list pathway see kind of code
alright so here's the method the method
is I want to move all these four to here
then recursively I'm going to do a
problem on three Donuts okay this is my
leap of faith recur
I'm going to assume I could do the
problem on a smaller set so I asked my
recursive slave do me a favor take these
three and do the problem but don't move
them from here to here using the middle
use move them from here to the middle
using this as your auxiliary and there's
no problem doing this right because this
guy might as well be nailed to the
bottom we're not going to get any
illegal moves because we left this guy
in the bottom maybe I don't need to
mention that maybe that's obvious but
when I give you the problem set I'm
going to give you variations of how
fruity Freddy and ditzy dot C tried to
come up with variations of this puzzle
and they come up with phony-baloney
recursive algorithms that look right and
part of the reason they're wrong is
because subtle assumptions that I might
miss to mention now because they're
obvious don't apply to the ones that
they came up with so be careful it's a
little subtle why things always work so
this works because this doesn't affect
anything having this big guy in the
bottom and I can do this three problem
just like before but I'm going to end
them up here so I'll just reverse which
one I'm going to and which one I'm using
in my list of parameters you'll see this
on the board in a second
then I take a single move I move the big
guy over here where I want it to be and
then I again do a recursive problem on
these three moving them from the middle
peg to the two peg using the original
from peg and that solves the problem
three steps
two recursive calls one actual move and
the base case here is if you ever get
down to having no disks on a peg that I
don't do anything that's an easy base
case watch I'm going to do this one
recursively I take off the top and
only one in the bottom there's none on
the top so what do I do with none
recursive call don't do anything now I
do the middle step move this from here
to here okay then I take the empty pile
that I had moved here and I move it from
here to here now I'm done in other words
the base case really is an empty disk
you don't have to make the base case a
single dish you can make it an empty and
empty just no no doughnuts at all and
empty peg no doughnuts so I'm going to
write this algorithm up in the board now
and then we're going to analyze it a
little here's what it looks like I'll
call a toh four towers of Hanoi and
towers of Hanoi has how many parameters
the number of the doughnuts or disks and
not just the number of the pegs well
we're assuming there's three pegs in
this one right right where I'm moving
from and where I'm moving to and which
one is going to be my auxiliary one okay
so presumably these have real names you
know called a B and C and a might be the
original from peg B might be the
original auxiliary peg C might be the
original to peg but as I move around
from 2 and auxiliary are going to change
values changing from might end up being
see later on etc so that's why we need
these variables so here's what it looks
like towers of Hanoi we'll call it n
from 2 using those are the four
parameters this stores the name of a peg
this stores the name of the peg this
stores the name of a peg okay they're
variables that store the name of pegs a
B or C what should this procedure do
first of all it checks to see if n is
bigger than 0 if n is actually 0 it
doesn't do anything it only does steps
when n is bigger than 0 ok so 0 is the
base case and if it ever hits 0 it just
ends it just returns without anything
doing anything but if n is bigger than 0
it does something what's the first step
that it does takes these three and moves
them to to the peg that I called using
so toh n minus 1 from same from peg but
now the to peg becomes what I call
before the using peg and what I call
before the using peg now becomes the to
peg
let me stop other questions Theresa
to move this 63 but yeah somebody'd have
to move alright now I've done these
three and I moved them here the next
step is to move this guy from 2 2 so I'm
going to display this display move disc
from the front peg 2 to peg so if I put
little quotes around something I mean I
just want it to print those words move
the disc from here to here peg all right
so I'm going to move it from whatever
this is equal to to whatever this is
equal to a 2 B now well I if I did this
is just you can see what's going on
otherwise the algorithm will run well if
I did this with a let's try to answer
this question without getting too far
off track if I did toh here with with 1
from 2 using the first thing it would do
is it would get 2 here see that it's
bigger than 0 do this this would be
empty and then it would do this toh 1
again and it would just be in an
infinite loop if I call toh here would
be an infinite loop there would be no
place there would be no way for me to
actually see this disc move well this is
within toh anyways to display
that's true at some point you have to
say move something from somewhere to
somewhere but if you're still not quite
sure you should go ahead and actually
write that up in scheme and see what
happens you're going to hit return it'll
just go forever and we can we could
write it out and check out ourselves but
maybe that's not best to do
right now what's that right nobody would
know not to have to run your program all
right the lot the last step this is
already here we're going to take these
three and move them on top of here
so toh how many disks how many disks n
minus 1 we're removing them from
removing them from the using to the to
the - to the original - and we're going
to be using the original from peg close
the bracket so say that's where why is
this pseudocode its pseudocode cos if i
type this into any compiler in the world
except one that I wrote myself it
wouldn't compile right I mean in C you
need little semicolons here and you need
some declarations of variables and
scheme and you need more parentheses
it's just you get the idea it's a pseudo
code and you could turn this into schema
if you wanted to or into any language
for that matter that has recursion
built-in other questions about this yeah
from here to here and otherwise what
otherwise don't do anything all right so
let's actually run through this
algorithm at least for 3 disks how do I
move these two disks from here to here I
the top disk over to here this disk over
to here that's the middle step and this
one back on top
that's the third recursive call of the
first recursive call now I'm finally up
to the second step of my original
recursive call this goes here and now I
make a second recursive call for towers
of Hanoi - which says move this here
move this here and move this here and if
I was doing it with 4
my goal is to move these three to here
how do I move these three to here I've
got to move these two to here how do I
move these two to here I gotta move the
first one to here this one here these
two are here now the middle guy can come
here where I want it to be now these two
have to move back on here now I can
finally do my middle move take this red
and put it here now I got to take all
these three and put them back on this
side in order to do that I got to get
these two over to here so how do I do
that
here here here this one goes back here
and then here here here
which one's black all right so let's
let's roll this out of the way you
should play with that toy for a little
while make sure you can do that yourself
I mean once you get it for four I think
you can pretty much get it you won't
lose track of where you are but 64 I
don't think you need to do that we'll
take you to many years
let's analyze how long this algorithm
takes and then see where we head from
there T of n is how long this algorithm
takes what does it consist of it
consists of three steps the first step
is a recursive call on n minus one so
that's how much time does that take TN
minus one I don't know how much time it
takes but I know what's called TN minus
1 and this takes one step and then I got
another TN minus 1 so I get 2 TN minus 1
s plus 1 and when n is equal to 0 how
many steps is this take zero
that's my recurrence equation for the
time complexity of towers of Hanoi what
I need to do now is just figure out what
this is so a lot of you know that this
is going to end up being 2 to the N
minus 1 we're going to calculate this
exactly the order some people do yeah
why would you because you're doubling
the time complexity every time you take
away one so if you double something
every time you take away one then by the
time you get down to zero
you've doubled it n times and that's 2
to the N so it's true and you should
develop intuition like that it's worth
having instead of having everything
being a mystery until you get to the end
you should know what you're kind of
expecting here in general in a
recurrence equation if this number is
going down by 1 and there's some
multiplicative factor here your solution
is going to be exponential if this gets
cut in half or gets cut down by some
multiplicative factor 1/2 or 1/3 or 1/4
then well if there's nothing here then
it's going to be logarithmic but what if
it's 2t n over 2 there's all sorts of
variations on this some of these
recurrence equations come up so
frequently in algorithms that there's
kind of a master theorem that lets you
deal with many of them all at once but
that Nasr theorem comes precisely the
proof of it comes from doing these
substitutions and getting general
summations and analyzing what the order
of complexity is of those summations and
we'll get to that in a couple of days
there are other recurrence equations
that are more mathematical that don't
come up as often in algorithms but we're
going to study how to solve some of
those basic ones as well but first let's
do this just with the repeated
substitution Theresa yes the first step
is the same code again but just on a
size of disks that's one less so if this
takes if we say this takes T n time then
this is going to take T n minus one time
because it's the same problem so that's
T n minus 1 and this takes one step
that's this one and this take the
display because all you're doing is
printing it out you do one thing
that's almost seems like an extraneous
yep well you're moving the disk yeah
well I mean if you don't have this in
the code then you never actually see
what's happening this is equivalent to
me picking up a disk and moving it over
here this is the only place we ever say
what happens this is the only place we
ever report what's going on if you look
at the program is not just telling you
how to do it but actually doing it then
that's the only place where it is
actually good this is the only place we
just actually get moved right right you
can make this a procedure called move
desk this is the only place we actually
say let's move a desk these are our
recursive calls which eventually we'll
get to calling this one line and now
this thing down here is another
recursive call it's actually a procedure
that runs again and the parameter is n
minus 1 so again it takes TN minus 1
time so that's where you get to TN minus
1 okay you're counting the display as
one yeah well what are you going also
count the bottom of this with the can
will go through is 1 that is the bottom
desk if you program the robot that would
be programmed robot that would be the
command that can create the robot the
result of this is going to be a list of
instructions for how you write the
result is a list of instructions here
I'll call it robot moved right this this
does the recursion for the first top n
minus 1 this moves the bottom one this
does the recursion for the top n minus 1
again so this does move the bottom one
and in fact the moves the bottom one in
every single pile even piles of one this
moves the bottom one which is that
particular disk that's why we can't call
towers of Hanoi again for a disk of one
because then we don't end up moving any
disk ok other questions let's let's run
through this step-by-step this is going
to come up with a result which gives us
a summation instead of just one number
in the repeated substitution so let's go
through it again as before we start with
this and we want to get rid of this so
we write down TN
is 1 equals 2 TN minus 2 plus 1 and
we're going to take our value for TN
minus 1 and put it back in here and this
time we'll be a little more careful
because you can make a mistake if you're
not careful
2 times 2 TN minus 2 plus 1 plus 1 I
and I did it slowly because some people
not Sam will not see exactly what this
works out to be in advance so we'll get
it slowly now see what it turns out to
be to square TN minus 2 plus I plus 2
plus 1 I'm going to write it out leaving
the summation there don't simplify
because if you simplify it you will lose
the pattern try to leave the pattern
let's do this a whole bunch more times
I'm going to erase the algorithm
everybody have this if you don't have it
you can find it in every single
programming book ever written in the
last 30 years just look up towers of
Hanoi in the back you can look at it in
Java and C++ and scheme and Visual Basic
and write anything you ever wanted
more time can you see a pattern what's
happening this bumps up by 1 right so
you'll get 2 cubed T and minus 3 and
look at this what would happen here on
the next time the next time through this
stuff gets multiplied by 2 so you get 2
4 and then 1 gets added at the end so
you get 4 plus 2 plus 1 so now what
happens when I do it a lot more times
when I do it r times after r times this
number becomes 2 to the r this becomes T
n minus R and this what's the biggest
term here it's not 2 to the our right to
the R would be 8 the biggest term the
term is one less so you get to to the R
minus one plus two to the R minus two
plus dot dot dot all the way down to
four to one that's the typical kind of
thing you get when you do recurrence
substitutions you don't just get a nice
sum you got sometimes these dot dot dot
things and you've got to figure out how
to add them together and now we're going
to talk a little bit about how to do
this what geometric series are
variations of geometric series and
things that come up frequently in
recurrence equations and explain for you
how to solve them I'm going to teach you
one trick in doing this a trick that
will work in the vast majority of
situations that come up and in order to
memorize anything and I really urge you
not to memorize anything because you're
more likely to just waste the brain cell
memorizing be too busy to think about
what's going on and then apply it wrong
if you just think about the idea here
you'll never go wrong in solving one of
these geometric sums and I'll show you
what I mean all right we need to figure
out a way to get rid of this capital T
so we're left with just the sum and then
we'll solve that sum so how do we get
rid of this capital T here here it's
straightforward
what should the R be our needs to be M
because we know T 0 equals 0 so if R
equals n let R equal n we're going to
get T and equals 2 to the N times 0 plus
I'm going to reverse this now 1 plus 2
plus 4 all the way up to 2 to the R
minus 1 that's 0 to the N minus 1 things
towers of Hanoi takes we want to put
this in a closed form in an easier way
to understand and perhaps calculate and
we're going to do that right now
other questions so far John okay
this step comes from here we're looking
at this general formula that we got
after doing this r times and we want to
make sure that this capital T disappears
so how many times should we do it we
should do it as many times as it takes
this to turn into a zero this turns into
a 0 when R becomes n then you get TN
minus n so every place you see an R you
put an N 1 2 4 8 2 to the N minus 2 all
the way up to 2 to the N minus 1 that's
where this thing comes from and when
this becomes 0 T sub 0 that doesn't take
any steps that becomes 0 so we get 0
times 2 to the N which just crosses out
okay yeah Teresa because we can't get an
answer when the T's on the right side
steps does it take here there's 36 discs
on the on the thing how many steps does
it take how are you going to tell them
an answer right right we just we want to
be able to answer the question how many
steps does this take for a particular n
and if this is here it depends on how
many steps it takes for some other
example so if we really want to give
them an answer we want to basically
unwind the recursion until it's all gone
down to the base case and there's no
more recursive calls and this keeps
track of what happens during that
sequence of recursive calls yeah it
represents the it represents the
subsequent recursive calls that get done
later and sooner or later all those
recursive calls will end and this keeps
track of how much work goes on until
they end so if you do that yep
recursive calls and how much work gets
done by each one of them because each
recursive call besides generating new
recursive calls does some work as well
it does that display and then it has two
other recursive calls that's where these
doublings started showing up so yeah we
are doing it other questions
all right so here we're up to here and
now I want to tell you in general how do
you get rid of sums like this and and
there's a trick that's going to work for
this some and then I'll do a more
complicated sum after we solve this one
but here's the trick of how to solve
sums like this you just give it a name
call it X oh and you're all done no give
it a name and it's happy give it a name
and our idea is we'd like to get rid of
the dot dot dot
so here is something that happens in
geometric series what's a geometric
series first of all a geometric series
is a series that each successive term is
multiplied by a particular number so one
two four eight what's the particular
that it's being multiplied by by two
each time it's going up by a particular
factor an arithmetic series doesn't get
multiplied each subsequent factor it
gets added you know so like one plus two
plus three plus four that's an
arithmetic series one plus three plus
five plus seven that's an arithmetic
series we talked about those already a
lot of them now you're talking about
geometric series Euclid new lattice
Summit geometric series 2,000 years ago
so we should be able to do it now yeah
no let's go all right how does this work
here's the trick if you multiply the
geometric series by that multiplicative
factor it just takes the whole geometric
series and kind of shifts it over to the
right one you did this in streams when
you talked about it in scheme two times
one is two two times two is four
the N minus 1 and 2 times 2 to the N
minus 1 is 2 to the N it just shifted
everything over 1 and now if you
subtract the top from the bottom 2x
minus X is X and this - this is all
cancel out by by 2 to the N minus 1 and
that's the answer and you should
remember in general when you're adding
up powers of things and you add up every
single power up to some length then you
just about get to the next power missing
it by 1 if you add up powers of things 1
2 4 8 all the way up to say 2 to the 3rd
or 2 to the 8th then if you add all
those things up it's just 2 to the 9th -
1 you're almost there
ok that should remind you of something
does remind anybody of anything so what
I'm thinking of I'm thinking of
integration this is like a sum of things
right if you're adding up the sum of
things all the way up to 2 2 to the I it
doesn't matter all right so here's how
you do a geometric series
if this multiplicative factor was a 3
then you'd be multiplying by 3 if the
multiplicative factor was 1/2 then you'd
be multiplying by 1/2 all right so a
quick another example
Zeno's paradox I did this before with
you a couple months ago but we'll do
xenos cake paradox today you're sitting
at a dinner somebody has a big piece of
cake
they cut it in half they give you a
slice you're a very polite person so you
look around the table and you see
somebody else doesn't have a slice and
you say oh would you like to share my
slice so you cut your slice in half and
you give them a slice and then you keep
doing this and you keep doing this and
somebody says whoa well we can just feed
like a multitude it's a religious
parable right we just keep slicing the
cake in half another slice of cake Xena
oh well what happens if you keep slicing
the cake in half what happens when you
keep slicing the cake in half is that
you actually get just one piece of cake
when you're all done X is the piece of
cake the multiplicative factor here is
is what 1/2 so multiply this by 1/2 and
you get 1/4 plus 1/8 and the nice thing
about infinity is that you don't even
have this extra term at the end that you
have to worry about because everything
just matches up at the end it goes
forever so when you subtract X minus 1/2
and X you get 1/2 an X and what does
that equal equals 1/2 so x equals 1 just
one piece of cake all right there's an
example let me show you an example of a
fancier geometric series that isn't
really a geometric series it just looks
a little like 1 and show you how to do
that and show you how to do a gazillion
things like it using the same trick just
remember this trick you never have to
memorize any formulas questions
questions and let's do this underneath
it
there were just ones up here this would
be a geometric series but there's not
there's this increasing arithmetic
series that kind of up on top and the
numerators and just the power geometric
series on the bottom but put together
it's not any series that you're used to
and here we normally we get a problem
let's review how to do it here in the
easy case who can do this at their seat
and tell me what you get for X I guess
the right answer would be one of you to
yell out very quickly Sam I said who
could I didn't actually ask for the sum
it is 1/9 and it also equals Oh point 1
1 1 1 1 1 no forever right point 1.000
1.000 one sets a 9th and you can do it
just the same way we did I won't do it
again but the multiplicative factor is
1/10 you know you divide by 1/10 you
subtract do it at your seat make sure
you can do it when you get to something
like this your gut instinct is why I
have no idea how to do it so I'll go ask
I or the TA or something or you can say
well I have no idea how to do it but I
have one tool in my bag of tricks that
worked on something similar so I'll try
to fit it on this and if I break the
tool then I'll give up or if I get
something that looks terrible I'll give
up but if I get something that's good
then I'll know that tool is kind of a
little more versatile than I originally
thought if your only tool was a hammer
the whole world of like nails there you
go right right
and if the whole world looks like nails
then you need a vacation
all right let's let's do this same trick
as before a tenth acts not because we
know it will work but because we're just
going to try it and see if it works what
happens when you multiply this by 1/10
this piece becomes 1 over 10 squared and
this piece becomes 2 over 10 cubed and
this piece becomes 3 over 10 to the
fourth
etc and now let's do the same trick we
did before we'll subtract this from this
X minus 1/10 of X is nine-tenths of X
is is 1/10 2 over 10 squared minus 1
over 10 squared is 1 over 10 squared
what happens here good 1 over 10 cubed
and the whole way down since we shifted
it over nothing canceled like before but
things got simpler than they were we
used to have an arithmetic sequence here
after we do the subtraction this
arithmetic sequence has simplified down
to a constant sequence of 1 what is that
equal who knows what that equals 9/10 x
equals 1/9 so x equals 10 over 81 this
equals 10 over 81 okay that trick works
a lot it's an easy trick to remember it
works for geometric series you can
derive a general formula for geometric
series with this trick it works for
series where the top goes up by an
arithmetic amount what if the top went
up by a squares what if I had 1 4 9 16
up on top what do you think would happen
the first time you do it it reduces to a
linear sequence the next time you do it
it reduces to a constant sequence the
next time you do it you get an answer
what does that remind you of reminds you
of derivatives of polynomials cubes turn
into squares squares turn into linear
terms linear terms turn into constants
constants turn into simplicity all right
and it's not an accident what you're
really doing here is virtually taking a
derivative you're really putting in a
particular value here for X you put in
another value for X here you subtract
the 2 you divide by the difference
between them it really is a derivative
if you think about it and then sometimes
it's called a finite difference it's a
discrete version of a derivative so it's
not an accident
not just some hocus-pocus weird isn't
that cool it's there's no there's no
magic about it if you actually analyze
it you'll see why it really is like a
derivative it's taking the differences
between successive terms in a sequence
and that's what derivatives really are
the rate of change of a sequence so
squares change at the rate of linear
time linear sequences change at a
constant rate all right so now you can
solve any kind of series like this where
the top is any kind of simple polynomial
and the bottom is just exponents you
just have to use this trick and over and
over and over again any questions about
this all right so that's towers of Hanoi
example this is geometric series and
variations of them now ready to start on
a problem which is which is a lot harder
than towers of Hanoi but before I do it
I want to give you the bird's eye view
of towers of Hanoi I want to take you
out of the jungle of the computation and
out of the summations here and let's you
see a picture for people who are
particularly visual minded this will be
like an epiphany for towers of Hanoi and
even those of you who feel you
completely understand towers of Hanoi I
think this will still be somewhat of an
epiphany it makes you feel like oh now I
can see what's going on completely all
right so here's how I'm going to
represent the towers of Hanoi I got
three pegs
three and if I place a doughnut on a
particular peg then I'll write one if
that doughnuts on peg one and two of the
donuts on peg two and three of the
doughnuts on peg three so here's an
example of the towers of Hanoi problem
with one doughnut there are three
possible configurations in this problem
the doughnuts here on peg 1 the
doughnuts here on peg 2 or the doughnuts
here on peg 3 everyone agree let's make
a picture a graph picture every one of
these configurations every one of these
rows now has a node in my picture of
vertex in my picture I'm going to label
this one one I'll label this one too and
I'll label this one three
I made a triangle here for a very
particular reason you can make a move
from one to two you can pick this disc
up and move it from here to here if you
can do that then I connect two vertices
in my picture two vertices are connected
two configurations in the game are
connected if you can move in one step
from one to the other
I can move from two to three and I can
move from three to one I can move from
anyone to any of the others this is such
a simple case it doesn't seem like it's
giving you much at all but the very next
case for two discs is going to give you
a lot more and will give you a real nice
sense and I'm going to go up to three
today and then I'm going to run out of
blackboard but you'll see a lot when we
get to three so let's write down all the
possible situations for having two
doughnuts on our three pegs see how many
there are
see if we can make a picture and see if
the picture gives us any perspective
together anybody know how many two disc
configurations let's write them out
and just move this one over so I've got
three with a bottom one on peg one
agreed I'm going to get another three
with the bottom one in the middle and
I'm getting another three with the
bottom one at the end three three three
that makes nine right when we get to
counting in another week this will be an
easy problem you'll glance at you'll
think about it and you'll blurt out nine
just like Sam did okay but right now it
may be take a little bit of thinking and
I don't want to get into the counting
part of it yet I want you to just
realize that there's nine and I want you
to realize the following thing that we
started with three now we're up to nine
and we're going to create this new graph
the same way we created the old graph
but instead of flailing around and just
making nine vertices and connecting them
where we might not see the pretty
picture and unravel it well I'm going to
specifically make a very particular
picture here to save you the the
horrible dead end effort of discovering
this pretty graph for yourself so here's
how what it's going to look like when
we're done graphing it
the right end which three configurations
to these three nodes correspond to what
do you think these three here what do
they mean what do these numbers mean now
I put two numbers down because now every
node represents a configuration and
every configuration has two doughnuts in
it so I need two numbers to represent
what it looks like instead of one number
this number represents the bigger one
smaller disk so this means that this
configuration means that the bigger one
and the smaller one are both on peg
number one that's this guy okay this
means that the bigger ones on one with
the smaller ones on to the bigger ones
on one but the smaller ones on three why
is it have the same structure as the
original because the bigger one is
staying on the same peg if the bigger
one stays on the same peg then it's just
as if it wasn't there at all
erase the big one one two three the same
configurations we had before so it's the
same triangle by the same notion if I
move the bigger one to the middle I'd
also have a triangle of configurations
as long as I keep the big one
second square I can move from 1 to 2 2 2
2 3 2 because the big one stays where it
is think about this a lot there's going
to be a problem set on this you're
really going to have to understand how
this works so so get the basics down
before you have to really do the hard
stuff I don't understand why you label
the verses where they have 1 2 at the
top oh why did I rotate these Dawei it
matters a lot and I'm pretending like I
did it randomly and I did it very
purposely like this I'm sorry that's
like it's like right it's like a date
you're about to break up with somebody
they go is there some reason why you
canceled our date for three weeks then I
go no that was just complete coincidence
none I'm fooling you here but I'm making
this seem like it's obvious and it's not
what you really end up doing Gary and
I'll tell you the secret now it's that
you put this up here and when you add
the two to the same picture to make
another triangle you rotate it once so
that the two two is over here in the
corner and you'll see why in a second so
we're going to do the same thing here
let's put the big one on the third disc
it's a graph it's a graph of how you
move from one configuration and the
towers of Hanoi problem to another this
graph is going to be the two disk towers
of Hanoi problem and if you want to
watch a set of movements it ends up
being a path on this graph okay I can go
from here to here right by moving the
top over here
what edge does that correspond to my
graph moving from here to here sorry
moving from here to here 1 1 2 2 1 any
movement in my graph corresponds to an
actual change of the configuration and
the towers of Hanoi by one move that's a
good question if you weren't sure the
answer to that question now that's a
super question that's really what we're
doing and I'm going to explain it more
but let me finish the picture for this
graph so you can see all the edges so
let's put the
big disk on the third one the big
distance on the third one all these
things start with three here and the
smaller disk can either be on the first
the second of the third and these
connect just like they did before
because the big ones on the third one
and that doesn't affect anything about
the top this the top this can still move
from 1 to 2 2 to 3 and 3 to 1 the
question is how do we reconnect now that
we've increased to another disk and
we've made 3 copies of what we had
before adding the bigger disk on the
bottom
first peg adding the bigger disc on the
bottom second peg adding the bigger disk
on the bottom third peg how do these
things connect to each other which
configurations can move to which the
configurations between the edges between
these two correspond to when you're
actually moving the bigger one 1 can you
move the bigger one let's do a
possibility we can move it from here
right if this is the smaller one and
this is the bigger one we can do this
move this is the number that we write
from right to left as 1 3 this is the
number we write from right to left as 2
undefined
so between 1/3 and 2/3 there should be
an edge this edge corresponds to moving
the bottom disc to moving the bigger
disk see how the big disk changes and
the small disk is different notice the
small disk had better not be on either 1
or 2 otherwise you couldn't move the big
disk right the small disk is away on 3
and we can change the big disk from 1 to
2 here the small disk is away on 2 and
we're changing the big disk from 1 to 3
here the small disk is away on 1 and
we're changing the big disk from 2 to 3
that's the whole graph a sequence of
movements when I sit there with that
table and I move doughnuts around every
time I move a doughnut around somebody
and
would be really cool if I actually wrote
a little Java applet to do this but I
haven't done it yet I could have
somebody with a little robot move Donuts
around and as they move you'd see a
little red light moving from one place
to another on this graph so that's
somebody playing with a picture of the
game would be able to see directly
what's half it correspond to on my graph
that's what this graph represents every
node represents a position in the game
every edge represents a one step
movement from one position to another
questions yes yes yes I'm going to get
into that in a second yeah John okay let
me make that one-to-one correspondence
completely clear I'm just I'm just the
bigger ones are on the right and that's
all I mean you have to decide what
direction you want to go here and and I
decide I go from left to right goes from
smaller to bigger right to left goes
from bigger to smaller but this number
represents what peg the biggest disk is
on and this represents what peg the
smaller ones okay you got it oh yeah no
I just picked it in fact you can see a
good picture of these things in a book
that I brought in today by Ian Stewart
that's the guy who who gave the talk
about the minesweeper game he writes
lots of popular math books and in one
book that I brought and he's got a
chapter on towers of Hanoi and he's got
a picture of this graph and I think
actually he might actually have the
opposite convention so looking at his
book might confuse you but but but it is
arbitrary right
at the solution two towers of Hanoi I
the solution it's a two-disc it's not
going to kill us right what's the next
step I mean right here on the this
picture small disc here big disc here
and finally we're all done now let's
follow this on the graph this is the
position that we call here peg one peg
to peg three this is position one one
what's this position where's the bigger
one the bigger one is on one the smaller
ones on two okay we go from here to here
this is actually moving that larger one
right the bottom one moving the bottom
one means moving the biggest one the
rightmost one changing the rightmost one
is done here and finally that's the last
one being three three if somebody showed
you this graph and said you started a
corner how do you get to another corner
would you sit there and scratch your
head for five minutes trying to figure
it out would you say oh this is a deep
problem I don't really see how to do it
teach me about recursion so I can
understand the idea you wouldn't you'd
say let me give it to my two-year-old
right boom it's so obvious what the
fastest path is to get from one corner
to another you just have to stare at it
the graph lets you build in on every
natural human advantage you have all
right you don't have to build a robot to
notice that that's the fastest path a
robot might not be good at it but you
can see it in a flash and that's why
graphs are powerful if I asked you to
move it to the second peg
also see it's just a straight line any
detour is going to take you longer
you'll also notice this what if I asked
you from any point in towers of Hanoi
except the starting and finishing points
how many choices do you have three right
the starting points you have two but all
the others you have three and actually
isn't so easy to figure out the possible
cases but if you stare at the graph it's
automatic there's three cases that you
can move to no matter what
sometimes it's twice for the top one
sometimes it's none for the top one but
there's always three except one they're
all in one Peck right right but this
just gets it all at once boom three
three choices
there's never none for the trouble no I
meant the bottom I'm sorry what the
bottom one sometimes is known for the
top one can always move absolutely right
rods asking a great question right are
we just getting lucky for the second
stage or is this just kind of like like
build up like a snowflake sierpinski's
triangle it looks just like sierpinski
I'm not kidding it really does now we
can spend an hour talking about
sierpinski's triangle I once had a
student that did a research project that
had nothing to do with this and it's
something to do with with some matrix
manipulation and in the middle there he
started printing out zeros and ones and
then he writes some comments and
something that I was supposed to edit
and he goes this is just like
sierpinski's triangle and at that point
I never heard of sierpinski's triangle
so I said well what does sierpinski's
triangle and then I found out that he
had no idea either that he just kind of
saw a picture somewhere so I ended up
having to look it up and figure out what
it is and it's got connections to a lot
of things and it has a connection to
this but but let's not go there let's
let's look at the case for three just as
the case for two is built out of three
cases for one with single edges
connecting the bottom moves the case for
three is built out of three
copies of the case for two with bottom
edges connecting those three copies
basically if you have two disks it moves
around like this this is the structure
for two disks if I add a big disk on the
bottom the structure remains I just have
to figure out how those three different
copies where the bottom ones on peg one
and the bottom ones on peg two and the
bottom ones on peg three how those three
copies of two disk problem connect
together and what's neat is that they
connect together in a way that should
remind you of the recursion here is the
recursive part here's the display here's
the recursive part here's the recursive
part here's the display here's the
recursive part the display part is a
part that moves the bottom one from here
to here is the recursive part now let me
show you in a bigger picture so the
recursive part is more than just one
move because that's what it's typically
going to be so here are going to have to
really draw carefully we're going to
need three copies of that there's one
let's label them to make sure we can all
do this the top copy is going to be this
one okay it's going to be one one ah
I'll add the yes I'll have the third
number in a second - I just want to show
you that it's that it's this copy the
two discs one and then when you're all
ready to believe that I'll throw the
bigger disc on the bottom of the first
peg because the top to still move in
this relation so 2 1 3 1 help me out 2 3
3 2 okay and just like I said this is
going to represent the case where we
take the new disc and we throw it on peg
1 which means it's on the bottom of peg
1 the other 2 discs move in this notion
just like they did before but at the
right end where we put the biggest one
it sits on peg 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1
we have to figure out what this guy is
remember this represents a movement of
the biggest disk so where do the small
disks have to be here if the biggest
disk is moving they have to stay where
they are I'll go for three good it's the
only possibility the big disk is on one
any movements that aren't the big disk
are taken care of in these pictures that
I've already drawn the only movements
that aren't taken care of are the
movements between configurations where
the big disk moves because the big dust
stays the same in all these
configurations that's why it's the same
structure as before so this three is
going to stay three here for all these
values let's label them notice you have
to take this and wrote watch it rotate
it up so what do we get two two three
I wrote it down so I can do this without
messing up but I like you to yell it out
so you can think with me three two three
everybody see what I'm doing two two
three three two three going up this way
is going down this way okay what's this
one three one three good and this 1 1 3
3 3 3 3 2 3 3 2 1 3 and 1 1 3 4 3 3 3
really right
which way to label these but if I just
follow the orientation and stay
consistent and make sure I have three
three three in the corner everything
works out okay here I'm going to have to
have two two two in the corner so let's
label all these here I want to move this
one from 1 1 3 2 1 1 2 and this 1 3 3 1
2 3 3 2 and then I can fill in the rest
1 3 2 2 3 2 1 2 2 & 2 1 2 3 2 2 and 3 1
2 at Chicago that's a New York City
that's Connecticut now they have area
codes I used to give a problem in in
finite state machines you know to come
up with a finite state machine that does
area codes because area codes used to be
normal right these that like like a
digit is 0 or 1 and then another digit
but now you can have any area code in
the whole world so I have to when you
get old enough you've got to change your
problem sets because the examples you
use like change like like imagine you're
using a phone how long would it take you
how long would it how many what if
you're dialing the number 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
8 9 how many inches does your finger
move right that's a great problem for
triangle numbers okay but only before
1971 or something right if you did the
problem now how long does it take I
don't get it yeah it's got the linear
right let's connect these whew this is
tough 1 2 3 so the answer to Rob's
question is yes yes and yes it's exactly
the same structure to go to 4 you'd have
three of these and connect them again
with three new edges there are so many
things you can learn from this picture I
just showed you a couple I showed you
how you can see the obvious shortest
path and actually figure out what the
moves are I showed you how this
represents the recursion from here to
here is the recursive call
that's the display from here to here is
the recursive call here's a sub
recursive call the recurse
call here has three parts recursive call
recursive call display recursive call
recursive call display it all just shows
up like a picture it's a great picture I
love this picture um the number of steps
to get from her mother is 2 to the N
minus 1 right so just declare by the way
that it's rotated is it kind of like if
we were to take the corner that connects
and swing it around so that it drops for
that right exactly and then swing this
around the other way and then connect
them all up right again right in fact
somebody is really good at doing little
Java applets and as a good visual sense
I'm sure can make a beautiful little
video of this just showing how these
things you know rotate around and
connect together and then the next one
grows it would just grow in front of
your eyes just the kind of thing I wish
I could do well but usually I don't do
it so well you can see how ugly my
picture is here but the idea is really
beautiful regardless of the picture this
is black this is white this is black
this is white if I alternate the colors
black and white on these disks and if I
add the constraint don't ever put black
on black or white on white you know make
sure that they stay alternating if I add
that constraint to the normal towers of
Hanoi constraint then the choice at
every point is no longer three choices
it's only two choices and going from one
state to another state is simply a
matter of making sure you don't go
backwards the problem solves itself you
can write an iterative algorithm to
solve it just say move don't make the
last move you made and follow the rules
right no same thing different sight this
same as before let's do an example this
it's going to be the same solution yeah
it's the exact same thing
what we'll do this is so easy
well yell on red can't go on green and
orange cheese try to I'm going to mess
up let's do it with three green can't go
on orange okay I want to move it from
here to say here all right green can't
go in orange green can't go in orange
green can't go in orange green can't go
in orange green can't go in orange we
can't go on our knowledge you don't have
to do anything actually there's a little
detail to this the first choice you make
actually could be wrong and if you make
the first choice wrong and you go in
that in that direction you'll end up
going around this way instead of that
way that's the only thing you can do
wrong at the corner if you make the
wrong choice because at the corner you
have a choice right you can make the
wrong choice there and go around this
way instead of this way right but if you
don't care which peg it goes on - this
is completely foolproof
just follow the rule no bigger ones on
small ones no black on black no white on
white all right so when you first tell
people this and they know the recursive
solution you say well I'll try to figure
out why the recursive solution is the
same as this and it's it's not easy to
see why these two are the same but you
have a fighting chance with this graph
right one of the problems on the pset is
to try to explain why those two are the
same why it's true that if you go from
here to here in the recursive solution
which is the same as saying if you go
from here to here on this graph why do
you never ever put a disk on an even
spot on top of a disk on an even spot
and a disk got an odd spot on top of a
disk in a knots but why do you keep that
black white alternation steady and the
way to prove it as you might guess is by
induction because you assume you never
do it
for these smaller triangles and all you
really have to concentrate on are these
connecting pieces with all this hint in
place this is not an easy problem I gave
you a lot of hints and the problem set
to help you try to do it but if you can
really do this problem then you've used
mathematical induction for a purpose
which is not just an illustration of the
technique but which you really really
have a hard time proving this straight
up and with induction you have a chance
and with this graph you have a chance
this graph is inductively defined and
the proof is built up out of pieces of
the scrap there's a lot of other things
you can get from this graph but I think
I've kind of shot my load here trying to
you know build up how cool graphs are
but here's a great example of it alright
other questions about this alright
here's what we're doing next time next
time switching over to that other puzzle
to that six rings puzzle or seven rings
puzzle that puzzle is also a puzzle that
can be solved with recursion I want to
give you since you have a day now to go
back and look at it if you haven't
solved it yet I want to give you some
hints that will give you a sense of what
that puzzles like before I will show you
tomorrow what's going to happen tomorrow
we're going to go through and analyze
that puzzle just like we did towers of
Hanoi I'm going to connect it to a bunch
of surprising things you should know
that in the store you can buy puzzles
that are equivalent to that puzzle I
gave you there's a little puzzle called
spin out that you can buy in any toy
store with a little track and little
things that turn right and left and you
have to pull out the track that's
equivalent to the six ring problem
there's a couple of other problems
equivalent to it here's something you
should know about this puzzle and it's a
little frustrating to know especially
I've been working on the puzzle for
eight hours and haven't discovered this
yourself you see how in the towers of
Hanoi you have a choice you go down here
and now you've got two other choices
where to continue backwards and to new
forward choices and this six rings
puzzle it's not that complicated
if you go forward to a particular
position in the six rings puzzle do you
have many choices you have you can go
backward or you can go forward that's it
so if I showed you the graph of the six
ring puzzle what would it look like
where's my eraser go yeah whoa out of
control
hold on put my pocket the graph of the
six ring puzzle looks like this if these
are six rings all on and these are six
rings all off say I made a vertex for
each picture you know when a ring is on
and when a ring is off and this is node
1 this is no 2 dot dot dot dot dot it's
one line it's a long line it's
completely trivial from the point of
view of this graph to solve this puzzle
either you're going forward or you're
going backward all you got to make sure
is that you don't turn around if I put
it out like this and I said go from here
to here a nine-month-old can do it if we
put peanut butter here and a
nine-month-old can do it a rat can do it
the thing about that puzzle is it's so
convoluted in all the Rings clanking and
clunking and trying to squeeze this up
is you don't even notice when you've
been to a position before you think you
make it progress it would be the
funniest thing to watch somebody fiddle
with this the first hour and watch a
little picture on a screen of what
positions they were up to this is what
they would end up doing I'm getting
somewhere now oh yeah oh yeah it's it's
comical I mean I did it myself it's
comical it took me three hours before I
realize this and then I smack myself in
the head and said oh there's only one
direction to go here but you have to
come up with an idea of taking these big
ugly mechanical things and associating a
vertex with each one and noticing what
position you're in when you get a big
mess of metal in your fingers and when
you get to that point then you can tell
whether you're going forward and
backward now that's just the beginning
of this puzzle it turns out that the way
we're going to identify positions is
going to be with binary numbers so if a
ring is on it'll be a 1 in that position
and if a ring is off it'll be a 0 in
that position so we'll have binary
numbers
of length six there's 64 though so
there's 64 positions in this game we're
going to go from one to another we're
also going to calculate how many steps
it takes us to go from one to another
the sequence of binary numbers that
start showing up turns out to be the
same as a completely separate sequence
that comes up in computer science called
gray codes and gray codes were
originally created not for this purpose
at all but for the purpose of when you
have a little spinner around and you'll
want to see what the spin was if you're
on the line you don't want the binary
sensors to be too far off more than one
or another I'll show you where gray code
come from but they don't come from here
at all they don't come from this puzzle
nevertheless this puzzled generates gray
codes right and none of this has to do
with recursion yet the most beautiful
part of this puzzle is that there's a
recursive solution to this puzzle that
happens to generate gray codes on its
way down and in the recursive solution
to this puzzle calculating the
recurrence equation gives you something
like this remember towers of Hanoi was
2n to TN minus 1 plus 1 so now we got to
TN minus 2 plus TN minus 1 plus 1 if it
was just 2 TN minus 2 we could probably
do what we did before that same
substitution idea we're going to do
substitution on this tomorrow for about
five minutes until we get sick to our
stomach of the ugly son that starts
showing up you get a horrible ugly son
when this shows up we're going to have
to give up on that naive substitution
idea and we're going to give up on a big
time and tomorrow for for the one time
in the class I am actually going to not
just show you the end of it we're going
to go down a plan dead end alley trying
this and back up and we're going to
pretend we're mathematicians instead of
just some mathematician telling you
about stuff we're going to try to solve
it we're just making a table we're going
to pretend we're clueless and we're
going to make a table and everybody in
the class
pretend we're clueless we're going to
make a table of how many steps this
takes we're actually build it up from
the base case op and we're going to look
for patterns in that table just like
somebody would who didn't know the
answer to this the beginning now we're
going to notice patterns in this table
they're not going to be that hard to
notice and we're going to say oh gee I
wonder why I didn't see it looking at
this well because you don't do this all
day long the whole your whole life and
you don't notice patterns when you see
it like that when you see numbers
standing in front of you start to notice
patterns and we're going to conjecture
some things about those patterns and the
things we're going to conjecture we're
going to be able to write out theorems
about we're going to be able to say
there's a really simple recurrence
equation for the even cases and a really
simple recurrence equation for the odd
cases and they don't give us these
horrible substitutions but how are we
going to know if those things are true
we just guess them because it looked
like it we're going to prove them by
induction which turns out to be a three
line proof we never would have
discovered the theorem without writing
down some data we never be able to prove
it from scratch but we'll look at the
data discover these theorems prove it by
induction work them back to get actual
answers for the even and odd case which
will solve this general case that we
otherwise would have been stumped by so
it connects the recurrence equations
it's connects to induction it connects
to really why you want to use induction
because it helps you really prove things
that you don't really see the big
picture on prove things that you only
understand what happens from one case to
the next and it's going to connect to
this nice iterative generation of gray
codes and that connects to Hamiltonian
circuits and hypercubes
so I really love this problem I think
this problem just knits everything
together sums
graphs recurrence equations induction
and recursion all right that's where
we're headed tomorrow so solve this
puzzle if you solve it than what I do