all right so new topic we're going to
talk about counting we're going to talk
about counting for the next whole week
and then the last week we're going to
switch over to number theory and things
that relate eventually toward public key
cryptography to the way you send credit
cards over the web and and not lose your
shirt but this week is all counting
quarter of a semesters worth I need to
tell you right up front and this is true
of every single topic in this course you
can take a whole course just in logic
you can take a whole course just in
circuit design that relates to boolean
algebra you can take a whole course in
combinatorics you can take another
course in it and then you can take a
graduate course in it right
combinatorics is counting we're doing a
quarter of a semester in it so you're
going to get the tools of combinatorics
you're going to get the rudiments some
of it will sink in right away some of
it'll take some time to sink in but this
is the beginning of a long long branch
that you could follow much much more
more deeply but you will get all the
basics that you'll ever need to do 98%
of the things that come up in computer
science all right so that's that's our
goal and I want to organize this
discussion about counting in the
following way I want to give you what I
think in my experience is the general
bag of tricks that that I've discovered
over the years that come up a lot
alright in this bag of tricks are
conceptual things ways of thinking about
problems and in addition kind of the
ABCs kind of like the basic ok I can do
that problem because it's a basic
problem you know so so there's
conceptual ways of going about solving
and then just basic tools and the
combination of those will help you solve
almost every problem that you'll see at
this level so what are these what are
these general principles so what is this
principle called a multiplication
principle I'm using this name because
the book uses this name rather than
define anything you can go look at your
book if you want
look at definitions or formal ways of
doing things I'm going to go through
this introduction to counting mostly
through examples and then you'll learn
the principle by the example then you'll
just be able to apply the principle to
other similar examples but here's the
idea of of the multiplication principle
let's say I spin one die right regular
six-sided die there's six different ways
that it can land it's kind of an easy
counting problem one two three four five
six count the number of faces on the
cube but if I spend two dice how many
different ways are there for the outcome
to show up well there's one one and
there's one two and there's 1 3 and
there's one for there's 1 5 in this one
6 there's 2 1 2 3 6 3 etc so altogether
this how many there's 36 and the
multiplication principle is an
overwhelming idea that when you do two
things one after the other in order to
accomplish a complete task then if you
want to count how many ways there are of
doing a complete task it's the number of
ways of doing the first part times the
number of ways of doing the second part
it's very logical everything in
combinatoric is logical but some of it
is very very deep and subtle and it
takes time to digest so how many
multiplication principle here you can
make a little table you know one through
six one through six and notice that
every little entry in that square table
is another pair of dice spins and six
times six but it's part of a more
general principle another example of the
multiplication principle that you've
seen before in your problem sets how
many ways for this class to get in line
New Yorkers say online we're in line I'm
never like I say online get online
anyway what if I think you guys have to
all get online and you have to go ahead
and and line up to use the soda machine
out there right so I can say there's 36
people here today there's 36 ways I can
choose the first person online now I
have to choose a second person and
there's 35 ways to choose the next
person when I'm all done I've
accomplished my task how many different
ways were there for me to do this it's
36 times 35 times 34 times 33 it's the
same kind of principle and the answer is
in this class since we have 36 people
it's 36 factorial
I said I don't want you to line up but
I'm randomly 36 different times gonna
choose somebody from this class you know
and let them go out and I don't know
check the doorbell or something then I
have 36 choices every time I can pick
the same person twice in a row so then
it would be 36 times 36 times 36 times
36 or 36 to the 36 all right so not
everything's n factorial some things are
you'll see factorials a lot they come up
a lot in a lot of different disguises
induction here's a theorem from 1321
this in algebra if PN is the number of
different ways to order n people then PN
is n times the number of different ways
to order n minus 1 people and this
theorem is written out in prose it's
written out in the vernacular was
written in Hebrew and it's a paragraph
long to define these terms and then
three lines to quote this theorem and
then another two pages to prove it and
if you actually look at that recurrence
equation because that's what it really
is and you solve it in P 1 equals 1 then
you get P N equals n factorial right I'm
not going to go in that direction
because that's what we did last week
that's not our topic today all right so
that's principle one next principle
addition principle these two principles
are very basic and the principles are
going to get a little harder as we go
along
how many ways to spin an odd sum you
spin two dice how many of them give you
an odd sum
well there's one brute force way to do
this write down all the possible 36 ways
and look at them and check each one off
if it gives you an odd son can do that
that's there's lots of ways let's do it
this way that uses what we'll call the
addition principle let's divide it up
into well how many ways can you get it
you can get a three that's odd right you
can't get a one with two dice so you can
get a three you can get a five three a
five a seven and nine or an 11 these are
all completely separate possibilities
the addition principle says that if you
can divide up the things you're trying
to count in two disjoint possibilities
then count them all separately and add
them together and if you're thinking
what kind of a principle is that it's
just complete common sense well then
good for you
that's all it is it's this complete
common sense so let's add them all up
how many different ways when you spin
two dice can you get a three you get a
one two or a or two one how about five
not everyone agree six this kind of
symmetry comes up a lot in counting and
there's often a lot more depth behind
what you're doing and you can discover
it looking for patterns but we're not
going to do that now we're just going to
look at this add it up there's our
answer 6 12 18 half of them I guess
that's not such a surprise although I
gotta tell you I could easily come up
with a problem where your gut instinct
would be to guess half and you would be
wrong so so be really careful in
counting your intuition does not always
correspond to what happens when you
really do the counting be really really
careful don't make kind of fuzzy
arguments and expect them to work
sometimes they do sometimes they don't
alright my next principle we're getting
a little away from whether way the book
has these two principles and then it
says okay here now I'm going to teach
you some basics but I think there's more
principles that the book leaves out and
these are the ones that anybody who gets
good at these problems routinely use
and I want to give them to you as
principals so you think of them as part
of your bag of tricks instead of having
to just discover them by yourself
all right the complement principle the
cobbler in principle is one of the key
things in counting it basically says
look if you can't count what you're
trying to count count the opposite
because sometimes kind of the opposite
is easy what does that mean here's a
simple example how many of the dice that
we just spun how many are not doubled
easier to count the doubles than it is
to count the not doubles
one two two six so how many were there
altogether there were 36 altogether
minus six for the doubles that equals
the not doubles 30 not those this is a
very very straightforward simple example
of this but this idea is a fundamental
idea that comes up all the time let me
do another example of it let's say
you're doing something some random thing
say say I take this teeny piece of chalk
and I throw it way over there on the
other side of the room and if it lands
in that flowerpot I succeed oh I missed
how often am I going to get that one out
of a hundred say never let's say it's
one out of a hundred if not I'll just
move the flowerpot down let's say
there's something I do that's one out of
a hundred chance and let's say I do it a
hundred times so if you ask somebody who
completely doesn't think about it for a
second or is very naive they'll say well
if you can get it one out of a hundred
times and you do it a hundred times I
guess then you'll have to get it I mean
that's not true right I mean there's
plenty of things you do like say you're
a 50% free-throw shooter does that mean
every time you shoot two free-throws you
get one in no it doesn't mean that at
all it means in the long run you'll get
half of a minute this means in the long
run I get one out of a hundred in but if
I do it a hundred times it doesn't mean
that I'm definitely going to get one in
well what is the chance
that I'm gonna get one in if I do it a
hundred times we're gonna calculate this
straight up and this actually relates
counting to probability which is a good
connection for you to have we're gonna
do this problem right now with a
complement principle and it's not that
hard it's going to be a combination of
the complement principle and the
multiplication principle all right so
what if I told you my chance of getting
it on the floor is ninety-nine out of a
hundred that's the same as the opposite
of my chance of getting it in or the
complement of my chance of getting it in
yet again is one out of one hundred
missing it is ninety-nine out of a
hundred now you can do something that's
a little bit better what's the chance to
be missing it twice if I want something
to occur and I want it to occur again
that and word is like I'm spinning this
die and I'm spinning another die if you
want two things to happen one and then
the other you can just multiply them
together to get the count on it
so if I take ninety-nine out of a
hundred that's a chance of me missing
and I want to know how many times out of
a hundred squared
I will actually miss it'll be 99 times
99 divided by a hundred squared that'll
be the number of times I miss if I do it
twice okay what's the number of times I
will what's the what's the probability
or the number of times I'll miss if I do
it a hundred times instead of twice I'll
write this out 99 over a hundred to the
hundredth this represents the chance
that I will actually miss a hundred
times in a row okay if anybody have a
calculator I can't do this in my head do
99 over 100 to the hundredth
the pot a hundred times in a row
it's the multiplication principle one
after the other after the other what do
you get all right but I don't want it
what do I get Rob 0.366 something okay
so that's a reasonable number even
though I have a strange-looking thing
here right it means that I'm going to
miss a hundred times in a row a little
over a third of the time so what's the
chance I'm going to get it
it's the complement of this it's one the
certainty minus this so if I ask the
question
I got a hundredth of a chance to get
this piece of chalk in that flowerpot I
do it a hundred times what's the chance
I'm going to get it after a hundred
times a little less than two-thirds at
least once right get it at least once
right this is a hard problem and well
relatively hard compared to this easy
one here and it uses just two ideas the
idea of complement and the idea of the
multiplication principle it also
connects the probability which I did a
little early here because I want you to
see it and I'm going to come back to
showing you the connection between
counting and probability later so keep
this in mind as a good example I am
going to build up to this later a little
more slowly question if you do this
problem instead of a hundred you make it
a thousand one thousandth of a chance
and then you do it a thousand times
or one ten thousandth of a chance and
then you do with ten thousand times then
this number this one here becomes and
the other one becomes e minus one over e
that's the complement of this this
number the chance of me missing goes to
one over e that number that came from
calculus it's where does it come from
it's not too hard to come up with this
but we're not going to do it now I mean
it isn't it it seems mysterious but it's
not so bad
well that's very interesting
um I do it for much more mundane things
like not really like free-throw shooting
you know I say guy or I do it with darts
I was going to challenge one of you guys
to darts I can get if I shoot I'm doing
well I can get out of a hundred throws I
can get seventeen in the middle that's
my that's like a good day for me and get
seventeen in the middle so then I have
to calculate well what's the chance if I
throw say ten of me getting two or more
and I can calculate that probability
knowing that I get 17 out of a hundred
it's very similar calculation to this
and I know whether I can bet on this or
not if I got a 65% chance of getting two
or more out of ten then I can bet to my
heart's content and I'm going to win
money if I just have a good instinct
that I can get two out of ten your gut
instincts about what you can do in life
are hardly ever good to bet on it's just
not a way to go you do a calculation
before you go ahead and bet on what you
think you can do let's move on to the
next principle we're reviewing
principles here not not not coming up
with with ABCs of counting yet these are
just the general principles and then
we're going to go through some more I
think what we call had a spell you know
kind of like what are the the basic
notations and and and definitions but
right now just principles are much more
important the next principle we did
addition we do multiplication being a
compliment and now we're going to do a
principle that I call counting double
counting double in a controlled way I
don't really mean double here I mean I
mean multiple counting in a controlled
way it's a really really good technique
here's one place you've seen this all
ready say I want to count how many ways
there are of choosing a pair of you to
go up and complain about the leak in the
corner all right I want to you to go
upstairs and complain to at stake
there's a leak here go how many
different ways can I choose you
well I can pick anybody for the first
person that's 36 and I can pick anybody
for the second person that's 35 but if I
pick Joe for the first person and then I
pick time for the second person and they
go up and then my next pick is Tom first
and then Joe second they're going to say
you two jerks were just here right so
that's not the same I got to pick two
different people every time and if I
just do 36 times 35 I've counted every
single person in a pair twice so the
right number of pairs in this group is
36 times 35 divided by 2 but it's a nice
way to count right I counted everybody
twice on purpose but I controlled it I
knew I was counting everybody twice a
lot easier than counting it the other
way will you come up with the triangle
numbers well not a lot easier but a
little bit different there are examples
where this double counting is a lot
easier let me give you one all right so
this time no more sending people
upstairs to complain about the the water
this time we are where we're getting
political we're going to get a president
a vice president a secretary and
treasurer for Adu that's right recant
president and secretary and a treasurer
I've got 36 choices for the president
and multiplication principle 35 for the
vice president 34 for the secretary and
33 for the treasurer and the order here
matters I mean it's different if I if I
pick Tom 2nd and Joe first then ones
president ones vice president so here I
don't want to divide by anything I don't
count anything double it's actually 36
times 35 times 34 times 33 but what if I
don't care who gets what title what if I
just want them to act as a committee
okay it's just a group in that case I
counted a lot of these things twice
here's my count again 36 times 35 times
34 times 33 and I'm going to write that
one particular sequence of president
vice president secretary and treasurer
I'll just give you guys here we'll do
Joe Tom Seth and Heather
I counted this once
look at this committee and I only care
about the committee right so all the
other possibilities that have JT SH in
them in a different order have been
counted more than once in particular
this one's been counted
this one's been counted in there as a
separate case well it's really the same
PJs H is the same as JT Sh as far as the
committee goes how many different ways
are there of counting this guy multiple
times I can rearrange it any way I want
four factorial right we did that earlier
so I got to take this number and note to
myself that every single one of these
was counted four factorial times so if I
want to get the right number of
committees I just have to take this
number and divide it by divided by 4
factorial then I have each one of these
possibilities as a committee kind of
just want this is an idea you'll see
again
it'll come up when we talk about the
ABCs of binomial coefficients but it's a
really important idea count double on
purpose count multiple times on purpose
keep track that you've counted everybody
24 times and then divide by 24 to get
the real number you're looking for it's
much easier to count this this way than
any other way you'll try questions about
this that's counting double one more
principle before we move on to the nitty
gritties one more principle when our
things the same I think of all the
principles this might be the most subtle
and the most important one of the most
common things you do in combinatorics is
notice that counting this turns out to
be the same as counting this even though
they seem completely different at first
glance and that's why I spent some time
at the beginning of the day reviewing
that question you all looked in the
previous problem set at the following
problem you're given three matrices or n
matrices in the general case or four
matrices and you want to put parentheses
around them to associate them and be
able to multiply them out so here's one
way there are plenty of other ways how
many ways are there as you all know
right there's five different ways you
did this problem said already another
thing which seems like it's the same but
one when you realize and you think about
it for a while it really isn't think you
think about it again you're always oh it
really is
are these balanced parentheses balanced
parentheses of three pairs turn out to
be exactly the same as counting
different ways of associating four
matrices give me four matrices how do I
associate them how many ways can I do it
same as the number of ways to write
three pairs of balanced parentheses
these things are the same it is not
obvious they're the same you have to
think carefully and explain why they're
the same there's one more thing that's
the same as these things which isn't
obvious as I said before the number of
different binary trees with three nodes
here's a couple of them there's five of
those
recurrence relationship all three of
these have the same values for given
number of nodes here and here given
number of nodes give a number of pairs
of parens and given number of matrices
plus one they all have the same exact
counting structure not obvious let me
give you another situation like this
when it is obvious or at least at the
stage where you are that you'll feel
it's obvious this is something you've
seen before the maximum number of edges
in a graph with n nodes okay I have a
graph with that nodes I want to throw in
as many edges as I can no multi edges
just two vertices or two nodes can be
connected by an edge yes or no what is
this the same as that we just talked
about right number of pairs chosen from
a group choosing two vertices is like
choosing a pair taking those two nodes
from a group putting an edge is like
sending them up how many different ways
can I choose these edges the same as a
number of ways that I can choose two
people from a group these two things are
the same there's something else that's
the same as these things that you've
seen dozens of times in this class
already and it's the triangle numbers if
somebody asks you to figure out what's
the triangle number when you're trying
to go up to a particular n it's going to
be the same as these two
don't know if I said it right so let's
do it right write it down let's do this
example with seven I got seven people
I'm gonna take pairs out that gives me 7
times 6 divided by 2 right so that
equals 21 let's look at the triangle
numbers 1 plus 2 Plus 3 plus 4 plus 5
plus 6 if I take the triangle number all
the way up to the number one below the
number of nodes of my graph that's the
same as that 21 it's not an accident so
this equals number of pairs from a group
with n people is the same as maximum
number of edges in a graph with n nodes
is the same as the triangle number of n
minus 1 all the same here you can
actually convince yourself they're the
same there I think you really need some
more practice before you can tackle that
problem the level of difficulty and
sophistication and seeing that things
are the same really varies a lot you all
know about binary trees there's binary
trees they spread out to each time I'm
gonna define something called a funny
binary tree here's a funny binary tree
funny binary tree here's the rules about
how you generate a funny binary tree
you on the left side split it into two
and on the right side only have one
coming out leave off this right note
let's continue this down in the next
slide on the left side it splits into
two on the right side it splits into one
what about here let's do a couple more
layers do you see how this graph is the
fight inductively I described how the
next stage comes from the last stage
the next level if I asked you you could
all do it all right now let's look how
many nodes are there at a given level of
this funny binary tree 1 2 3 5 8 yeah
what's on the next level 13 you have any
idea why it's the same as if you Bonacci
numbers because you've seen it before
either there's a good proof I don't
think it's obvious why this is the same
you can think about it and you might be
able to come up with an idea but
probably not on the spot at 30 seconds
but here's an example of something
that's the same as this that you
wouldn't naturally notice that it's the
same as this how many different ways are
there to write binary strings without
double ones remember that from the
problem set the number of different ways
to write binary strings without double
ones is the same as the number of nodes
in this tree now that I can convince you
quickly every one of these nodes is
going to represent a string of zeros and
ones which one does this one represent
left is zero right as one this
represents zero zero this represents one
zero how come there's no double ones at
any node because I left out all the
right moves after I made a right move
anytime you go right you can't go right
again that's how this trees define no
double writes this trees nodes
represents in binary exactly the binary
strings that don't have double ones it's
not obvious have I just described this
tree to you and then gave you the
problem with double ones that you'd even
notice there was a connection after you
worked on it for a while but you got to
look for these connections because each
one shines light on the other it's like
walking around in a dark room and
somebody keeps dimming up the lights
until you get a better and better
picture all right I won't do the proof
of why this recursive relationship is
true but it depends exactly on the
connection to the double ones you all
supposedly did a proof for the double
ones what you came up with a recurrence
equation how'd you do that
you thought that there's the last case
either there's a zero or the last cases
either there are one you should have two
cases I can go over that problem maybe
later on but if you take whatever you
did for that problem and connect it one
two one two what works here in this
problem you'll see a connection between
the number of nodes here and how they
correspond to this set so you take one
problem you see the correspondence there
you know there's a one-to-one with these
binary trees and you can take your
argument there and transform it to an
argument here even though you might not
see the argument on the tree and you
might be able to see it with binary
numbers more easily change your
abstraction and you can change what you
can think about it's one of the key
ideas and scheme change your abstraction
it's not just makes things easier it's
that you couldn't even think about it do
it before now you can do it
same thing in here same thing in
combinatoric change your way of looking
at the problem and what used to be
obscure becomes obvious all right I'm
gonna leave this we can't do every
little detail of stuff I try to motivate
with but this is just motivation will
get this particular problems that I want
you to work out soon questions about
this yes Tony it's cool all right isn't
it cool yeah
and I think so okay
that's a nice way to look at it alright
that's it for principals y'all got the
principal's check yeah all right they're
deceptively easy be careful they're
really deceptively easy combinatorics is
famous for here's a really easy sounding
problem that is really hard it's also
famous for really hard sounding problems
that are really easy don't be afraid to
engage yourself in the maze don't
memorize stuff in this course do every
problem take your principles with you
and think about it if you start to
memorize you'll kind of get lost if you
have to memorize you can make it through
but try not to yeah Anthony yeah let's
say a B C and D is the group that I
chose for a president vice president and
treasurer secretary but if I don't care
about what order they're in you know if
I want to count for example a BDC as the
same group but I didn't I counted them
separately then the question is how many
things are counted ABCD how many of them
are equivalent to this one that were
actually counted separately it's all the
ones that have ABCD in them in some
different order and how many different
ways are there counting ABCD in a
different order
it's four people how many different ways
can they line up 4 times 3 times 2 times
1 so that means I could list if I wanted
to 24 possibilities here and every one
of them was counted separately even
though I really want to count those 24
as just 1 and every single unique
collection ABCD gets counted 24
different times so if I just take my
whole big collection and divide it by 24
I end up getting one for each real
unique group that makes sense it's a
really good question and it's
fundamental and it seems so easy after
you've thought about it for 10 years and
it's not easy and I just got to tell you
just to admit my own
the reason that that I like this part of
the course so much and the reason I
spend so much time where I feel I'm
spending a lot of time making sure we do
it in a gradual way is because this is
the part of the course that when I first
learned it 20 years ago was the most
dense to me it took me a long time when
I first saw this stuff to really digest
that and have it be automatic but it'll
come if you just spend 20 years if
you're me but you're smarter than me so
it'll take you less yeah if we chose
this group out of 10 we'd have 10 times
9 times 8 times 7 and then we divide it
by 4 times 3 times 2 times 1
right now
what you're discovering right now which
is just perfect it's like a pedagogical
dream it's like I'm just we're doing
this right away you should exactly be
thinking about these things once you
have these principles the next thing you
discover are these things called
binomial coefficients which is exactly
what Chris was asking about and we're
going to do that right now
about rigorously maybe for the first
time in the 1600s by Pascal they were
talked about on a very very algorithmic
and also somewhat rigorous way long
before way back into the early Middle
Ages maybe eight or nine hundred people
were already talking about permutations
and combinations they didn't do proofs
with it mostly by the time eleven twelve
thirteen hundred came along there were
some proofs that you can find in Islamic
and and and Hebrew mathematicians works
and then nobody really knows whether or
who looked at that stuff from this huge
gap between the end of the Greek period
and the beginning of the Renaissance in
Europe but there was clearly a
transmission of information it didn't
just jump there wasn't this dark period
in that as people kind of think there
was definitely an evolution and it
worked its way from you
and combinations having a very fuzzy but
but but definite origin sometime in the
in the early Middle Ages
all right so people knew about the stuff
a long time ago and they did it for
mysticism and for astrology and also for
astronomy and all sorts of different
ways but we're going to do it today for
computer science here's a symbol pnk we
use PN before to mean the number of
permutations or the number of ways to
order n elements so what this means is I
want to choose K people from n people
and permutations mean that I care about
the order that I care who's president I
care whose vice president so for example
P of 36 4 equals 36 times 35 times 34
times 33 no division because I
absolutely care about who comes first we
just did that problem this is a general
way of writing it for any end that you
start with in any K that you're choosing
and we're going to come up with a
formula for this now now that we
understand the principle for the
particular case questions well let's
write it out the choice for the first
one how many choices do we have
n right not 36 but n and then the next
one and minus one all the way and minus
K plus 1 is that the last one let's just
double-check Sam's right of course but
let's double check let's double check
the last one here was 33 36 minus 34
gives you 32 and minus K then you got to
add one to make sure you don't go too
far make sure you get the detail right
now that's not usually how we write it
although back in the Middle Ages they
would write it that way they just
wouldn't write it with these symbols
they'd say it would be the product of
all the numbers starting from one where
you go in a downward direction
subtracting one with each subsequent
number until you get to the lowest
number which would be K less than the
number you started with plus one you
could
figure out what the person was talking
about unless you already knew the idea
in advance or you spent five hours
deciphering it so notation is very
important and it's clear that there were
definitely mathematical works back in
those times that for a hundred years
went completely not understood it just
wasn't clear anybody could make heads or
tails out of it unless the teacher
actually was presenting it alright let's
go ahead and write this in a better way
it's n factorial right it's everything
but let's divide out this part and
that'll give us what we have left up
there
what's that part know Oh n factorial
divided by n minus K factorial everyone
see why this is the same as this it's
because you have a whole list of
products and then you want to divide
through the stuff that would come later
that's the formula let's make a formula
for the same issue but we do not care
now about the order we want it to just
be a group of four same as before but
now this is called combination so we say
C of n K and it's the same formula
except for one thing what do we do to
fix this right now we divide through by
in this case 4 factorial or in general K
factorial because we have counted each
one of the things that we're trying to
count K factorial different times so we
divide through by K factorial make it
work this comes up more often than this
although they both come up a lot this
comes up in so many areas of mathematics
that it's completely fundamental to know
this and have it be as automatic to you
as arithmetic it's so fundamental and
automatic that it has a special symbol
this and this are the same and we say n
choose K when we want to talk about this
symbol and choose K means that I'm
choosing K things from N and I don't
care about the order
coefficients and you'll see why in a
second yes yes this n factorial takes n
times n minus 1 all the way down to 1
I'm gonna put this in for a second this
whole thing would be n factorial and now
if I divide through by this part to the
N I get the part I really want do you
see that good it's a good question other
questions so far okay good I had a
fifth-grade teacher who was a very nice
man but he uh he was also a very strict
guy and this was in some Bible class I
was taking about the prophets and and we
were studying something and and he asked
me what does this word mean it was a
Hebrew word I hadn't the slightest clue
what it meant it was some kind of a verb
somebody doing something to somebody
else and I didn't know so I read I was a
good reader even though I couldn't
understand what I was reading I could
actually pronounce everything in Hebrew
so I read look down in the book and
there was an interpreter from the Middle
Ages who had described the meaning of
the word because it was a strange word
and he described it in terms of other
words but I also didn't know so I
hesitated for a minute and then I kind
of paraphrased with the person wrote and
I said it out to him and I smiled at him
and he smiled back and he goes what does
that mean well it's kind of like you
know he I'm looking for a clue he
doesn't give me he's like stone-faced no
clue at all and I go well like when
somebody wants to tell somebody
something but they don't want to tell
him you know straight up they want to
kind of like tell somebody else first
and then you know what I mean he goes oh
you mean like like he related it over to
somebody else to to tell this guy and I
go yeah that's right
and he goes wrong
cuz I feel like such an idiot I go I
trusted you let's do this problem what's
the coefficient of x cubed and X plus 1
to the 7th this seems like a completely
unrelated problem but it's completely
related to this point and I want to run
through this with you because in going
through the answer you'll understand the
connection between this counting idea
and this question and you'll understand
why these things are called binomial
coefficients so here it is here's X plus
1 to the 7 1 2 3 4 5 this chalk is great
it's so much better than that other
lousy truck I feel good I'm moving it's
good chalk and it's not dustless it's
just full chalk that's what makes it
work we're not going to multiply it out
but we are going to do this right it's
hideous to multiply this all right
nobody wants to do it but what you can
do if you write it out this way is
notice that any one of the terms if you
did multiply it out can be written in
the following way if I keep track of
what X is I'm dealing with so I'm going
to write X 1 here just to keep track X 2
X 3 X 4 X 5 X 6 X 7 and let's multiply
through an example I could get X 1 times
X 2 times 1 times X 4 times 1 times X 6
times X 7 I can just multiply through
and as I go along left to right I can
choose either to multiply through the X
part or the or the 1 part now let's try
to write down as I do that which ones
end up having 3 X's in them because
those are the ones that will accumulate
to eventually giving me all the X cubes
all right let's write them down let's
start writing them down at least x1 x2
x3 1 1 1
okay that's one that's one X cubed
what's another one thank you must have
been so much fun to grow up in your
house must have been a puzzle just to
get to the peas children you've noticed
today that I've set the main course up
locked away from the appetizer if you
can get it within a minimum number of
moves it really would have been fun
here's another one every one of these
combinations of X's and ones multiplied
together as you go left to right
corresponds to one X cube so I could
list these out and and exhaust them but
that's just what you don't want to do in
counting unless you're desperate you
don't want to go the brute force way
okay if you're desperate you do it but
we want to figure out a way to count
these more easily
what is this there's seven places here
right imagine that they all had ones in
them what we're really doing is choosing
three of those ones to get replaced with
X's how many ways if we have seven ones
can we choose three of those places to
throw X's 7 times 6 times 5 I don't care
about the order right if I pick X 6
first and X 2 next and X 5 last that's
the same one I don't want to count that
twice so I don't care about the order I
care just about choosing a collection of
three places from 7 that's exactly the
same as 7 choose 3 which is exactly the
same as 7 times 6 times 5 divided by 3
times 2 times 1
35 so you can see you'll be good because
week 35 ways to exhaust this it's better
that we do it this way that means there
are 35 ways of multiplying these terms
together and getting through
axes in the resulting term that means
there are 35 pieces of this
multiplication that will have X cubed so
the coefficient in front of the X cubed
is going to be 35 right this is an
important problem to look at it connects
counting back to algebra all right let
me stop for a second turn I did a card
trick at the very beginning of this year
which you are going to see again in this
kind of a roaming problem set that I
that I put up there that needs to be
done by the end of the year and this
week I know what you're thinking you're
thinking he said year instead of month
this problem had to do with you choose a
set of five cards my assistant looks at
your five cards doesn't show them to me
picks four of them out and then hands me
four of those cards in order so I can
see what order they come in and then I
look at the order of those four cards
and I determine the fifth card that's in
your hand and this is not a magic trick
it's just a combinatorial trick you can
make a look like magic if you patter it
up a lot but but it's completely a
mathematical trick we're going to do
that again but before we do it not today
we won't do it but we'll do it soon next
couple days before we do what I want to
do is show you part of that problem and
analyze it combinatorially how many
different ways are there for you guys to
choose the five cards to begin with how
many different sets of five cards could
show up in your hand if I start with 52
cards in a regular deck and I let you
choose it doesn't matter what order you
choose them right it's just the
collection of cards in your hand
so it's 52 choose five that's 52 times
51 times 50 times 49 times 48 divided by
5 times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1 right
that's the number of different ways you
can choose cards all right now out of
all those ways then oh here's my
assistant then thar I pick is that you
know no my glasses huh so Tyrel picks 4
cards out of that out of that collection
how many different ways given given a
hand of five cards can she choose four
and show them to me in order this
requires a little more thinking once she
chooses the four how many different ways
can she hand them to me in order once
she chooses that 4 factorial 4 times 3
times 2 times 1 but she gets to make a
choice before she shows them to me in
order she gets to choose which 4 she's
going to show me how many ways are there
for her to choose those 4 5 choose 4
of picking the 4 cards and for each one
of those remember the and for each one
the multiplication principle for each
one of those she has 4 factorial
choices so it's 5 times 4 factorial
which equals 5 factorial or 120 that
means when Tara sees your hand she at
least theoretically can transmit to me
how many pieces of information 120
different possible pieces of information
she can give me a hundred and 20
different possible sequences of cards
since there's only while one card left
in your hand presumably with 120 pieces
of information I should be able to
determine the card left in your hand
because there's only 48 cards that I
don't see I even seem to have a little
bit of slack so at least theoretically
it looks like we could do this puzzle
and we'll get back to this puzzle again
but I wanted to immediately show you the
connection between what you just learned
with combinations of permutations it
relates immediately directly to
analyzing that puzzle that magic trick
questions
are cooking cooking with gas
Pascal's triangle
triangle a lot of people had pictures of
it in their works long before Pascal
sometimes when I give talks on on my own
research in history of math I show some
weird script in Hebrew with this funny
weird diagram that looks like it's
Pascal's triangle actually it's just
long division and I asked any group of
mathematicians hey what do you think
this is in the all guessed Pascal's
triangle and I go that's just a long
division and they'll look at me like we
wanted Pascal's triangle but it also it
shows up everywhere you can get in
almost every culture Pascal's triangle
shows up it's very very fundamental you
can find a lot of stuff in it not only
the binomial coefficients that I just
told you before but all sorts of other
relationships the Fibonacci numbers show
up here in an interesting way that
you'll see in your problem set almost
everything you've seen in some way shows
up here where the triangle numbers in
this picture anybody see them triangle
numbers well what is this weird picture
and why does it have so much symmetry
and beauty and and and combinations it's
just got so much in it this picture is
supposed to represent the binomial
coefficients of all the possible values
of N and K so for example let's take
this row this row is to choose 0 to
choose one to choose two q20 is oh what
is 2 to 0 how many ways are there of
choosing nothing from a set of two well
there's one way to choose nothing it's
use nothing so there's two two zeroes 1
2 choose 1 is 2 & 2 choose 2 is 1 the
next row is 3 choose 0
three choose one 3 choose 2 and 3 choose
3 it's a table of all the binomial
coefficients everybody okay so far I
want to show you a theorem which is
known as the binomial theorem that
relates to this and relates back to the
algebra we just did and then I'll talk a
lot more about this triangle here's the
theorem there's a lot of versions of the
binomial theorem here's one version if
you take two things X plus y and you
multiply them out n times kind of like
this X plus 1 okay this is a special
case of the binomial theorem here's what
ends up happening first I'm going to
write these terms out X to the N X to
the N minus 1 Y X to the N minus 2 y
squared the first thing that happens is
I need more room I'm going to rewrite
this sorry X to the N what's so funny
happens is you start with X to the N
you'll know you'll get that term you'll
also get terms with our n minus 1 X's
and 1 Y you'll also get terms with our n
minus 2 X's and a y squared anytime you
multiply these things n times through
you're going to get some number of X's
some number of wise but the combination
of the X's and Y's together have to add
up to n just like the combination of X's
and ones here have to add up to 7 so if
you notice I got all X's here I got all
X's except 1 I got all X's except 2 and
this goes all the way down to what's the
second to last term XY to the n minus 1
and then and Y to the N right so that
part's okay but the question is what
numbers come in front of each of these
terms remember here in front of the X
cubed one to the fourth term we got 7
choose 3 so the binomial theorem tells
you that this is general and here's what
comes in front of each of these terms
in front of here comes n choose 0 in
front of here comes n choose 1 and
choose 2 and choose good was that you
Joe good for you and then n choose n you
see these numbers n choose 1 n choose 0
n choose 1 n choose 2 all the way up to
the end they represent a particular row
in this triangle so if I want to know
for example what's x plus y cubed all I
got to do is write these out x cubed x
squared Y XY squared Y cubed and copy
these numbers over 1 3 3 1 who gets this
half of you 2/3
taking expressions like this and
splitting them up into pieces it's
deceptively useful it looks like it
makes things more complicated but it
often makes things easier you're going
to see it come up later on I want you to
see it today because it connects to this
nice example of permutations and
combinations and it because it relates
to this triangle that lists all the
permutations that lists all the
combinations for every n in K all right
let's make sure everybody gets this what
if I have here 1 plus 1 to the N ok
let's use let's use the binomial theorem
it equals to Dean you're all laughing
you're right it equals 2 to the N what
does a binomial theorem tell you that
it's equal to the X's and Y's are all
ones right so they all become ones
that's a nice example to use you don't
have to worry about the XS and the Y's
are all ones X to the N is 1 X to the N
minus 1 is 1 why do they anything is 1
so what do you get here n choose 0 plus
and choose 1 plus all the way up to and
choose N and that equals 2 to the N well
that's neat that came out for free this
is one of the basic combinatorial
identities there's dozens there's a
hundred of these don't memorize them
well this one you can memorize if you
want to what which one all right I'll go
for it
who knows what happens if we run through
1 minus 1 you get 0 right
what's the series going to look like
being negative because these negative
ones multiply and when you have an even
number of terms you get positive and we
have an odd number of terms you get
negative the terms number of terms
change one each time so they start equal
to
or minus huh this is negative that's
neat so if you alternate the terms well
that means we can let's check this out
this should equal to this should equal
four this should equal eight right it
depends on the end right I'll put a
question mark here depends right two
four eight if you add them this should
be 16 is it better be now let's do the
the other trick one minus five plus 10
minus ten plus five minus one that
should be zero to this row 1 minus 4
plus 6 minus 4 plus 1 zero more
impressive
agreed this is symmetrical not so fancy
this is less symmetrical more
interesting there's a lot of hidden cool
things in the binomial theorem we're
going to touch on them later what do you
think the squares of these things equal
N 1 squared plus n 2 squared
addy instead of just adding up the
regular binomial coefficients and choose
0 and choose n we'll square them each
and then add them up now that's all
right you'll see it on a problem set
that's okay
point out a feature that you might have
noticed or you might not have and it's
something we can prove we can prove it
in five different ways the styles of
proofs are going to be things you're
going to see again and again so I want
to concentrate on at least one or two of
these kind of proofs one of the proofs
will be a proof by induction which I
won't do because we're sick of it right
we don't need to do more proofs by
induction but you could and I'll mention
that you can but what is it that we want
to show you can write how did I write
this out so fast that I go ahead and do
the factorials in my head no to get the
next number like three you add the two
that are on top of it so the 10 is a
some six and four and fifteen is a sum
of ten and five and the ones you just
imagine they're zeroes all the way on
the outside like a sea of zeros so 0 and
1 gives you one you always get one out
here so the next row would be 8 20 a
5670 56 28 8 1 it's a nice easy way to
do it let's write out what that means
now that we've noticed it it means that
n choose K pick a random one say this
one and choose K equals this one what's
this one n minus 1 because it's the row
up and it's one to the left so this is n
minus 1 K minus 1 plus n minus 1 K back
1 and then up straight
proved this yet we just noticed that it
was true one way to prove this and I'm
going to leave it to you if you feel
like because it's a very boring way is
you have formulas for all these three
things right and factorials plug them in
and see if they're all the same you
could all do it and that would prove
this formula and it would be a perfectly
fine proof everyone agree right it's
just going to be a bunch of factorials
you mush them around let's do it a
different way
so there's proof by formula check
there's proof by induction yeah actually
in this example of proof by induction is
not so easy and it doesn't scream and
it's not natural and it's hard you get
these ugly things when you try to prove
it by induction so it's a good thing
we're going to leave that there but
we're going to prove it by combinatorics
by Counting proof by Counting this is an
important method to learn whoo-hoo let's
do this proof by Counting I'm going to
show you that if we think about this in
terms of how to count it that it's the
same as if we think about the sum of
these two things as far as how to count
them this is that same idea of what
things are the same counting this many
things is the same as counting this and
this together adding them together let
me convince you of this the best way for
me to convince you is with a particular
example and then convince you that that
example really used none of the
specifics to convey the idea so it will
really be completely general
pretend I'm doing new stuff at least
let's see now let's do it like this I
choose three of them i don't care about
the order how many ways are there to do
it
35 ways right 7 times 6 times 5 divided
by 3 times 2 times 1
i want to divide these ways up into two
categories
some of the ways there's a very special
individual in these 7 let's say they
represent people okay so say a is the
that woman down in florida that gets to
decide who becomes president everybody
else is just some some schmuck doesn't
matter there's an important person in
everybody else so what happens I have to
choose three of these people for my
committee so in my head I'm thinking
about well there's two possibilities
either I include the person you know who
can push the button on who's president
or I don't include her right some of
these Committees of three will include
her some won't
everybody with me how many committees
include her she's included how many
committees include her if I include her
then I can include just two more people
I include those two people from six this
represents the bigwig is included okay
but that's not all the possibilities
let's do the rest of them where I do not
include her
the picture I have six left but now I
have to choose three from those six and
choose K equals n minus 1 choose K minus
1 plus n minus 1 choose K there's
nothing I did here that was specific to
7 and 6 if I had written it up with ends
and K days it might have been a little
less clear but writing it up like this
doesn't make the argument any less
general there was nothing I said that
really relied on 7 & 6 this list could
have gone on forever and your answers
would have been just the same in terms
of the ends in the case so let's call
that a proof check that's a proof by a
combinatorial argument let's do this by
combinatorial argument okay we know this
is true by not by binomial coefficients
let's do it by a combinatorial argument
by a counting argument
Michael I'm arguing that I didn't use
anything particular to 7 in this
argument you want me to write it out the
other way no I'm not being facetious but
I'll write it out the other way and you
tell me if it's more clear here are my
elements X 1 X 2 X n black X I be a
randomly chosen element I'll keep
talking I'll stop writing be a randomly
chosen element where I is between 1 and
n inclusive then I claim the number of
ways to choose K things from here is
divided into two subsets the subset that
contains X I and the subset that doesn't
contain X I the sub that that contains X
I how many ways are there to do that
there's X n minus 1 things left and I
have to choose K of them so it's n minus
1 choose K
and the subset that doesn't contain X I
going to do that right K minus 1 and the
subset that doesn't contain X I I still
have n minus 1 things left but I have to
choose K of them so I would write it all
out like that it would take me a half a
board and it would still be just as
general so I'm really not kidding about
it I might have to write it out more
detail to meet a twentieth-century
audience but the issue is have I
convinced you that this argument is is
is in general and and I didn't use
anything for 7 & 6 that were particular
so I think I did right and you can pick
any one you want this is you don't have
to pick a random one you can say pick
the first one it doesn't matter which
one you pick the whole thing goes
through you can choose anything you have
a lot of choice it doesn't have to be my
adversary that no there wouldn't if I
pick a as if I choose a is the one I'm
going to focus on then all the possible
collections of three committees
committees of size 3 either include a or
they don't include a that cats takes
care of all of them I could divide it
into another two possibilities where
they either contain B or don't contain B
but those two groups of two sets would
overlap a lot and I certainly don't want
to count them all so I can and I and
it's okay and it's a good idea to focus
just on one of them it makes the proof
easier so I can't tell that I didn't
convince everybody of the truth of this
but but I'm not going to do it in more
generality because you can't find this
proof you know what if you really wrote
it down and complete English and then
you said and there was nothing here you
know that where I used the seven and six
so this is a completely general argument
I would accept it absolutely let's go
back to here let's try to prove this in
a bunch of ways we proved it by the
binomial theorem that was cool
you could plug in the formula for each
one of these binomial coefficients and
add up that whole list of factorials and
get 2 to the N that seems ugly or we
could do it by combinatorics all right
ding no ding ding you know were you
going to do it and the problems that
you're gonna do it by combinatorics but
today I'm going I'm backing up we're
doing the yeah I'm gonna prove this to
you by induction oh you're thinking no
it'll be good let's assume this is true
let's try to show that the next case is
going to be true I'm going to write down
what we're gonna try to show over here
this is a kind of induction you all like
because the thing you're trying to show
on your assumption look like formulas so
it's easier to get a handle on where
you're coming from and where you're
going to what this one but this equals 2
to the n here's our assumption this
works for all n you can check that if n
is 1 it works right if n is if n is 1
it's just n choose 0 its 1 choose 0 plus
1 choose 1 and that's 2 and so for
there's a base case if n is 0 it works
and it's just 0 choose 0 and you get 1
that's ok how do we do it in general
we're going to try to head from here to
here you're not gonna hate this proof I
promise this is what we want to prove
everyone agree I just took the formula
before and i and i replaced it with n
plus 1 not that I know this is true I
don't know it's true I know this is true
by my inductive assumption and I'm going
to try to prove that this is true n plus
1 over n plus 1 right thank you right
thank you oh I'm now missing a turn
there we go
make any chocos all right what's next we
want to get from here to here or from
here back to here some connection
between these two that's just you can't
just plug in n plus ones here and expect
this theorem to still work that's what
we have to prove is true but we can't
make a relationship between these ugly
things and hopefully these things by
using this
let's fiddle with this until it looks
like that
this identity it's n choose 0 plus
because it takes things with numbers up
here and converts them to binomial
coefficients with numbers that are one
less so it gives me just what I want a
connection between here that has ends on
the top and here that I've n plus ones
this one what happens if I try to do it
on this one why did I start on the
second one they had some negative number
right what the heck is a negative value
in a binomial coefficient well your book
will go ahead and define what that means
so that it works in some other cool
problem but we don't go down that road
so if you see that in the book skip it
negative binomial coefficients are
really cool they do a lot of neat things
but we don't have enough time so we're
not going to define them we're just not
going to do this we're just going to
copy it down but notice is n plus 1 0
isn't that the same as just n choose 0
so if nobody minds I'll just change it
to n choose 0 and now what about this
guy what does he turn into + 1 and
choose 1 + and choose 2 everybody see
what's happening I'm going to go down
the whole way this way and choose 2 and
choose 3 double double double double
double double what happens at the very
end is Jo right and choose + n choose
magic of chalk again those are the last
two
this one oh I see what's the last one
it's just fine well n plus 1 choose n
plus 1 I'll just make that n choose n
because it's the same these two are
special everything else gets doubled
everything doubles except for the two
ends now look at the bottom the bottom
is exactly twice this that means this
whole thing is 2 times 2 to the N and
that's equal 2 to the n plus 1 and
that's what we want to prove
so this induction proof is actually very
nice it's not bad like I said the other
one would be it's actually very nice as
long as we have this relationship in
place doing combinatoric is like doing a
jigsaw puzzle and the more people you
have which means the more tools you
bring to the table the more everything
fits together and the faster it fits
together and it takes time to develop
all that stuff but you'll do it you'll
be good n plus 1 choose n plus 1 how
many ways are there to pick all of the
things from all of the things there's
just one way if I have 7 people
6 is what I'm saying if you run through
this formula you get you're right
you're right dog that would be a problem
but this is the last one that I doubled
this one gave me these two the last the
two on the ends I don't double up the
two on the ends I just write down the
way they are good question that's
important to clarify I was a little
fuzzy when I got to the end here because
I messed up a little but you're right
the two ends just go through the way
they are and that's why I got the double
the double end to 0 and the double n
choose n comes from those two ends being
copied down so isn't that a neat induct
proof that's powerful right that's yeah
I go right to your grandkids hey kids
let you go we did a lot one more example
of a combinatorial identity that we can
prove in a lot of different ways one way
you can prove this is by substituting in
formulas with factorials and doing
algebra I know you guys can do it we
won't do it here plug in to n choose 2
and choose 2 n choose 2 is n times n
minus 1 divided by 2 2 n choose 2 is 2 n
minus 2 n times 2 n minus 1 divided by 2
you can just put in the formulas and get
algebra who thinks I can do it
raise your hands really high so I know
you really can do it you want me to do
it what if you want me to do it raise
your hand if you want $100 raise your
hand it's making sure all right that's
one way you could try to prove it by
induction that's another way we really
won't do it that time but I want to do
this with a combinatorial argument again
I want to show you that counting this
number of things is the same as counting
this number of things so the way to show
that two formulas are the same is to
come up with something we're counting it
one way gives you this and counting it
another way gives you this it's a really
useful technique because it not only
lets you prove things like this but it
gives you a better way of looking at the
same problem from two different angles
got to prove it okay okay all right I
gotta try to do this proof more
generally since Michael didn't buy my my
more specific proof last time
I got I got an even number of things
here and I'm choosing two out of them
since it's an even number in my mind I'm
going to divide it into two halves okay
one half I'll call the 1/2 and 1/2 I'll
call the behalf and each of a and B has
how many things in it and and elements
here and elements here and I have to
choose two things out of these 2n things
that's 2 n choose 2 now I'm going to
show you another way of thinking about
how to choose two things from an even
number of elements and that second way
will be equivalent to this let's do it
I got two one things I have to choose
two out of here I'm going to divide up
the possibilities into the following
categories either my two let's make this
a little more motivated okay so I got 2n
people half of them are men half of them
are women I got to decide whether I'm
going to pick two people of the same
gender or one of each gender for this
committee all right that divides up the
category into two parts the committees
that have one man one woman and the
committees that have two people of the
same gender either two men or two women
right how many ways are there to choose
committees that have one man and one
woman I'll give you a hint you could
have done this before you started
today's lecture
I got n choices from here well maybe not
before but after five minutes and
choices from here and end choices from
here I can combine them in any way I
want if I have three men three women I
can take any one of those three men and
combine it with any one of the three
women it's like spinning to dice one
with n men one with n women and I get N
squared possibilities that's this one
man one woman two men enter one man
leaves
Max movie some of you watch that Mel
Gibson he does Shakespeare let's do this
one now I got two men or two women two
men or two women so if I'm going to pick
two men I got to pick them from this set
how many ways are there to choose two
from this set and choose two that's men
women and you see they're completely
distinct here they don't interfere with
one another so one man one woman N
squared all men and choose to all women
and choose two altogether to n choose
two plus N squared is the same as
choosing a pair from two it
it's another combinatorial argument it's
a very very useful trick to get under
your belt to be able to think about two
things in a different way counting them
the same yeah two times n choose two
this just means two times this two of
these