but maybe we'll talk about them in a
couple example cases so first if you
and I'm not going to go through these
have if you if you consider the strategy
that shy and I used so that strategy was
to use the first card to designate the
suit and then use the remaining cards to
designate how much to this card you were
supposed to add to get the hidden card
much to add to this card the question is
what size deck could this possibly work
for and for the case when we choose five
cards the case that this does work for
or that this strategy is suited for is
for a 52 card deck
so if hard if our let's see let's let n
be the number of cards we're choosing
so if if n is 5 then the number of suits
we can have is 4 suits because we need
to apply the prison all the pigeonhole
principle to allow to allow the
pigeonhole principle to work so that we
get two cards at the same suit so we can
have four suits and then the remaining
three cards so I guess this is in
general n minus two cards so the
remaining three cards can be permuted
there's three factorial permutations of
that so
chose from the given suit and so the
actual total number of cards that we can
have in the deck is 6 plus well 2 times
6 plus 1 so the total number in the suit
the total number of cards in the deck
for which this strategy works is 4 times
13 which is 52 so I guess what the one
question is asking you to do is to make
a similar argument for supposing you -
you chose wealth and cards what size
deck could you possibly get does this
make sense so far ok so the next
question that is on the problems that
asks you about how to you know what
what's the maximal total sized deck that
this could potentially work for I mean
it may may or may not work and you have
to figure out how big that deck could be
and I'll leave that for you because it's
sort of a fun counting exercise but what
I really want to talk about today is
well what's you know I mean what's if if
we know if we have some deck size that's
not bigger than the Mac then the upper
bound how is it possible to find a
strategy or you know how many strategies
are there so on and so forth so given
equal to the lower bound or the upper
bound rather is their strategy it works
and I guess in theory I mean you could
just ask your computer you know check
all the strategies
is that going to be very efficient how
many strategies are there so
have a deck of size D and we're choosing
end cards out of it so they're there do
choose end possibilities we have two
these as n choose D digits if you will
and choose D possible answers that we
have to find and how many when we have
when we have a particular subset of size
n how many possibility how many possible
things could we choose to show so if we
have given a subset right so give it a
subset of size n how many n minus 1
cards can we show so we have to choose
the N minus 1 cars and then there's n
minus 1 permutations so it's entries n
minus 1 times well times n minus 1
factorial that's the number of
permutations of n minus 1 cards shy is
now hidden in the audience this works
out to be n factorial that's gotten 1
given a subset of end cards there's n
factorial possible things that we can
show to the magician and so how many and
that's not enough to get the other 48
cards that are missing and that's
because she left at the end she's n
minus 1 that she had a choice to make
take those 4 parts at a 5 so truly 122
120 card deck on a 24 card deck but yeah
so so if we have these for each for each
possibility we have n factorial choices
that means that the total number of
strategies and probably a lot of these
are going to be awful and just not work
the D choose n possibilities we've
entered possibilities so 10 factorial
times n factorial times n factorial D
trees n times that make sense does
everyone believe me so that's really big
I wouldn't want to make my computer run
an algorithm friend very much bigger
than four I guess with what not even yes
I mean I guess okay so if we do if we're
I don't want to erase any of this if D
is equal to eight cards and we're
choosing three than n factorial to the
eight choose three well 3 factorial six
to the a choose three is what yeah so
it's big so even checking all the
possible strategies for choosing three
cards from an eight card deck is not
very efficient and so in particular I
mean you really wouldn't want to choose
check all the strategies for choosing
five cards out of 120 card 124 card deck
I mean that just seems like not the best
way of going about this problem all
these Palm Pilots
everybody knows they're getting faster
right so let's make them a billion times
faster and then we get down to ten or
nine years after the nine years a
billion years see how many centuries
that would take until computers were
fast enough for us to actually what
let's imagine is let's say you can do an
operation in the time it took light
is going to improve has some limits as
well I mean it works for the next thirty
years but if you say that okay perhaps
the speed has an absolute limit maybe
there isn't much of a limit to the
number of computers okay so let's say
we'll have a computer on every a
demeanor every atom in the universe will
have a computer and they'll all work
simultaneously it would be hard to
paralyze this computation of course we
realize right because this computation
has to look at everything that was done
before so so the issue of paralyzing it
is just completely hard but let's just
assume by some miracle we can paralyze
it perfectly and every atom had a
computer how many atoms are there in the
universe maybe have a ballpark to the
watch but how if every atom has a
computer then what about the computers
that are on atoms today the atoms that
are in computers today also have
computers are just finding a strategy
perd three cards out of eight
know anything else and I'm done okay so
so let's try and find a strategy for
four seven choose three let's just sort
of see if we can plow ahead and get
stuck or not get stuck or what my stress
yeah my strategy so so here we have
seven cards in our deck so let's suppose
that we have seven cards well that's the
question first we have to figure out how
many suits we want to divide them into
okay so we've a seven card deck we want
to choose three cards okay so there's
two suits I don't know let's call the
low suit in the high suit one two three
and four five six seven nine one two
three four okay
cards in the same suit I guess the
problem is so first we want to put the
suit here we have one card hidden and we
have one more card that can tell us how
high to go and so that's not going to
work I mean there's just no way if we
get well so so the point is if we have
suppose we have 1 & 1 & 3 & 4 & 7 or 1 &
3 & 7 that we chose
oops no I guess it works for that or it
works for so suppose we have supposed to
be at 4 & 6 & 2 that we chose
okay so 4 & 6 are both in the high suit
but well so suppose I want to show 4 5 6
well showing the 2 here is going to say
1 so that's supposed to signify that 5
is hidden not that 6 is hidden and
similarly if we put the 6 here the 6
would signify that or the 2 would
signify that 7 was hidden not that 6 was
hidden right right so so here if we had
4 6 2 4 6 & 2 4 5 both of those that in
both of these cases we would have to put
the 4 here and show the 2 right so we
can't so yeah so strategy is bad if we
have 4 4 2
for two distinct sets of three we have
the same set of two that we're showing
subsets of n you generate the same for
two distinct subsets of n you generate
the same n minus 1 subsets and so if
you're going through your dictionary to
figure out which card is hidden you
can't figure it out because there's two
possibilities any strategy order 2 pairs
to go around that's how you got the
upper bound to begin with right so maybe
we should write that down
figure out how big of a deck can we how
big of a deck will not emit a strategy
size nine so this is what tri claims if
we have a deck of size nine then we
can't possibly make any strategy work so
if we have a deck a size nine there's
nine choose three possible three subsets
and I choose three possible things that
we could be thrown what's nine trees
three nine times 84 okay and there's the
possible things that we can encode
that's the possible ordered pairs of
cards from a nine element set so that's
nine times eight so this is possible
three card subsets and nine times eight
which is 72 is the possible number of
ordered pairs but now by the pigeonhole
principle at least two of these are
going to show up for the same guy over
here which means that it's a bad
strategy or that any strategy would be a
bad strategy so
simular a similar argument for I mean
this this is sort of how you can find
your upper bound for any size n/4 for
your deck size so you figure out for
which size of the deck is is the number
of n card subsets bigger than the number
of n minus 1 ordered subsets
big but a deck of seven I claim isn't
too big
if we compare set 7 choose 3 to 7 times
6 well 7 choose 3 is bigger than 7 times
6 so whoops no the other way around
sometimes 6 is bigger than 7 choose 3 so
7 cards work so let's and we know that
our original strategy didn't work for 7
cards so let's just sort of brute force
try and write down a strategy that we
think is going to work so what I have to
do is for each I've carefully beforehand
written down all my three card subsets
so now we have to figure out which 2
card which ordered pair we're going to
associate to the hidden third card for
each three card subsets we just I mean
essentially what we have to do is write
down a dictionary that you know the I
get handed a three card subset I showed
I I look it up in my dictionary and then
I put two of them down and then try
picks up his dictionary and he goes
through and looks at the two cards and
finds the the third hidden card so right
so it has to be a 1:1 function
yeah with 124 choose five it's got to be
on two right so okay so wants to be the
spokesperson for the class what should
we use for the strategy for one two
three which card I didn't just like
choosing the first okay okay wanna
change it and now if you put two one in
the next place okay so now now we can't
use one two or 2 1 here so let's try to
5 only hide 1 okay so now you would go
ahead and find the next possible place
that you can fit five two oh gee so here
right Wow so Chris is Chris's method was
to now go up to 2 3 5 and put the 5 to
here because that's the next possible
spot that we could fit that we could
choose a 5 and a 2 out so here we'd put
5 to unhide the 3
there's a lot of leeway here I mean
let's just sort of go blindly through so
let's say two six means one two seven
means one okay
so we're okay now here with two three
four let's see so we've already done
three four is taken two three is not
taken use for three Oh
okay so let's use four three okay so
four two three six let's see two threes
not taken so let's use that now for two
three seven two three is taken three
twos not taken so let's use that okay so
four two four five two four is taken no
it's not good let's use two four four
two four six four twos not taken excuse
for two okay so now for two four seven
let's see two for is taken in for two is
taken to seven is taken but four seven
and four sevens taken but two two sevens
taken at 72 is not taken another 74 so
let's use seven two
5 & 2 6 are both taken 5 6 is taken 5 2
is not taken 5 2 taken oh geez
why she's taken a face of 6 5 is not
taken okay so 2 5 7 let's see two fives
taken two seven is taken five seven is
taken two seven five is not taken
2 6 2 7 & 6 7 7 6 is not taken okay so
now we go to our third row 3 4 5 let's
see 3 4 3 5 are taken 4 or 5 is taken
five fours that taken no I'm gonna be
really shocked if this works 3 4 6 so
let's see 3 4 is taken 3 6 is taken 4 6
is taken 6 4 is taken no three four
seven seven three seven three is not
taken three five six three five and
three six or taken five six is taken six
three is not taken good three five and
seven let's see five three is not taken
seven threes all right seven three right
seven three is taken five three five
threes okay five threes not okay where's
five three five threes not there
three is taken seven three is taken how
about seven six that's taken two and so
are three six and three seven and six
seven so now we're stuck so we'd have to
go back yeah I mean that's what we could
do we could go through and continue in a
moment we're only four away let's sort
of forget this one for right now oh one
six wasn't taken you okay okay so I put
one six I mean the problem is the
problem is you can't tell your computer
too well if it screws up then just go
back and find I mean right now you'd
have to write a good program that knows
what the best one is to kind of switch
instead of just kind of looking at it
intuitively and saying oh I can see that
would be three and it would help me here
and if you're going to have your
computer just go back to the last case
and try the next possibility instead of
the one and just backtrack the worst
case that happens let's say none of
these strategies were once they were
actually really dead here then the worst
thing that happens is you run through
every single strategy in your
backtracking and you finally report none
of them work and if you do that for this
three seven case even this is centuries
but if we try every strategy here so so
we have to hope to get lucky in doing
this the brute force way and we have to
hope that we don't have to backtrack
hardly at all and if we do it's just
very briefly and there's a million
different ways to write your program
because none of them were really work
they're just hoping for a lucky break
here so so this is really an engineering
kind of kind of experiment rather than
an algorithm to solve this thing I mean
I guess the answer is is that at least I
don't know and try doesn't know for what
values there are solutions
I mean so this is really so I'm
open-ended question it's hard well maybe
it's not hard but it seems hard to us
dictionary the other direction that
might be easier yeah so how they're
suggesting why don't you start with the
pairs and and generate your triples that
way right right exactly yeah so let's
try and finish this okay so we we took
away six seven so now we can put six
seven here okay so four five six let's
see yeah okay so now I want to put four
six here okay four five seven or any of
those not taking probably not okay so
see let's change this to 1 5 meaning 7
and then we can still use 5 7 yep
see we should be able to change it with
one five six lips to use one six I guess
we've used one six six one oh six one
right and now we can use five six here
this that works here right memorize the
question is is there well my question is
the sky's question is you know how often
can you find a strategy is it possible
to find a strategy that works is it
possible to find a nice way of
enumerated strategy my question is how
many strategies are there I mean what's
the probability that we just brute-force
hit upon a strategy when we just go
through I mean total number of
strategies is this how many of them are
good so I guess you could figure that
out I mean that's harder 52 cards and
you're trying to say get it to work for
60 you know instead of 52 that so many
of the strategies that you pet will work
that if you just go ahead and enumerate
them in any kind of an order you're
going to get really lucky and not have
to look through even the tiniest
fraction of this huge intractable
universe because what Tyra said if you
just want a random you'd probably get
lucky I can be interesting to just pick
a strategy completely abandon them and
do it a million times and calculate
what's the chance of you getting one you
probably the chance of you getting one
is pretty good so just pick one at
random and try it which is basically
what I want you to try to do so so
hopefully we can get some answers and
see how high we can go so you want to
talk about Sean's wipes yeah so so
came up with right it's it's really nice
so she has a nice strategy which is
essentially it says so her strategy is
for each if you're given if you're given
this set of three that you want to code
that you want to encode first write down
all the permutations in Reverse the
lexicographic order so that means well
fortunately have letters that means okay
first we write down CBA then C a B then
let C be ca B AC then a c b a b c so
this is sort of the reverse dictionary
order and I guess the alphabet for 1 2 3
4 5 6 7 8 9 is just 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
okay so first write down all the end
factorial permutations of your your guy
and then try to encode using this right
so try to hide the so go through go
through through your permutations in
this order and try to hide the first one
and show the second two and see if that
works see if that's already been hit by
or see if the if the second 2 has
already been shown by your strategy
before or not and if it does if it has
been then move on to the next one and
try and use a B to encode C and then try
and use CA to encode B and so forth so
written down the six permutations in
Reverse dictionary order and so the
first ones I see what you're talking
about but how did hell are you saying
this EAB is reversed dictionary they're
not internally reverse order the if I
have six words namely C BAC a BBC a BAC
a CB and ABC and in the dictionary they
would occur in the order ABC ACB be a
CBC a CIA CBA okay and so when I turn
that upside down right okay okay yeah so
kuvasz first let's try her suggestion
and so far you've never had the
backtrack right if there was one you
found it yeah 237 she was full we did
the highest four four four cards so this
kind of strategy without backtracking
for the maximum you can hope for for
choosing four cards and now so now the
question is what happens four five cards
elizabeth i mean--can it right like what
if we could prove that her way of
generating always got a strategy that
works without backtracking if we could
prove that then it would be a real
algorithm we wouldn't just be lucky it
would be a constructive kind of an
algorithm and we know that you could
always get the maximum value our upper
bound and this problem would be solved
and nobody would ever look at it again
but I think that that that's really kind
of a lot to hope for to prove that I
think we're just kind of lucky so far
and if you need to see why it's really
working but nobody knows so let's yeah
so it's yes one means a B encoding C
this one means C a and coding fee this
one means a C and coding B this means C
B encoding a and B C encoding a so the
reason Tom's wife the reason Russian e I
think chose reversed lexicographic order
is that this right I mean she's not here
well she if this distance learning we're
working maybe we could dial her up and
ask her right that is is that here in
this first column we really want to use
a lot of the ones I mean earlier when we
well of course in the strategy I just
erased
we had to backtrack and we we tried to
use a lot of the things that had one
like we would use a one we we wanted
ones to occur a lot here because there's
no ones over here and so we want to use
up the pairs that have ones in the first
column and so this sort of maximizes
that this uses the ABS and the A's a lot
first and so you know the using the
reverse lexicographic order has
something to do with the fact that we've
written down our numbers here in
lexicographic order right but there's a
lot more C's over here well there's a
lot more five six seven s over here and
a lot more ones over here so really we'd
like to use the fact that there's ones
over here rather than just sort of go
blindly along sure you could do that and
then start at the end and that would
work just as well okay
right
very quickly you end up hiding
combinations of two threes and two fives
and many of you hide three sets of them
and then you automatically guarantee
that there's two ways to go back to a
one yeah so so the problem is is if we
if we put both of these in lexicographic
order in alphabetical order then what's
going to happen is we're going to hide
one an awful lot over here we're going
to show an awful lot of two threes two
fours four twos four fives and then when
we get over here to something that has a
two four and five in it we're going to
have already used up all the
possibilities and so we would have to
backtrack so it just turns out you know
no one's proved anything yet we haven't
proven that this is the most efficient
way to do it
but in the examples that Shaun has seen
this seems to be the nice way to do it
do that so Todd suggested why don't we
just prove that there's only one
possible strategy for for the maximal
size deck and if we could do that and
strums and Chum strategy works then we'd
have a nice there a nicer and even nicer
theorem yeah but I don't think we're any
closer to proving that than we aren't
throwing anything
the the first thing there's going to be
CBA well that works because we haven't
run out of anything yet
so we encode two one and codes three so
everyone see how I got that so now I
come to a four to one and I want that's
well four to one is the first thing but
I've already used two one
so I next come to four one two so I use
one two to encode for and run out on
your very first shot it says that you'll
get it on one of your first six tries
strategies n factorial to the D choose n
if we look at the total number of
strategies there are using this
algorithm well at each of the N choose
guys you have n factorial things to look
at now you don't backtrack see yes d
choose n times n factorial usually
doesn't look convinced so is anyone else
not convinced
times 56 rather than 6 to the 56 yeah
right what number would this that's like
Carl Sagan as many stars as there are
quickly go back into the twilight zone
right I mean the minute n gets up to
five or six I mean the point is is we
still have an N factorial there right I
mean checking all these strategies is
still not the smartest way to go because
checking I mean n factorial we know
that's n to the N and this is d choose n
times n factorial and so this I mean
this still is not going to be checking
all these slick strategies it's still
not going to be an efficient way to
solve this problem
it may be the best way that we know of
right now but it's not Fisher
right right I guess what is this for one
hundred twenty four and five
anyone
rather 124 times 123 times 120 times 121
right drive to multiply 100 times
hundred twenty wait well two seven zero
one eight hundred this is the number of
things we have to check for 124 cards
choose five so the number of slick
strategies is a lot yeah
27 trillion that's not so bad 27
yeah 27 trillion no billion billion 27
billions that's most about that's 27
seconds according to shiz yeah so okay
anyway what's off finish filling this
out so we can't choose to one or one to
here so we choose to five no five one
and here I guess we choose six one
you name it you could do this I mean you
could sit here and do this if you were
not as tired as I am maybe yeah are
there any questions about how the
strategy works or how I mean what the
strategy is I mean why does it work if
you can answer why it works then great
you know you can prove our conjecture
maybe that's the only shred does anyone
else have a strategy not in the ways
that I've tried it so far ok so I
haven't tried to dis extensively the
show so your strategy was actually not
to go in Reverse or you actually go into
forward order but anytime you get one
you look for a place where the where the
flip may be use to generalize my
algorithm it would be to list all of the
ordered pairs and drop the ordered pairs
in the first place they fit right and
that's that's more or less what heather
was thinking yeah yeah right the first
place where they belong right and then
and then if it's already filled go to
the next possible point right yeah and
if that never gets up to a situation
where you can't put with it and you have
to pick them all up and start again
right right that actually that seems
like a good strategy to so our second
strategy is look at all the ordered
pairs I don't know I'm just gonna write
that down and figure it out
Lassalle order pairs and I guess we list
them in lexicographic order right the
first two would star pack words they're
not going to be the strain strategy
definitely not going to be the same
strategies because these strategies I
guess we list all the ordered pairs in
lexicographic order right we list 1 2 2
1 1 3 3 1 what
oh you list them that way you don't even
do this 1 2 1 3 oh yeah that that's how
I did it when I did it by hand and I
think that that is analogous to doing it
this way yeah I'm not sure that it is so
here we get 1 2 here we've got 1 3 1 4
don't know this doesn't mean this is
very different from chums so oh the okay
so but maybe that gives us two different
strategies in fact in fact if you if you
if you have a strategy then you can
reverse all your pairs and you'll still
have another strategy right okay so so
there's at least two strategies yeah
equivalence relation an equivalence
relation in this case would be flip all
pairs in fact any so if you if you have
a strategy for end cards out of a deep
card deck then you're going to have
another equivalence relation namely
permute use the same permutation to
permute your strategy all the way along
that's going to give you a new strategy
and so we have an equivalence class
again we have an equivalence relation
where two strategies are equivalent if
you can permute all the use the same
permutation to permute all the answers
and all the dictionary entries or
whatever you want to call them so you
look confused should I say that again so
if we well so one thing we've just
noticed is that switching
want these to be the same yeah that's
right so in general if we have so if we
have this as our thing that we want to
encode and so what we do is we say a b c
d e and we encode this to be f so we
have now we're choosing 1 2 3 4 5 6
cards if we choose a permutation of 5
cards so fix one permutation then if we
apply that permutation so say our
permutation is switch the first two then
if we switch the first two of each of
our five card entries in our dictionary
then that's going to be a different
strategy it's going to be somehow we
want to call that equivalent to the
first one and so applying this
equivalent so any size deck to six cards
yeah in general it will be if we choose
end cards fix the permutation of n minus
1 cards blah-blah-blah-blah-blah this
will give a new permutation of each and
or this will give a new strategy and we
should call these equivalent so in this
case we'll get equivalence classes of
strategies the equivalence classes will
be the n minus 1 factorial permutations
applied to some given strategy we can
probably well we'd have to somehow
choose one of them to be the least but
we don't want to think about that okay
class of strategies maybe there's who
knows how many write of successful
strategies yeah right right I mean I
guess the hope is is that when you have
the maximal size deck there's one one
equivalence class of good strategies but
that's even not clear to me I sort of
suspect that they're right I think my
gut instinct is that when you have the
maximal size set there should just be
one equivalence class of strategies yeah
but that would making a nice paper right
yeah right yeah yeah so this is nice
the the moral of today's recitation I
guess is that this is hard I mean this
is sort of unknown like we don't know
what the answer is and so that you know
this is what math is sort of about this
is what research in any field is sort of
about you have some question you don't
know the answer and you just plug away
and you program in a computer to test a
few cases and and you say oh look the
strategy seems to work now let's prove
it and of course then you have no idea
where you're how you're supposed to
prove it but that's the moral of the
story so are there any questions any