generalized compliment principle to
using inclusion/exclusion is kind of a
solve problems that otherwise would
defeat us and then talk about the
pigeonhole principle is a completely
separate principle it really is on its
own it sometimes gets connected up with
other discrete ideas but sometimes it
doesn't and I'm going to go through
examples of the pigeonhole principle
starting from the most trivial to some
of the more subtle and that'll be a
separate topic about a half-hour at the
end of today's lecture well hopefully
we'll be able to finish with that so
what I want to do now to begin my intro
to inclusion/exclusion is go back to
Chris's question and yesterday Chris
said yesterday we talked about putting
distinct objects into distinct boxes it
was this kind of a problem let's say we
have five dollar bills and each one we
can buy a cookie and there's two types
of cookies to buy so we want to
distribute our $5 bills into either
cookie box one or cookie box two this is
equivalent remember to let's repeatedly
select five cookies from two types same
problem distribute 5 single dollars into
two distinct boxes cookie one cookie two
or choose as five cookies from two types
of cookies same problem here's another
way to look at it I have two numbers X +
1 X 1 and X 2 and I want these to equal
5 okay this will be cookie 1 this will
be cookie - so how many solutions are
there to this equation yeah Rob no I'm
not going to build up to that
already nine this thing I said it wrong
thanks right now I got to go back and
make sure I said it right or wrong sorry
this is distributing non distinct
objects the dollar bills in two distinct
boxes the same as selecting with
repetition this many items from this
many types thank you
I said it wrong no I said it right there
is distinct into this thing but that was
before that was a generalized
permutation that's not this okay
questions right it's also the same as
the number of solutions to this equation
choose a number for cookie one choose a
number for cookie two they have to add
up to five and we saw this yesterday
this is not new we did this and we
showed that what we're really doing here
is taking taking five dollar bills and
dividing them into into two parts right
and to do that to divide them into two
parts we put a little squiggle sign and
thats wiggle sign could go anywhere here
here here here here here and I think
that's what made Chris ask the next
question now I'm going to change this
there's three kinds of cookies so now we
get two squiggles okay and I'm going to
write down all the different ways I can
do this there's ten of them so I got
here my three dollars and I'm going to
divide these into three different parts
here's the first way I can divide them
that means zero zero three okay here's
the next way
way ok those are 4 ways there's more
let's write a few more down I'm doing
this in a very particular order I'm
starting with them both at the left and
then I move the right one over one at a
time and then when I use all those up
I'm moving the left one over one and
then I'm moving the right one over one
at a time so what's left
squiggle xxx
squiggle squiggle it's the discrete math
dance that Jeff Radcliffe was doing
you are understanding something thank
you
how many altogether 10 we worked this
through yesterday it's three dollars
that means three x's three different
cookies so we're going to buy these into
three different areas that means we need
two squiggles to divide it up into three
different areas so it's 3 plus 3 minus 1
choose and then we get to decide where
we want to put these two squiggles 5
places where are you going to put the 2
squiggles we can put them in the first 2
1 & 3 1 & 4 1 & 5 it's 5 choose 2
minus 1 choose the number of cookies
minus one okay this is what we did
yesterday this is review other questions
about it Teresa because this represents
having none of the first cookie none of
the second cookie in three of the last
cookie right right it shows that there
are none in the second category and this
represents one of the first cookie
none of the second cookie two of the
third cookie and actually that's going
to get right into Chris's question and
we'll get in a second yeah Gary no it's
not coincidence at all I mean it's this
is this is something choose to so
something choose to you know as always
triangle numbers it's the first one with
all the rest that's four okay and then
you can't use that one again so it's the
next one which there's three choices
with all the rest and then two and then
one
so it's not coincidental no it's
completely because of that all right so
the answer is 10 here but Chris asked
this question you said look it seems to
me that you know say you have like eight
of these dollar bills 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
and if you want to divide these into
into three parts you really just want to
insert a divider into one of nine places
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 right and if you want
to insert 2 in there then it's 9 choose
2 here's one here's the other one
there's only 9 places you can put it and
then he said oh and I'll handle this
situation where you have these two
together I'll just you know Sal put them
on top of each other
alright so Chris said how come that
isn't a good way to do it and the truth
is it is a fine way to do it but if you
count how many ways there are for Chris
to do that it turns out also to be 10
choose 2 and not 9 choose 2 and that
specifically because when he says let's
double them up that adds possibilities
that he already has not counted yet we
already has counted yet let me show you
let's look at this and convert each of
these two to Chris's notation so I'll
check the ones that looks exactly like
the way Chris would do it or I'll Circle
that this one
these look exactly like the way Chris
would write them they're exactly the
same as the way I wrote mine the ones
that look different are these
now if Chris is choosing two spots out
of how many spots are in here 1 2 3 1 2
1 2 3 4 4 choose 2 he's got 6 different
ways of choosing those 2 spots and here
they are these are all of Chris's
possibilities if he counts 4 choose 2 so
all of these where he counts this and
puts them double our situations that
have to be added and counted separately
so what Chris is really saying to do
he's saying I want to count it this way
and I'm saying that's fine Chris but
then you have to do call this n you have
to do n minus 1 choose 2 plus n and
that's the same as just n choose 2 does
that make sense ok right and what's and
you would see this even more if you had
more more dividers with more dividers
suddenly there's a lot more that you've
missed or that you've that you have
encountered or that you've counted twice
in some way because these wouldn't be in
yours at all and you'd have to add in a
lot more wouldn't just be a need be
adding you to be adding more of an N
squared calculation so if you counted it
your way the calculation would be much
more complicated but you could get the
right answer and it's probably better
just to think of it this way and that's
why everybody thinks of it this way is
that good all right so this is going to
lead us to the next question here's the
same kind of problem you got three
different cookie jars and you want to
buy a bunch of cookies each one cost a
buck and you have eight dollars so you
want to take your eight dollars and
split them into three different
categories but well let's solve it first
let's solve it if we don't have any
constraints what would the answer be
that's ten choose two there are ten
choose two is 10 times 9 divided by 2 45
different ways of filling in these X's 8
plus 3 minus 1 that's 10 choose 2 you
have 8 X's 2 squiggles how many
different ways are there to put those
squiggles in the 10 places this may be
but now I've added these two constraints
this does not make the problem much
harder let's think about it if I added
these two constraints so it looks like
this X 1 X 2 X 3 and I insist that X 1
has to have at least 3 dollars in it
okay so here's the dollar bill and
here's a dollar bill and here's the
dollar bill and X 3 has to have at least
one dollar in it here's a dollar bill if
I insist on these constraints then I
start my problem out looking like this
and now the question is how many ways
are there to finish up well now I only
have four dollars
I have no restriction at all on my x1 x2
x3 just like I had in my original
problem so I have four dollars and three
categories so it's going to be this new
problem without any constraints the
constraints are now gone when you get
constraints like this that X eyes have
to be bigger than some number it hardly
affects the problem at all you just add
up these numbers take them away from
your total and do the problem with a new
total so what would the answer be would
be 4 plus 2 which is sex choose to and
that is both 15 6 times 5 divided by 2
what order you put these dollar bills in
you just because they're all
indistinguishable so we only care how
big x one is at the end so if X 1 has to
start out at 3 and X 3 has to start out
at 1 the question is okay that's fixed
well what can I do from here and if I
did care about the order of the dollar
bills then I have to do some counting
before I started how many possible
different ways can you give a number to
X 1 X 2 and X 3 so that they add up to 8
could erase these and just change that
number to 4 and then write that's harder
no no we're gonna do something that's
kind of just what Rob asked a second ago
and he said what happens if it's less
than something we're gonna do examples
of these it's very hard to count
directly how many ways there are to find
values for X 1 X 2 and X 3 which equal 8
when X 1 has to have less than 3 here's
one way to do it we can just divide it
up into cases if X 1 is less than 3 then
X 1 could be 0 X 1 could be 1 and X 1
could be 2 well if X 1 is 0 then we have
a problem of two variables equaling 8
and you can do that how many ways are
there to split to vary
Bulls T equal eight you can do that in
your head actually without even using
the formula there's nine different ways
right and how many different ways are
there this is the addition rule right
because these are in completely disjoint
cases if X is 1 then there are how many
for the other two
X 3 having equal 7 so they're 8 right
and then this one would be 7 so the
answer to this you can do in this direct
way 17 + 7 is 24 but there's another way
you can do it and this other way you can
do it is going to work for more
difficult problems and it's the
complement way instead of looking at X 1
less than 3 we're going to look at
things where X 1 is not less than 3
right when it's greater than or equal to
3 and they'll just take those away from
from the total number of solutions well
the total number of solutions we know is
10 choose 2 how many solutions are there
where X 1 is bigger than or equal to 3
we just did that before if X 1 is bigger
than or equal to 3 then this turns down
to 5 right and we get 7 choose 2 and
that's the answer and that better be 24
this is 45 and this is 21 so it's the
same two different ways of solving the
problem two different principles yeah my
friends and I call that a brain fart yes
you can still speak it's ok then excuse
me for a brain fart
solutions to this original problem and
these are the solutions where X 1 is
bigger than or equal to 3 so when you
subtract you get the solutions to X 1
less than 3 we did the problem like this
before we did base 10 numbers that have
at least one zero how do we do that how
do we
do based on numbers that have at least
one zero we did yeah Robert exactly
right we said that here are all the base
10 numbers let's subtract off all the
base 10 numbers that don't have any
zeros in them the remainder will be the
ones that have at least one zero in them
how many base that numbers don't have
any zeros in them
it's like base nine numbers and that's
what we got that's when you just want to
exclude no zeros that's when you want to
have things that have at least one zero
but now I've made it harder now I want
numbers that I've at least the zero and
at least the one why can't I just go
ahead and say okay well I took off all
the ones with zeros and now I'm going to
take off all the ones with no one why is
that wrong right because they overlap
this is an important idea
that's why inclusion exclusion theorem
comes into play because the normal
complement has no overlap but sometimes
complements overlap and when they do
that's when you have to use inclusion
exclusion so let me present this now
from scratch as an inclusion exclusion
problem we're going to solve this by
doing all base 10 numbers - - the ones
that have at least a 0 and at least a 1
there so I meant I'm going to make all
base 10 numbers - those that are not the
ones that have at least one zero and at
least one ones that's the same as this
top is the copper well if you can
describe to me the compliment of these
than I could have written that down but
it's not just the ones that have that
have no zeros or let's see what it is
this equals all base 10 numbers you all
know this you can all just do it
logically but remember this from set
theory a intersect B complement equals
what not a union not B so now I'm going
to rewrite that not the first one this
and is intersection so not the first one
which means it doesn't have at least one
zero that means it has no zeros okay so
no zeros or Union or no once I did that
just to remind you that set theory isn't
a complete waste of time I mean you does
come up it just comes up unconsciously
sometimes we're taking away the
complement of this the complement of
this turns an intersection into a union
the reason I'm doing this slowly also is
to force you to see that you have to use
inclusion exclusion inclusion exclusion
is a way to count things that are Union
together it's a way to count things that
are this or this or this or this that's
when you get the overlaps
here's inclusion exclusion for two
things if you want to count the union of
two sets it's the size of the first plus
the size of the second minus the size of
their intersection let's use that
theorem over here
base 10 numbers have no zeros 9 to the
end how many base 10 numbers have no
ones 9 to the N how many base 10 numbers
have no zeros and no one's a intersect B
this and this that's the overlap that's
the part we counted twice that we need
to subtract off a to the N right no
zeros or ones means you only have eight
symbols left that's the right answer a
things are in here or is Union and is
intersection right well again like last
time we could split this up into cases
the cases where you know we have two A's
and choosing them first then you could
do this directly but we're going to do
it indirectly using the inclusion
exclusion we're going to get the total
solutions which is what we just
mentioned and subtract from them the
complement of our constraint
going to be its permutations of these
letters which which do have right and
that means if they do the three that go
together could either be a or B or C and
that's where the inclusion exclusion
comes in anytime you use a compliment
trick which gives you a union of
possibilities that's when you have to go
back and resort to inclusion exclusion
to finish your idea so I'm going to
write down three A's Union three B's
Union three C's and make a note to
yourself because if you look at it later
you'll forget what this means this means
all strings that have three consecutive
A's in them this means all strings that
have three consecutive B's in them all
strings that have three consecutive
season them
a B C minus a intersect B intersect C a
intersect B intersect C thank you plus
feel free to completely argue with my
choice here but would you rather right
now have been taught the
inclusion/exclusion theorem for the very
first time and then after that side 45
minutes come back to this or would you
have rather already known this when you
saw set theory and then just have me do
it now because I thought it's better to
do it before right now you see now right
all right so this Anthony asks is the
beginning goes well you know this is a
really good book and I agree and you're
like why don't you just like go in the
order well I think his choice here just
stinks I think it's just the bad choice
I think he really should have done
inclusion/exclusion in the set theory
chapter and maybe in addition v if
enough people telling that he'll move
that section over there
but there's lots of situations here
where just isn't obvious where to put
the section and I think here it doesn't
belong so much in counting as much as it
belongs back in set theory and then you
just refer to it again let's figure this
out
no no I took the compliment of this I
skipped this step I took the compliment
in my head and just wrote this down it's
it's minus the complement of the things
without three consecutive same letters
that complement is the things with three
consecutive same letters okay so I just
did that step without writing it down
you okay well let's do this piece by
piece let's take this just this part
here and break it up into pieces the
first piece is the number of things just
in this set the things with three A's
how many are there six remember what
this means this means there's different
there's six different ways to order
three A's but that's not what this is
measuring this is measuring how many
strings are there that have that have
three consecutive A's in them what does
that mean
then why don't we glue them together
just like Baruch was saying right let's
think of them as one so how many items
do we have now if we move around seven
and what are the different types three
three and one good isn't it nice to have
some tools to have some ABCs we wouldn't
have known that this was helpful if we
didn't know how to do problems like that
but we know so we can continue to the
next step three B's is similar and three
C's is similar so it's just going to be
three of these I've taken care of this
part now let's take care of the next
part 3 a's and 3 B's that means I have
only five objects one a chunk of a is
one a chunk of B's and then three
distinct C's that can move around so I'm
going to take five objects and the
different types are 3 factorial 1 and 1
and I have 3 of those possibilities 1 2
3 three different pairs of things that
go together finally plus if they all
have to be that means there's three
possibilities there's one of each type
and then B and C AC B B it's like how do
you what are the permutations of three
elements exact same thing okay right
good
well I don't know what did I do the
answer here no no but I did I write I
didn't write the answer down in this
problem so I have no idea what this
turns out to be but this is the right
answer you do this you subtract off all
of this keep them
that this is equivalent to this
bracketed part okay that's not the whole
thing here that's just a part after the
minus sign so the minus will have to go
through that right and you're going to
end up subtracting this adding this and
subtracting that remember in this
problem when you have the less than
criteria it's hard to count if I want to
find out the number of solutions to this
equation
when each of these has to be less than
one two and three respectively that's a
tricky problem so we're going to do it
by complement we'll take all the
solutions to this which we know again is
ten choose to the total number of
solution is 10 choose two we want to
subtract from that the solutions that
don't have this criterion the complement
of these now this is supposed to meet
Ann's right this and this and this so if
I complement it
I get what reverse it so x1 is bigger
than not greater than or equal but
strictly bigger than 1 or X 2 is
strictly bigger than 2 or x3 is strictly
bigger than 3 this is again from the
Morgan's law if I run a knot through
here all the conditions change parity
and the ends changed into ORS but now
I've got a set of conditions that have
ORS between them so to count those up I
need the inclusion exclusion theorem and
that's what we're going to do okay so
far okay good let's work with this piece
let's do the a and the B in the C part
first how many solutions to this have X
1 strictly bigger than 1 remembers how
to do that if it's strictly bigger than
1 that means it has to be at least at
least 2 right so if there's 2 in there
that means there's only six left here
that you have to get so it's 6 plus
bigger than two what's that going to be
x3 bigger than three is going to be six
choose two now let's do this double
cases what about when X has to be bigger
than 1 and X 2 has to be bigger than 2
that means x1 has to be at least 2 and
x2 us to be at least 3 that means I have
how many left I have 3 left here so it's
3 plus 2 choose 2 so it's 5 choose 2
right - what's the next one - 3 that's 3
choose 2 good you guys are doing this
fast on your heads it's not obvious and
now finally we have the case where they
all have to be what's that going to be 4
3 8 8 leaves 0 4 3 2 9 right so that
leaves negative so this is just a 0 make
this a 0 everybody agree there's no way
to add up positive numbers to add up to
negative 1
agree I agree I agree there's something
really fishy about this all right so so
now that I can see what I actually did
what I actually did in all of these is
that you see these equal signs here they
really met they really should have been
strictly and these should have been
equals and then I don't think I get this
problem because that's the problem I
really worked out in my notes so I
didn't work this problem out in my notes
and I'm not sure if it's going to work
out evenly or not I did work out the
problem where these are equal signs and
these are strict signs if I switch them
it just changes the numbers by one is
messed up well I mean I think it's okay
I mean it means something how many ways
are there how many solutions to this
equation are there that have all three
of these being true and the answer is
there aren't any so oh no we still have
all these I mean I'm not sure that I
way to get right right but but we just
got no solution to this sub-problem we
still don't know that the whole thing is
going to agree yet I agree I agree a lot
of them would turn out to be zero let's
go ahead and check this I'm not sure if
it works out or not it does work out to
zero so 10 choose 2 is going to be 45 -
what's this read them off -
hope to god that turns out to be 0 it is
at 0 woohoo
there are 1 for the inclusion exclusion
theorem so this is a perfectly fine way
and a perfectly stupid way of doing this
problem if I gave me this problem on the
exam and you said oh that's an inclusion
exclusion problem you just spent 20
minutes like I just did doing it then
you got your brain turned off it's true
you should just look at this like Berto
said and said there's no way to do it
and you should but I don't I think it's
still completely reasonable and
worthwhile thing to work through this
and see that it still works and gives
you the right answer even it gives even
if it gives you it in a convoluted way
and I will change my notes next time I
probably do 3 4 5 rather than 1 2 3 or
maybe not I'm not sure if this is a good
way to do it or not but I think it's
worthwhile it still works there's
nothing wrong with what we did we just
get an answer the slow way instead of a
fast way you all come in with lunches
you give me all your lunch as I put them
in a box I hand it back out I'm not
malicious I hand them back out in a
random way what's the chance all of you
get somebody else's lunch that nobody
gets their own lunch back ok that's the
question sometimes written down as the
hatcheck problem everybody checks their
hats they're giving back randomly by a
clueless hat check person and what's the
chance to get your own hat back what's
the chance nobody gets their own hat
back yeah no everybody gets this one
lunch back except if it's their own then
that counts as a non derangement but if
it's not their own if everybody doesn't
get their own it's a derangement ok so
there are n factorial ways of me giving
back the lunches it's just the way of
ordering the lunches in a row and having
you come and pick them up n factorial
ways the question is how many of them
are derangements how many of them don't
give you back and the one you want and
we're going to solve this by complim
I'm going to subtract off the ones that
are not derangement well which ones are
not the arrangements describe them to me
in English what makes a permutation
Anand arrangement at least one person
gets their lunch back so it could be how
do you want to divide these up into
cases let's divide it up into unions of
cases there's lots of ways to do it
here's a bad way one person gets their
lunch back two people get their lunch
back three people get their lunch back
exactly one exactly two exactly three
you all exactly get your lunch back I
can count some of those the chance of
you all getting your lunches back is one
the chance of one of you getting your
lunch back well any one of you could be
the one that got their lunch back that's
36 possibilities and then the rest of
you can get your lunches back in anyway
as long as sorry the rest of you could
get your lunches in anyway as long as as
long as you don't get your own but isn't
that the same problem we're solving it's
the arrangements for 35 so either we go
down this route and make a recurrence
equation or we go another route we're
going to go another route okay this
route for the recurrence equation isn't
a bad route and it will teach a lot of
good stuff but it's the wrong week so
this week we're not going to do it
instead we're going to divide up the
cases differently instead of saying one
person gets their lunch back two people
get their lunch back I'm going to divide
it up into Chris gets his lunch back
Sharon gets her lunch back all the
permutations were sharing gets her lunch
back all the permutations we where Chris
gets his lunch back now this thing's
even worse because Sharon can get her
lunch back in permutations were a lot of
you also gets your lunch back so how do
you going to add these up but here we
can get the overlap taken care of by the
inclusion exclusion theorem so let me
write down the categories
usually you like Anne's and here you
don't like ends here ends are hard
you're right
good point to make I don't have any
comment on it really except that it's
true it is really hard right you can't
it's hard to count this directly it
really this really is the only way
people know how to count it easily yeah
all right so let me write this down I'm
trying to figure out the best way to
write it but uh this the this is the
list of things that are not arrangements
so let's say let me list the people as a
p1 to PN those are the people right so
I'll say p1 is fixed that means p1 gets
gets his or her lunch back this means
all the permutations where p1 stays the
same person one gets the lunch bag okay
everyone get that Union or p2 is fixed
or PN the end person is fixed we gotta
add up all the different permutations
where this is true or this is true or
this is true or this is true okay let's
do it
subtract all the intersections oh geez
you can all all the combinations of
pairs plus all the combinations of
triples minus all the combinations etc
etc go look this up in the book it looks
just that ugly it's very hard to
describe the generalized inclusion
exclusion theorem how many permutations
are there where I make sure that Sharon
gets hers back I don't give a hoot about
what everybody else gets back but she
gets back her lunch so I got i got 36
launches I look for hers
okay an apple and a cheese sandwich very
good choice here it is and now I got the
other 35 lunches and I can just toss
them out any way I want how many ways
are there to do that
35 factorial or n minus 1 factorial if I
started with n so this is n minus 1
factorial does everyone agree and so is
that one so how many do I got yeah but
don't simplify things because you lose
the pattern how many ways were there for
me to choose a single person out of you
all
I chose Sheeran at first thought I found
n minus 1 factorial ways but I could
have chosen John and I could have chosen
Donna and I see Jamie and I see that's
not to do romper room so I got n choose
1 that's how many different people I can
choose to fix single people to fix and
each one of those represents n minus 1
factorial permutations plus next row
sorry
- next row now I'm fixing to people and
then I don't care what happens in the
rest of them so I can choose two people
from N and n choose two different ways
and then I get n minus 2 factorial and I
do this over and over again and I hope
you see the pattern yes it means two
specific people are fixed sorry
no it means person two is fixed but I'm
not up to here this isn't this this row
is this it means person 1 and person 2
are fixed person 1 and person three
effects so there's n choose two things
in this row and each one is n minus 2
factorial okay sure everybody gets that
and choose one things in this row and
choose two things in this row and choose
three things in this row the number of
permutations with this criterion or n
minus 2 factorial the number with this
criterion are n minus 3 factorial
because I fixed
people and I have n minus three choices
for the rest of you I keep doing this
until I get to the very last one now the
last one is either plus or minus and I
don't know what it is so it depends what
n is if n is odd it's going to be minus
and if n is even it's going to be plus
so I write minus 1 to the N and what
goes there and choose n times and minus
n factorial there it is and the
factorial minus this mess but this mess
you can simplify with some algebra and
it simplifies to some really really
surprisingly really cool answer and
that's why everybody puts this in books
because it's it's a cool problem that is
a cool answer sometimes you get one not
the other I don't know I don't know
about that piece all right but here's
what happens when you fiddle with us and
you factor it all out what was then
always happens at that particular time
we get here I get n factorial right plus
what do we get here and choose 2 is n
times n minus 1 right times n minus 2
factorial so this is n factorial over 2
factorial
factorial here's what you get and
factorial I missed one somewhere hmm
term at the beginning here I mean no I
don't think I did anything wrong but
something's wrong I hate that well let
me see what I have so far here's what I
have so far
have a 1 here and all the minuses are
going to be shifted over so that would
make this right but I don't know why I
lost my one here in front what did I do
wrong my notes are wrong - so where I
know those cancel I know I know but I'm
supposed to get an in fact an extra n
factorial in here that I lost I don't
know where it went
I'm sorry I goofed it up but where did
it go I mean I should be able to let's
let's figure it out together I hate to
just leave this undone because it's a
nice result looks n factorial is all the
possibilities - the possibilities where
somebody gets their lunch back here the
first person gets their lunch back here
the second person gets their lunch back
right and I don't say anything wrong
with that all right I subtracted it all
right right right I did nothing wrong
sorry
nothing's wrong right
right nothing's wrong I didn't do
anything about I'm so happy
subtracted earlier than I wanted to this
is the number that's the number of
derangements and if I take that this is
the number of non derangements and if I
take it away I get the number of
derangements I think I did it right now
good let's hope all right if you
actually go ahead and calculate this
here's what you come out to get and this
goes back to calculus and I won't go
through the details you can check your
book for this if you take the number of
derangements and you divide by n
factorial that gets rid of this n
factorial in here you get just this
funny-looking fraction and this
funny-looking fraction as n goes to
infinity approaches 1 over E or e to the
minus 1 and you should kind of recognize
why that's the case because of these
because of these 1 over i factorials all
right I'm not going to prove that to you
but you can check your book for the
details of the proof of why it relates
to e I want to do I still have a bunch
to do today and I need to keep you
probably 25 more minutes the the
derangements
okay so if I divide this through by n
factorial I get one minus this it ends
up being the same as one over e for
pigeonholes and five pigeons then one of
the holes has two pigeons in it okay if
I have five cards and four suits two of
those cards are going to be the same
suit okay it's one of the key things in
that problem set in that magic trick
we're going to do problems with the
pigeonhole principle not because it's a
hard principle but because it's
sometimes incredibly deceptive and these
problems are very much on their own they
don't connect back into the other
combinatorics so I leave them in their
own topic but it's just filled with lots
and lots of examples where you know you
think you get the idea and then somebody
shows you a proof that uses nothing but
that idea and you just shake your head
and say how did I ever come up with that
and it's cool to see a simple principle
being milk to its incredible potential
so that's what we'll do here we'll start
with easy ones so I've got one two three
four five six six being the hardest
here's a prove that to people in this
room we're born on the same day of a
month at least two that means one
through 31
you know same we got 36 people in this
room right there's only 31 possible days
there's got to be a duplicate down the
fourth already back same what's the
chance of that that's a different
problem B see only six we're done with
1b prove that to people
in the United States
body we're going for the whole gusto
here
body it's nowhere near 250 million it's
a lot less there's lots of people in the
United States with the same number of
hairs as somebody else that's comforting
right right and I mean we'll have a
little political caucus for all of those
who have exactly eighty nine thousand
four hundred and fifty two hairs in
their body and see if there's anything
in common with those people scary
see alright this is going to get a
little bit harder there's an exam that
goes from zero to a hundred and score
you can get anything from zero to a
hundred if I want to guarantee that
three people will get the same score
I want to guarantee three people with
the same score how many people do I need
to take the test I need to guarantee
three people with the same score this is
a little bit of an extension of the
pigeonhole principle I have a hundred
one possible values that people can get
101 boxes I start throwing people into
these boxes and I'm trying somehow to
guaranteed three people in the same box
to guarantee three people in the same
box I've got to fill in the worst case
two people in each box there's 101 boxes
that makes 202 I can still set up with
nobody getting with no three getting the
same score the second I put in any
number bigger than
people with the same score so how many
people anything bigger than 202 because
we have a hundred and one possible
scores and I can fill them up super
score without having anybody get three
of the same scores and that's two
hundred two people the second I had that
last person one of the holes gets filled
too big okay
now and this is not a hard problem but
doesn't it make you pause longer than
you think you should
it makes me pause longer than I think I
should I mean I get the answer but it
takes me 20 seconds instead of two
seconds these take two seconds so the
next two are going to be even worse next
three 51 houses on the street there are
dresses are between 1,000 inclusive and
1099 okay so every address on the street
is something a thousand a thousand one
up through and including a thousand 99
fifty-one houses on the street prove
there are at least two houses with
consecutive addresses
a thousand and seven and a thousand
eight there's got to be two houses with
consecutive addresses okay so look good
so let me describe how to say that idea
in terms of pigeon holes what are the
holes here the holes here are things
that contain addresses they contain
pairs of addresses there are 50 holes
each contains two consecutive addresses
okay the first pole contains a thousand
a thousand one the next one contains a
thousand two and a thousand three so
I've got holes of consecutive addresses
what am i putting into these holes
houses all right I've got fifty-one
houses I put the houses into these holes
I fill up all 50 of them I got one left
there's got to be two houses in one of
these holes how do I put the houses into
the holes I look at the address of the
house if it's address is labeled on the
whole I put it in there so I've got
fifty-one houses I can put the first 50
into 50 different holes but when I get
that 50 first it's going to have to go
into a hole that already has another
house in there and those two houses that
are in that hole
have their addresses labeled on the hole
and the holes contain consecutive
addresses so those two houses will have
a consecutive addresses there's a lot of
elegance in these arguments because it
doesn't say which two houses have it
just shows you that there exists two
that have to be consecutive this is a
very slick way of taking a problem that
isn't obvious at all how to prove and
turning it into a pigeonhole issue are
there questions about this should I do
this one again what do I mean by a
network that means the
computers are connected to other
computers okay so so imagine that each
of us are a computer and maybe I'm
connected to sharm and and Jakob and
Greg and and Joe's connected to borrow
somewhere else connected to Teresa or
there's connections
okay so n computers on a network we're
connected in some way I'm not telling
you anything about how we're connected
prove that at least two computers are
connected to the same number of other
computers this is also very very
straightforward once you just think
about it for a minute that means if I'm
connected to you and Baruch O'Neill and
Sharon's connected to Chris Peter and
Donna we both connect to three computers
okay how do you know there's at least
two computers in the room that are
connected to the same number of other
computers there's n computers in the
room right how many different possible
computers could we be connected to I
could be connected to one computer I
could be connected to two computers I
could be connected to n minus one
computers every single computer in the
world in in this room could be connected
to n minus one other computers in the
room so I make a bunch of holes each
hole is labeled how many computers are
you connected to how many holes are
there n minus one holes if you're
connected to two computers you go in
this hole if you're connected to n minus
one computers you go in this hole but
there's end computers in our room so
when I throw them into these holes one
of the holes has two computers in it and
those two computers are connected to the
same number of other computers this is
actually from a graph theory question
prove that you have a graph with n nodes
that there are going to be at least two
nodes that have the same degree the same
number of edges connected to it it's
really a graph theory question
yes Brian that's right it assumes right
there are no directed connections here
right this assumes that you just make a
wire and which may not be realistic but
that's the assumption to yourself right
right right and that you're not gonna
know if you well if you allow them then
we don't include that in the in the
number right right we don't count that
exactly all right the next one's the
most clever use this one really is not
at all
apparent unless you think about it and
even after you think about it it's not
too apparent but it's an excellent
example it's I would say there are maybe
a dozen good examples of really
complicated uses of the pigeonhole
principle most of which are more or less
alike this is a canonical version of one
of them okay a lot of them are just like
this if you get this you'll get the rest
of them so this is f this is our last
one and after this I'll take a minute
and summarize and finish up this is what
I call a really clever you screw lever
cooking with gas going down the baloney
trail a computer goes down at least one
time every day okay you got a computer
every single day it goes down at least
once that's given you call it our
network okay during a month a 30-day
month okay only 30 days in a month here
during a month it goes down it goes down
it won't go down any more than 45 times
once a day no more than 45 total during
a thirty day period okay that's all the
information here's what we have to prove
prove that this implies the following it
goes down exactly exactly not at least
but exactly 14 times
about what this is saying for a second
before we go ahead and prove it
the proof is not going to be hard but it
will be hard to find if I don't show it
to you right now let's see what it's
saying it's saying computer goes down
once a day there's no trick it goes down
at most 45 times in a 30 day period
prove that you can find some consecutive
sequence of days and if you add up the
number of times it goes down in that
sequence
that'll be exactly 14 all right so this
is not it is neither obvious nor
unbelievable I mean this doesn't say all
that much it just means it's somewhere
in that 30 day period I can find some
consecutive period of days where if I
add up the number of times that went
down it's 14 we're going to make a
sequence starting from the first day of
the month County how many times this
computers gone down okay so if it's gone
down three times in the first day our
sequence would start with three if it's
gone twice on the second day the next
number and the sequence would be five so
if the number of times it's gone down
say looks like this then our sequence
would be 1 3 6 7 8 10 everyone
understand the sequence that I'm
constructing ok now I don't know
anything about how many times it's gone
down in each day except that each day
it's gone down more than once so I don't
know much about this sequence once or
more so let me tell you what I do know
about this sequence I just described
boom the sequence has how many values in
it how many values in the sequence
thirty values
range the rate the smallest that could
be as one and the biggest that could be
is it's gonna be it could be four it's
good got to be 45 right by the time I
get to the end I better have 45
oh I'm most 45 I think a pack but it
could be 45 at the end what no it's
gotta have at least one at most 35 the
range of any particular I could have
numbers as small as one and numbers as
doing us 45 this is all I can say about
my sequence I know it's got 30 values I
know if you look at each of the values
they could be as small as 1 they could
be as big as 45 and you also know
they're going up let's do a sequence
here's a sequence 1 2 1 2 1 2 1 2 this
is the sequence of how often the
computers have gone down in day 1 2 3 4
5 6 7 8 and here's the sequence that I'm
constructing 1 3 4 6 7 9 the cumulative
sequence is what I'm talking about can
be as small as 1 and can be as big as 45
okay that's all I know so far everybody
with me where are we heading here where
does it go it's almost there I'm gonna
make a new sequence all right
here's the number of times let's write
the sequence that so everybody can see
an example 1
sequence I'm going to add 14 to every
one of these and make a new sequence
what's my new sequence I'm adding 14
each one geez am I in the right place at
such a all right now I've got two
sequences this one's also 30 long right
what is the range in this one 15 - 259
okay
what's the range in all of them
altogether 1 through 59 how many numbers
are in these sequences 60 numbers in the
sequence
I could have motivated this a little
better to make it seem less magical but
I love the magic of this proof the fact
that it just creeps up on you and then
you're done yeah here's one and here's
another and gluing them together at the
end so I got 60 things in my sequence 59
possible values that means that if I
think of the 59 values as holes and
these numbers is things I put into the
holes means two of these numbers have to
be identical I got 16 hours I got 59
values can any of the numbers in this
sequence be identical no because they go
up by one each time right you got to go
down the computer's got to go down once
each day this sequence repeatedly
increases this sequence repeatedly
increases I can't have duplicates in
this sequence I can't have duplicates in
this sequence where is the duplicate
going to have to occur it occurs
somewhere here and somewhere here
presumably further on here we'd have a
15 and it would match this 15 somewhere
in this sequence is
to be a number that's the same as this
sequence what does that mean
that this is the 17th one here is the
number 15 okay and the first one here is
duplicate there that makes all right so
let's you're right that's a bad example
plus 14 equals the Jade day say that's
where the duplicate occurs that means
between the I say and the JPA between
the Jade and the 8th day we have a
number of times the computer's gone down
equal to 14 all right this is a very
very slick proof and comes up out of
nowhere and how do you decide to
construct these weird sequences where
you get 59 different values and 60
possible numbers and just get that
duplicate and that duplicates going to
be 14 apart you know because this
problem is constructed backwards right I
mean you start with this and your work
your way backwards and then you kind of
hide it but it isn't always obvious to
solve a pigeonhole principle problem and
the good news is that they don't come up
as often as the standard combinatorics
problems they come up I'd say one out of
a hundred times rather than ninety-nine
out of a hundred times but when you do
come up there most often not this really
clever really neat way but it's almost
always you got five cards four suits you
got two of the same suit so appreciate
the power of this principle don't think
it's just like nothing but at the same
time be aware that these really clever
ver
they do come up but not as often as the
basic combinatorial things that you'll
have to work with all right so here's
what we'll do in recitation I'm going to
finish up the onto functions I'll have
taro do that we can discuss this proof
if you're interested we can discuss any
of the problems on problem set five I
will today make sure the TAS post
solutions 4 5 & 4 make sure they're up
there and I will make sure that that I
get problem set 6 up there so you can
look at it if you want over the weekend