talk about a problem that Donna asked me
we're going to talk about we're gonna
a few weeks ago that I think is really
interesting and that doesn't appear
anyplace in your book and you can't find
in any of the problem sets so here's a
question let's say you have a set with n
elements I'm going to ask two questions
that I hope everybody does know the
answer to question one how many subsets
are there and question two how many
permutations
this one how many subsets are there
Michael Wright there's two to the N
subset we only have done this in 2 to
the N different ways this semester right
those subsets the number of binary
strings the number of rows in a truth
table etc etc there's a gazillion
different ways of thinking of of the
number of subsets of a set with n
elements and the number is 2 to the N
you're distributing types of 0 or 1 into
n just distinct boxes there's a lot of
different ways of looking at it it's 2
to the N that's true how many
permutations are there n factorial right
whole set permute them all so these are
two of the really basic things that
we've used as building blocks in all the
counting stuff we've done so she asked
me hey so how many ways are there to
choose to choose subsets when you do
care about the order kind of a
combination of these two things this is
just subsets we don't care about the
order that we choose the subsets right
we care about the first one the third
one on the fifth one out of all the N
the first the eighth and the ninth and
the tenth but what if I care about the
order that I choose them in well
obviously it's going to be bigger than
this right what's more it's going to be
bigger than this too because just take
the case where I take the subset of the
whole set the number of ways to order
that
is equal to n factorial so if I
mentioned so I could look at this in a
generalization in two ways or during the
subsets here she is I'm doing your
question that you asked me two weeks ago
now you can wave to the camera
this is Donna's sequence here or you can
look at it this way here's the number of
permutation of all the elements how many
permutations are there if I take some
subset of them okay
we're I can think any subset I want
they're the same question I can either
generalize from here or generalize from
here but it's a generalization of these
two things and it's so natural I mean
it's the most obvious thing I think
someone would think about not to take
anything away from your cleverness
because it's not in the book and it's
not in any of the problem sets so what's
the answer how many ways are there to
order any subset of elements from from a
set of n
idea which is on the right track
let's go through your idea we want to
divide this up into cases Chris is going
to sum up a bunch of cases and that's
the only way that I can see of doing
this why don't we go through the cases
where we have all the elements as a
subset how many ways are there to order
all the elements and factorial okay
that's one end let's go to the other end
I'm not taking any of the elements okay
there's one way if I take none of the
elements right that's called zero
factorial that's one now let's say I
take one element there's one way to
permute one element one factorial but I
can take lots of different elements how
many can I take n or n choose one so I'm
going to write this out actually here
too and choose zero if nobody minds just
to keep things steady and this is going
to be n choose and what's the next one
I'm going to take two elements I can
take two elements in n choose two
different ways and I can order them each
in two factorial ways so I get n choose
two times two factorial X X this is not
such a crazy sequence it's pretty
straightforward and that's the answer
there's right this is the same as P + 0
+ p n1 plus PN - all the way up to P and
n that's right Chris everybody remember
what these this is the permutation of
this many things from n elements this
has taken the combinations and
multiplying through by the thing we
divide it through to get the
combinations in the first place
so it's this sequence it's not such a
bizarre sequence to have added up to
begin with right I mean we have added up
the sequence of CN 0 and CN 1 and you
better remember what that is
CN 0 plus CN 1 plus CN 2 plus that
equals 2 to the N that's all the number
of different ways there are of taking
subsets you take none you take one you
take two you take three you take four
you take n this is the one of the first
things we did and then we spent a lot of
combinatorial identities so why don't
you do this I don't know why it's not in
there I'm somebody must know this and
think that this is just completely
trivial but nobody I asked things so yet
so in the meantime let's look at it so
here's the answer
well this answer is fine I'll call it
what should we call it how many ordered
subsets we'll call it I don't know
cheese I've got a better name than t mr.
t ordered means that I care about the
order so it's like if I have if I have
three elements you know one two counts
two one counts things like that all
right well I don't want to spend too
much time in this I'm gonna do this for
about another five minutes but I just
want to tell you what I've found out
about this and what is true you can
fiddle with us a little bit with the
algebra and here's what happens you can
factor out an N from here to the right
and if you factor out an N from here to
the right here's what happens C of N
equals this part is 1 plus N
out the end and you rearrange the terms
and you can check this yourself what
happens is that all these terms go down
by exactly one value of n so it looks
like this I get it right
you'll get this and if you're wondering
is that really true check it yourself I
think it's really true and you can check
it yourself if you want and if you play
enough with it you'll see that it's true
so what does this tell you it tells you
that T of n equals 1 plus n times T and
minus 1 because this is the same as this
with n minus ones replaced with the ends
ok this is the same as all of this with
n minus 1 place at the end so here's a
recurrence equation is this a linear
homogeneous recurrence equation with
because it doesn't have these constant
coefficients if this were a 2 or a 3 we
could solve it but it's not it's an N
this makes it very hard to solve
nobody knows a closed-form formula for
this as far as I can tell as far as I
know nobody has a simple closed-form
formula but there is a really nice thing
you can do with this because it's very
close to a similar recurrence for
derangements and I want to make this
connection and then show you something
about the T of n here and then we'll let
this go as an interesting problem so
here's the derangement recurrence
equation that I never prove but it's
true we could prove it if I had time and
this was the direction we'd want to go
derangements it's exactly the same as
this one except instead of adding one
sometimes you add one sometimes you
subtract one alternating each time if
you remember here's what we got for D
event we got the d of n equal of n
factorial 1 minus 1 plus 1 over 2
factorial minus 1 over 3 factorial did I
get this right I think this is right
plus 1 over 4 factorial minus 1 over 5
factorial etc
remember we did something like this and
then we proved that that this goes to e
to the minus one right so the number of
derangements was 1 over e times the
total number of n factorials if you do
the same thing in this example and you
factor this thing out you pull out an N
factorial and you're all done here's
what you get C of N equals n factorial
instead of them alternating minuses and
pluses you just get pluses and what is
this equal as n goes to infinity this
equals e naught e to the minus 1 just
regular old e that's from the Taylor
series so that means what happens to the
number of permutations when you allow
taking subsets or what happens to the
number of subsets when you allow taking
permutations you used to have 2 to the N
you had n factorial and when you answer
the third question as n goes to infinity
no closed-form formula for a particular
n but as n gets larger and larger it
ends up being a times n factorial that's
kind of a cool place where each shows up
that if you just go ahead and take all
the subsets and you care about the order
you multiply the number of permutations
by about 2.7 that's as far as I know
anything about this problem there seems
to be a relationship to derangements
were the pluses and minus alternate here
and here they just get pluses but I
don't see any combinatorial connection
I don't see why taking permutations and
caring about when none of them get fixed
has anything to do with taking all the
possible subsets of looking at their
order I'm not sure why those connect and
if they do connect it's a subtle
connection because it's changing these
minuses
it's a pluses but anyhow yeah I mean I
don't want you to feel like when you
when you study all this stuff that it's
all just you know there from day one
like a Bible and you sit and learn it
everybody knows it nobody really knows
as far as I know from my email context
anything about this any more than you
guys know right now and maybe I'll find
somebody who's worked on this and maybe
not but but for what it's worth there
now you know the answer so when you
asked me how many different subsets are
there when you care about the order the
answer is between 2 & 3 times n
factorial alright questions about this
I'm going to switch gears for a second
so this was a little review a question
that Donna came up with and I'm going to
pursue it a little more and see if I can
find somebody who can tell me more about
it
like I said before discrete probability
is 98% counting in two percent
understanding probability so let me fill
in the two percent and then we can go
through some examples if you want to
know the chance of something happening
you can go through all sorts of
mathematical definitions and be very
formal about it and in fact you probably
should at some level but for the
purposes of what we need to do today
it's a very very intuitive kind of idea
if you want to get the chance of
something happening you count all the
possible things that might happen and
you count of those which ones are the
ones that meet your criteria so if I
have a coin and it's got heads and tails
on it and I flip it up in the air there
are two possible things that might
happen heads or tails say I want heads
the chance of that happening is one out
of two it's two basic two to go through
let's do a die I throw a die it's got
six sides six possible things might
happen the chance of me say getting a
one or a three is two of those things so
the probability of me getting a one or
three is two divided by six or one-third
that's all you have to know about
probability for now yeah
to make a more careful analysis we're
gonna get at the end of the day to
something called conditional probability
and actually there's a way to test
whether a die is loaded or not you look
at the outcomes and you say hey what's
the chance if I spin this die of getting
four sixes when it's a fair die and you
can calculate what's the chance that I
just got four sixes in a row and it's a
fair die in fact let's do it right now
I just spun four sixes in a row what's
the chance of that happening well when I
spin four sixes in a row there are how
many possible outcomes any possible one
through six four different times okay
this is counting so that's who can do it
six six to the fourth it's like numbers
with six possible digits and there's
four digits 6 to the fourth possible
ways of spinning four dice and looking
at the outcomes how many of those ways
give all sixes one so the probability of
getting four sixes in a row is 1/6 to
the fourth pretty slim but it's possible
in your life if you spin a lot of dice
you probably will have gotten four sixes
in a row at some point or another it's
only one out of 1296 chance it's not too
unusual you can even calculate this
problem what if I spot a die 1290 six
times what's the chance of this
happening once kind of a meta question
but it's still within the ballpark we
could even do that but let's hold off on
it let's do some simpler things first
all right simpler question I'm throwing
free throws I'm not so good I got 50%
chance to get my free throw in yeah I'm
better than his
his free throws do you think it's okay
what does he think okay easy question
what's the chance that you throw five
throws and they all go in one chance
that they all go in two to the fifth
chances total misses and hits
okay so there's 32 different ways that
he could hit or miss during those five
two to the fifth and one of them works
so not so likely one out of 32 chances
if I keep throwing five shots that I'll
get all five in got it once in a while
all right what's the chance that I'll
get four out of five in same deal 50%
what's the chance that I get four out of
five same denominator 2 to the fifth
ways of throwing misses and hits 5
different times how many of them yeah
the same kind of idea but a compliment
if I have a sequence of five and I want
four of them to be hits I get I got five
spots and think of the hits as ones I
want to know how many ways are there to
choose to choose one this or to choose
four hits 5 choose 4 or 5 choose one so
I'll put 5 choose 1 here so that's 5
over 32 to get 4 out of 5
how about 3 out of 5 5 choose 2 or 5
choose 3 same thing out of 2 to the
fifth that equals
so far yeah no because that's just the
way Chris said yes I went with him but
you could do it the other way which is
more likely if you can get 50 percent of
your shots in to get four of them in or
to get one of them in he took five shots
they're the same right it's no more
likely that you'll do better than your
average than it is that you'll do less
than your average and that makes sense
what around the idea of average that's
right right in a bowling league you
always want your average to be going up
so you want to do bad at the beginning
because they give you a handicap so you
don't want to do really well at the
beginning and then well when you all get
older enjoying bowling lanes you know
alright questions about this who gets it
everybody gets it am i right that it's
98 percent county and 2 percent new idea
I think that's about the right
percentage would be a little new idea
coming up but not much in the context of
learning how to read math I asked you to
read this little article about this
birthday paradox and I want to review it
now that you've got all this counting
behind you so we're going to review this
not like a bunch of beginners who are
reading that for the first time but like
people who can do a lot of hard counting
problems and and we're going to analyze
this problem in a sophisticated way the
problem is the following you have a
bunch of people in a room you're
wondering what's the probability that
two or more of us have the same birthday
okay and it turns out that this
surprises most people that once you get
past
I forgot what the numbers 32 or so
anybody remember the number 2023 I think
what yeah for 50% 23 so when you get 23
people in a room the chance of two or
more of them having the same birthday is
50% when you have more than 23 people in
the room it's greater than 50% when you
have about 50 people in a room it's very
high already the chance of two or more
people having the same birthday and most
people have a gut instinct that this
doesn't really make sense that that you
would expect the percentage to be less
and it's it unlike some other things we
do this is a good thing to make a couple
bucks on if you need to drink at a bar
and you got a rich friend who doesn't
know much man or just looking for an
excuse to buy a drink all right so how
do we do it
how do we analyze this it is hard to
count the actual number of ways for us
to have two or more people having the
same birthday
we'd have to count the number of ways
for two people that have the same
birthday and for nobody else they have
the same birthday then we'd have to
count three people are more having the
same birthday there's a lot of
possibilities and it just seems daunting
so whenever it seems hard you do the
complement trick you count the opposite
instead of counting how many people two
or more have the same birthday why don't
we count the opposite of that that no
two people have the same birthday that's
much easier to count and then we'll
subtract that from the total number of
possible sets of birthdays that people
could have so let's let's back up what
are the total number of possible
sequences of birthdays let's say I have
36 people in the room each of you could
have a birthday from 1 to 365 they know
leap years today yeah yeah like question
right
right I didn't go to the November
birthday club meeting no not what do you
mean excited well only if you care about
really being rigorous we got a bunch of
random people I pulled them off the
street I agree right
the chance of any sequence of birthdays
is as likely as the chance of any other
sequence of birthday so I have to say
that and we're assuming that we'll
assume that's true so so say I've got 36
people and I want to calculate how many
different possible birthday sequences I
have you know starting with Peter then
going to Michael and going around the
whole room how many different possible
birthday sequences Peter's got 365
choices Michael's got 365 choices all
around the room 36 times so how many
total so right who agrees 365 that's
like instead of putting binary numbers
in each slot I'm putting 365 possible
digits in each slot and I've got 36
slots this is a total number of possible
birthday sequences it's a lot it's a
huge number are not going to actually
enumerate them those of you who who when
you get nervous on a on a problem set
your figure ok well now I'll just list
them you're not going to be able to do
it here this is too big we have to be
able to analyze this in a more general
way scheme could do it yes okay how many
of these have two or more birthdays a
saying that's hard to count but how many
have nobody the same that we can
definitely count how many have nobody
the same well Peters got the first
choice he's gonna have 365 choices for
his birthday but if I insist on counting
how many were nobody's got the same
birthday then Michael's only got 364
choices here so what's the number that
goes on top 365
36 times right so it is up to a point
365 times 364 times 363 okay
smarty-pants
good it's P 365 , 36 good now that
you're fancy you can write that good all
right well now what well that's the
probability that nobody's got the same
birthday but we want the probability
that two or more do have the same
birthday so what we have to do and
subtract that from from one or
equivalently put 365 to the 36 up here
and subtract P that's the same thing and
this is the whole paradox go ahead and
calculate see what you get now actually
if you go on a calculator and type in
365 to the 36 that's pretty silly
because your calculator will buzz out
and lose lots accuracy but you could
calculate this because as you can see
it's 365 divided by 365 times 364
divided by 365 see if you calculated
each fraction as you went along and did
it as a product you could actually do it
on a calculator and get an answer and
you get a percentage and that's it
there's no paradox here you just do the
calculation and see and if it's not what
you thought well then fix your intuition
because this really is true are there
questions about this
consecutive numbers or an approximation
that we could probably do that earlier
problem today - I don't know of any
questions about this ok good what
happens as the number of people gets
very very big well what happens say this
36 gets very very large you know it gets
to be 365 is it a certainty when it gets
to be 365 no this becomes n factorial
right and this becomes 365 to the to the
N right
more or less well it becomes 3 to 65
factorial over 365 to the to the 365 and
that's the number it's not certainty
right and if you just kept making this
bigger and bigger and bigger and bigger
well what happens when a third and Sigma
6 you should have certainty right so
what happens we'd expect this to turn
into certainty after a while right does
it
can't right right if you have to take
more than you actually have then the
number of ways to do it is zero so the
probability of having two or more people
with the same birthday becomes one you
should always do that boundary case
analysis whenever you get an answer that
can be generalized because it will
confirm to you whether your answer
originally makes sense let's do another
example like this from the problem set
that you've already finished 2n socks in
a drawer you're pulling out two socks
you want to know what's the chance you
get a pair we calculated yesterday that
it's 2 n choose 2 divided by 2 times n
choose 2 divided by 2 n choose 2 this is
a total number of way of choosing a pair
of socks this is the total number of
ways of choosing a pair of blue and then
choosing a pair of red you add them
together what happens to this as the
number of socks and the drawer gets very
large if you calculate this what does
this end up being anybody remembered you
do the problem set what does it end up
being something like this all right if
it's not somebody calculated and
corrected if this is true then when n
gets very large what happens to this
fraction where does it tend to go this
is limits from calculus goes to 1/2
right so that means if you've got a huge
draw socks and it's just bigger and
bigger and bigger the chance of you
getting a pair is about 50% which is
just what somebody might have guessed if
you gave them the problem for 10 even
though it's not 50% for 10 it's only 50%
as n goes to infinity but it's not 50%
for any other number it's not 50% for
any particular number is it bigger or
less than 50% for any real number it's
always a little less than 50% right this
heads to 1/2 from
bottom here's a question I haven't done
with you yet and it's going to relate
back to the number of binary trees the
number of ways to multiply n plus 1
matrices and the number of ways to setup
K pairs of balanced parentheses or n
pairs of balanced parentheses so it'll
be related in a particularly unexpected
way and it also relates in an unexpected
way to derangements so this is a really
cool problem and it's one that
originally I came up with on some test I
gave I don't know some 20 years ago it's
in some beginner computer science class
and and like a lot of things like put on
tests weeks later I realized that
there's some good stuff on it and I
didn't realize it when I first gave the
problem so here it is it's the World
Series World Series is a 7 game series
for those of you not from this country
or from this world the first team to win
4 games wins the series you got to win
the majority of the games there's a lot
of tournaments like this you know two
out of three 3 out of 5 4 to 7 5 & a 9
you can generalize it okay so let's say
we have a World Series it doesn't have
to be the real World Series but well
let's make it the real World Series
seven games what's the chance even teams
now even chances to win every game teams
are evenly matched what's the chance the
World Series goes all the way that means
goes to the seventh game people always
wonder whether it's going to go to the
seventh game it affects whether the
Simpsons premiere is going to come on
Monday or the following Monday
it affects whether these commercials are
going to be on that people spend 10
million bucks on it affects whether the
bookies in Las Vegas are going to have
lots of business it affects a million
things it's actually practical so what's
the chance when you start this series
that it's gonna go all seven games let's
calculate that everybody with me all
right what are the total number of ways
we could play seven games in this series
that is I'm team Juan Chris's team two
we play each other either I win or he
wins right and we do this seven times
how many sequences can we get two to the
seventh it's just number of binary
numbers with with seven slots and that's
that's some number that we can actually
calculate that's true and we'll do that
up here so you're saying why don't we
divide by two to the six because we want
to know if I play seven games how many
of them have three wins and three losses
in the first six places the only real
reason to go to the to win after
that's a nice way of trying to express
this really is the right way to do it
but I want to convince you that it is
because your question is very subtle and
and it's not so easy to answer the way
I'm going to answer it is first I'm
going to tell you what Jacob just said
and that I'm going to head and I'm going
to do it for a very small case so you'll
see why this makes sense for the small
case and then I think you can
extrapolate to here but but let's assume
we've played the world series and I want
to know that's what Jacob just said
we've played the seven-game series it's
over how many of them ended up being
three three before the seventh game okay
now sometimes it's going to end after
four games right that's true but that
represents a lot of the possible
sequences of seven we just don't play
the last three but they could have been
anything and it wouldn't have mattered
it's a little tricky let's go ahead and
do it let's go let's gotta finish this
and then we'll calculate smaller cases
so here the total number of ways there
are to play a seven game series okay I
flip a die that has two Seth Lepik wine
seven times and I get say 0 1 1 1 0 1 1
2 3 4 5 6 right but I flip it seven
times I finish now that this series go
all the way or not no right because it
ended it ended right here alright some
of these sequences of seven games are
going to go all the way and some won't
or I should say it this way some would
have gone all the way and some would not
have I want to calculate how many of
these sequences of seven wins and losses
actually make me play the full seven
game actually care think of this as
Florida all right and this is Iowa and
this is Arizona I do all the electoral
votes they're all done how many
of the states do I really care about
when I'm all done I still do it all and
now I look to see which ones make a
difference in which ones don't
so I just won't play those other games
if I don't need to but to calculate
their probability I still need to look
at them alright so how many ways have in
these seven sequences have three zeros
and three ones I got seven places I want
to know how many of them have exactly
three zeros and exactly three ones how
can we do that in the seven sequences
there's the first six places you have to
write the first six have to have three
zeros and three ones I should I said it
wrong right the first six places have to
have three zeros and three ones how do
you do that 6 choose 3 is that it how
many different ways are there of taking
6 digits and putting 3 zeros and three
ones in them I got three choices for the
ones anywhere I want to put them that's
6 choose 3 and what I'm done with that I
got I got no choices for the zeros they
just have to go in the other spot so 6
choose 3 is it let's calculate this the
bottom is 128 and the top is 20 right
from the start the chance of reaching a
seven-game series where the first six
games are split three three is five over
thirty to about one six and we can go
back and look at all the world series
for the last hundred years and see how
many of them went all the way and how
many didn't and we would expect in the
long run for it to be about a six going
the whole way and the rest not right
right that's true
maybe not we'd have to find out right
right I've that's true especially for
the Yankees in the forties right how was
that Tris speaker doing nowadays I'm
doing my Monty burns abilities we have
to double this I agree with I agree with
Doug what do you think about that
he's right or else we could do it Chris
said before we could change the seven to
uh either we changes seven to a six or
we say that once I put these three zeros
and three ones in these places that the
next spot could be either a zero or it
could be or it could be a one either I
didn't count this right or I didn't
count this right I got it I got to be
consistent so let me back up so what we
have here is wrong
is the number of ways to put three zeros
and three ones into the first six places
this is the total number of strings of
seven wins and losses but this is not
the total subset of these that have
three ones and three zeros in them
because it doesn't include the very last
position being either a zero or one so
we really would have to put a two in
here and that's the same as taking it
two away from here and maybe that's what
you were asking at the very beginning
you were saying why don't we just think
about the first six and then wonder
about how many ways there are putting
half of those in as white and black so
does that you feel good about it now
this really is right and this is really
wrong about 1/3 yeah sorry everybody we
were careless and I was the most
careless evenly matched teams about 1/3
that's in a world series of seven games
so we're gonna do this again in a world
series of more than this many games
we're gonna see what happens as n gets
bigger and bigger and bigger as you
increase the number of games in a series
what do you think what's the chance that
it goes all the way do you think it's
going to go down do you think it's going
to get less and less do you think it's
gonna average out here let's calculate
it for three game series who can do it
for three games to two the two to the
two and up here is this is a three game
series okay it's either either a win
loss or loss win so this is two over for
50% then it goes all the way in a three
game series what's the chance that goes
all the way in a one-game series 100% so
100% 50% and when you're down here in a
world series of seven games it's down to
about a third does it keep getting less
does it level out what happens let's
let's calculate it we're going to
calculate it we're going to get
something a little bit surprising well
maybe not so surprising are the
questions so far
so EJ and Chris you're you're ahead of
me here and now you're happy
you're giving that one a dog all right
okay
take a bow that's right all right let's
solve this in general I got a world
series instead of seven games it's two n
plus one games okay so in this case the
N was what's the end in this case for a
real world series 3 right 2 times 3 plus
1 7 so in general what would the formula
end up being the bottom is 2 to the 2n
and the top is 2n choose good we're
going to work with this for a little bit
and instead of me saying okay just do
the algebra yourself today we're
actually going to do the algebra because
I think it's important
before if n is 1 that means it's a
three-game series what was the
probability of it going all the way how
and when it's a five-game series we
didn't do that can someone do that and
check what it was a seven-game series we
calculated it was 5/16 I think that's
right somebody check that somebody check
it is it right don't trust me a check
says yes ok nobody sees a pattern yet
how do I know what the next one's going
to be without looking some kind of power
of 2 on the bottom and what happens on
the top hmm it's tricky huh I kind of
hid the pattern a little bit because I
converted everything to lowest terms as
I went along and if I hadn't I wouldn't
have hit it so much but but here's what
actually happened this is 1/2 this is
1/2 times 3/4 this is 1/2 times 3/4
times 5/6 this is 1/2 times 3/4 times
5/6 times 7/8 so I'll work out
to be at any point just put the odd
numbers on the top the even numbers in
the bottom and multiply your product as
you go along it couldn't be more
iterative and also more obscure why does
this turn out to be this so I want to
show you why and it's really not obscure
we're going to fiddle with this so we're
going to turn this into exactly one of
these sequences and in doing so it's
going to help us with a lot of
approximation somewhere else where this
number comes up this is a key number and
understanding number of binary trees and
understanding balanced parentheses and
understanding how to multiply matrices
this number comes up and being able to
approximate it is important and the fact
that it has something to do with this
sequence of odds and evens is kind of
neat okay questions so far yeah Tony we
did a proof that this equals the sum do
you remember the proof we did that this
equals the sum of good memory well
almost the good memory
remember this proof I asked Sam this and
there was the one thing he said this
whole semester that he didn't know off
the bat is if you add these up without
the squares it equals 2 to the N if you
add them up with the squares it equals
2n choose n remember that that you have
to prove that
well that's neat we're not going to use
that right now but it's new well you got
this 2 to the 2 to the N on the bottom
too let's fill it with us a little bit
factorial things are kind of easy to
fill it with lots of things cancel let's
play with it and see what we can do all
right chew n choose n turn that into
factorials for me 2n factorial
right / n factorial times n factorial so
I'm going to put those those two n
factorials if you don't mind on the
bottom ok neck next to this so n
factorial n factorial and ok let's just
do that for now let's just work with
this shoe n choose n let's just work
with this you throw this in at the end
and fix it all right now what how can we
fix this up make it nice and get odds
and evens out of it
take an example say e n is 4 alrights 8
times 7 times 6 times 5 times 4 right so
let's go ahead and pull out a factor of
2 from something like that let's look at
an example 8 times 7 times 6 times 5
times 4 times 3 times 2 times 1 I could
pull out a 2 from all the even terms
right if I do what happens what do I get
if I do that
how many twos do I pull out and in
general in this case two to the fourth
and what's left I got 1 3 5 7 times 7 5
3 1 times 4 3 4 3 2 1 it's going to be
useful or not let's see
out a 2 from here and a 2 from here and
a 2 from here and a 2 from here I pulled
out for the twos out front and I'd left
myself with a nice factorial and a bunch
of odd numbers but you see those odd
numbers that's what I'm hoping to look
for that's why I did this I'm looking
for those odd numbers so there they are
let's do this in general let's do the
top now with ends 2n factorial I can
take out 2 to the end from that what's
left n factorial is left times what
times those odd numbers 1 3 5 up to what
odd number 2 I minus 1 good and on the
bottom I still got n factorial n
factorial all right so one of them gets
cancelled out that's Pleasant bye-bye
bye-bye
now we're going to take this guy and put
him in okay there's two to the two to
the end that's been sitting out and
waiting rid of this this
divided by n factorial divided by 2 to
the 2n now I'm ready to manipulate that
we're almost done 2 to the N and 2 to
the 2n what happens there
I got n twos on the top I got 2 n 2 s on
the bottom and of them disappear from
the top they're all gone and I'm left
with just 2 to the N on the bottom so
that's also nice bye-bye but look at
here I got n twos I got n factorial now
I'm going to put all the twos back in
here so if this n factorial is like 4
factorial 4 3 2 1 now I'm going to put
the twos back in and I'm going to get 8
6 4 - these are just going to be the
even numbers starting from 2n let's try
it
1 3 5 up to 2 n minus 1 and on the
bottom 2n is going to be the biggest
number I have when I start from 2 4 6
all the way up to 2 N and that's what
these numbers are so that funny-looking
equation turns out to this infinite
product very different ways of looking
at the same thing but they're really
completely identical and again this last
step is distributing these twos back
into the N factorial so you get the even
numbers from 2 - 2 n ok so if you want
to know the probability of a world
series going all the way you could put
large end into here and calculate it but
if I ask you what happens to this as n
gets very large it might not be obvious
what happens to this as n gets very
large but if you see it like this it
might be more obvious what's going on
here maybe maybe not
what's happening here well you're always
multiplying by some other fraction a
fraction closer closer to one it's true
but it's always by 7/8 and then by by
9/10 and then by 1012 so what's
happening to the overall product as you
go along it's always getting smaller
it's still not clear that it doesn't
level out but I think either on your
problem set or on some no it's probably
a thing I thought of putting on an exam
you can prove by induction that this
ends up being smaller than like 1 to the
2 to the something in other words you
can prove by induction that this
actually is smaller than something which
strictly gets smaller and smaller and
smaller and smaller in other words this
really does go to 0 the chance of you
making it all the way in a series where
the number of games is longer and longer
and longer is less and less and less the
chance of it happening tends to 0 as the
games tend to a thousand ten thousand
one hundred thousand namely parentheses
how many balanced ways number of ways to
multiply matrices to multiply n plus 1
square matrices the number of binary
trees with n nodes these are all the
same you proved in one of your problem
sets that these two were the same
remember that and I just told you that
this was the same as these two I got to
talk a little bit more what it is today
but I want to tell you the answer to
this because we're going to prove what
this answer is later on when we do our
last topic on all this stuff when we
finish probability but I want to give
you the answer in advance the number of
ways to do all these three things is 2n
choose n divided by n plus 1 let's do an
example if you have three pairs of
parentheses or 3 no
for a binary tree or four square
matrices that you want to multiply
together how many different ways are
there to do it anybody remember three
balanced parentheses three binary trees
how many different ways five right good
memory Jeff right five let's put three
in here and check that 6 choose 3 is 20
20 divided by 4 is 5 right so this is
works it's correct proof by single
example and these are called the Catalan
numbers they come up in lots of places
so they got a name just like Fibonacci
numbers have a name because they come up
in lots of places and your problem set
this week one of the problems is to get
some kind of big order growth for this
function to n choose n divided by n plus
1 and the way to do it is to use what we
did over here to show that we know that
2 to the n choose n over 2 to the 2n
that this is equal exactly to this
fraction right
using this equaling this is a way to get
an approximation here ok there's one one
way to do it so you should be able to
connect these two ideas we're going to
talk about this idea much much more in a
little bit but I have another topic in
between are there questions so far I'm
going to talk a little bit more about
this and I'm going to finish up with
probability any questions
they're called Catalan numbers ca ca LAN
I want to remind you of something you've
done on a problem set before I asked you
on the problem set to prove some
recurrence equation about these two
actually it was about this one the
square matrices then I asked you to show
that this was one-to-one correspondence
with this one so that they're really the
same and the same recurrence equation
would hold for this one anybody remember
what the recurrence equation was here
what's CN depended on I'll give you a
hint it had to do with where the last
multiple
was you could do any sub multiplication
of all of them then the last
multiplication followed by any sub
multiplication of the arrays that were
left over so what did that end up being
C 1 times C n minus 1 plus C 2 times C n
minus 2 all the way up to C n minus 1 C
1 and that's the same as what I think
Michael was calling out I equals 1 to n
minus 1 of C I see n minus I I think
that's right let me double check it 1 n
minus 1 2 n minus 2 and minus 1 yeah
that looks right remember that
recurrence equation now do we have the
foggiest vaguest idea of how to solve
such a Twisted Sister now these these
are these Catalan numbers are the same
as it's the number of ways to to balance
parenthesis of n pairs of parenthesis n
minus 1 pairs of parenthesis etcetera
they're one what are they one two five
and then like 13 14 and then some big
number they got big fast they grow
quickly I don't I don't know the first
few by heart
this is daunting I mean it nothing that
we've done so far works not linear
homogeneous not substitution not not
proving by induction I mean everything
just just falls apart and we aren't
gonna be able to solve this but we need
a new tool and we'll get to it later but
before I get there I just want to add
one more thing before I let this go and
then come back to this later on but one
thing that's left over that we still
have to finish up is how come binary
trees have anything to do with this why
are binary trees in the same category
besides the fact that I just told you
they were well here's why let's say I
want to build binary trees with n nodes
how can I build them how can I build
them and get the same recurrence
equation we'll call it BN number of
binary trees with n nodes
what is it depend on think recursively
here how do you build up a binary tree
with one extra node I'll give you a hint
don't put it at the bottom that's harder
to do put the new node at the top how
many new ways can I make a new binary
tree I always put the new node at the
top okay there it is how can I continue
I got two sides right the left side can
be any binary tree as long as it has
minus one so I can put any tree here and
any tree here I'll call this t1 and t2
as long as the sum of t1 and t2 s nodes
equals n minus 1 well there's a lot of
possibilities there
b1 the N minus 1 B 2 BN minus 2 B 3 BN
minus 3 all the way up to how many ways
can I get n minus 1 vertices on the left
and one vertex on the right it's the
exact same recurrence equation it's the
exact same idea the binary tree idea
because you're balancing left and right
and you want the sum of those two to be
n minus 1 gives you the same exact
recurrence as this no it is the same as
look the first possibility is that we
put 1 all the trees with 1 node on the
left and all the trees with n minus o
that I do this that's fine that's ok
yeah so you call this n plus 1 right now
I'm okay no now it's our mentally right
ok but that's not quite the same oh I do
right right right
thank you EJ me I got saved by a good so
this is B 0 B n minus 1
that still not the same but it should be
the same oh you got to wonder I think we
did
the same hmm
have to reconstruct those sorry right
but I thought I'm more it's more likely
that this is wrong than this is wrong I
made a mistake in one of these but I
forget which one let's go back and redo
this I tried to do this from memory from
your pset and maybe we can redo it a 1 a
2 a 3 a 4 or if I want to figure out the
number of ways to associate a 1 a 2 a 3
a 4 I can group them say here's the last
multiplication right so this would be C
1 C 3 and I'm trying to do C 4 so they
should add up so that looks right
in this situation it's M plus one
matrices and n vertices we didn't do
anything wrong but I forgot to in this
situation the CN refers to having it
work for n plus 1 matrices and for n
pairs of parentheses and for n binary
trees so that takes care of this of this
extra no not exactly
no I'll have to come back to this when I
really do it I thought I would fill this
and now and it would make it better and
I just filled it in and made it worse
when I do this problem and actually
solve this recurrence for you which I
will do very soon not today but soon
I'll come back and redo this and show
you the connection to binary trees but
you have to take my word for it today
they really are the same
I didn't prove it today I made this area
but I'll back up and do it soon yeah
borough had a question Tony tight end
of ways there are to do this so so what
we generally are doing is trying to get
the one with n vertices to be dependent
on one whose sum of the sub-trees is n
minus 1 vertices not whose heights are n
minus 1 but whose sum of the actual
vertices themselves are n minus 1 so I
don't think we can do a product like
that but like I said let me get back to
this this is not what I this really was
meant to be a short diversion to lead
you into it when I do it next time but
what I really want to do is finish up
probability things today there's one
idea here but I want to motivate it to
make sure you all get it it's not a
complicated idea but it can be a little
bit subtle in its applications it's
called conditional probability instead
of me asking hey what's the chance of
this happening you just count all the
outcomes and you count how many work out
to the ones you want I'm asking you a
different kind of question I'm saying
I'm giving you that this happened what's
the probability that this other event is
true given that this happened so it can
change your probability here's an
example here's a very famous example
that that people always present this
puzzle so you can probably find in some
ask Marilyn Vos savant column and in
Parade magazine this is the kind of
thing she likes to talk about so here it
is and then she goes on and on
explaining in the most completely
obscure way about why the things true
appealing to to trust me
as the main reason I don't like her
because she makes everybody feel like
more magical than it should be rather
than just explaining how it really works
well she's got a good job and she
certainly understands the things herself
and to her credit when the famous let's
make a deal puzzle that relates the
probability here came about and do you
know that one I'll play you play let's
make a deal
ever see let's make a deal what okay so
you talked about in recitation fine it's
a good puzzle but basically when you
first hear it your intuition is to guess
the wrong answer but what was worse is
that some PhDs actually wrote her some
letters chastising her saying she got it
wrong and if there's one thing she
doesn't do she doesn't get things wrong
she's pretty bright and she usually
knows what she's talking about she has
no clue usually how to explain it or how
to make it comprehensible she just makes
it seem transparent and for anybody who
doesn't understand math it just
reinforces the idea that well I'll never
really understand it so I should just
keep talking vaguely and sooner or later
someone will say yeah you got it and I
hate that but but but she does get the
answers right and she had all these
letters from people who should know
better saying that she was wrong and
explaining that she didn't understand it
and in fact they didn't understand it or
they just mistakenly talk too quickly
but we're not talking about that we're
talking about something different
Terral talk about that maybe today
here's a famous example you you uh
alright here's an easy one yeah you walk
up to a box somebody says there's a
child in that box they say what's the
chance that child's a boy equally likely
it's a boy or a girl here you say 50%
what's the chance of it's being a girl
you say 50% you're right no big deal all
right now all right you have two little
motivation
all right here we go
you walk up to somebody's house you're
an undercover agent you've got a big big
SWAT team behind you you bang on the
door presumably this family is keeping a
child in a box and you want to save it's
costing you right now we need it all
right my imagination could not be
actually stranger than life right all
right so here we go you walk into this
house and you knock on the door and and
it got a suspicious-looking box in the
corner so and then and then you see this
little kid run across the hall and and
you see it's a girl and your SWAT team
leader says should we open the box
what's the chance to think it's a girl
or a boy and you say to the woman at the
door how many children do you says I
have two children and you say well I see
your other child's a girl and she goes
yeah that's true and then you say well
you're under arrest and we're about to
open that box and what's the chance that
the child in the box is a girl it seems
like 50 percent right now same situation
but we come into the house same exact
thing there's a box in the corner
there's a kid in the box now a little
kid runs across the way it's a little
it's a girl and you walk up to the woman
you tell her she's under arrest you
introduce yourself you say oh what a
nice little girl you have the one that
you saw running and she goes oh yes
that's my oldest she's very sweet I have
two kids what's the chance the girl in
the box is a but kid in the box is a boy
or a girl it's not a hundred percent
it's a girl but the probability here
changes there's a big difference if you
just know she has another kid before you
make your decision about the probability
then if you know her older kid is the
girl there's two conditions here one
condition is you know she has another
child and that's all she has and the
second condition is you know she has an
older child who's a girl your first gut
instinct when you hear this question is
well it's still 5th
% but it's not and it really isn't you
could do this experiment and and
convince yourself it really isn't
you need a swab you know let's calculate
let's calculate it logically without
gluing any formulas up on the board how
you calculate conditional probabilities
it's very logical conditional
probabilities mean that I've told you
something is true so the number of your
outcomes of possible outcomes has now
changed here's what I mean this woman
has two kids what are the possible
outcomes for her children normally it'd
be two boys normally the boy boy boy
girl girl boy or girl girls right that's
normally now when you saw when you saw
that she had one other kid and that kid
was a girl which of the probabilities
remain this one's gone that is not one
of our possible outcomes anymore you
have been told that that is not a
possible outcome it could be any one of
these out of those
the other one being a girl what's the
answer just this one right not 50% what
about this case the case when I told you
the older ones a girl what are the
possibilities the older ones a girl so
in this case the original case I told
you that you figure oh it's 50% it's not
really 50% it's really 1/3 and in the
second case where I told you the oldest
one is a girl it's really 1/2 right this
is really strange right so forget the
stuff with the kid in the box for a
second just think about all the friends
you have that have two kids if their
first kid is a girl if their oldest
one's a girl the chance that the second
one's a girl also is one attitude ok if
you get a girl the chance of having a
girl the next kid is still one at it too
but if I tell you I've got a whole bunch
of friends they all have two kids they
all have at least one girl what's the
chance the other one's a girl and you
can do this experiment get all your
friends that have two kids that have at
least one girl put them in a big pool
and count the number of people that have
two girls it's going to be only
one-third not one-half so this is subtle
even though it's a simple case and it's
not what you originally feel or your gut
instinct is but you can calculate it
here it is here's all the possibilities
where somebody's got at least one girl
here is the only one where they have two
girls so if I tell you somebody's got at
least one girl in the family exactly two
children
one-third of a chance they have two
girls if I tell you that the oldest
one's a girl then it's down to 1/2 it's
weird right
what if I didn't
say the oldest ones aggro what if I said
let's forget the oldest what if we said
what if I said that's the one with
freckles what if I I mean it's something
what did you gain from here right I mean
the person told me that's the oldest one
right and suddenly my probability change
what if they told me something else
about that one you know just something
unique that that separates it from
another one you wouldn't tell you
anything right well would tell you
something if you knew that every family
only had one freckled kid and once you
had a freckled kid you couldn't have
another freckled kid it would actually
tell you something because then if you
had the freckled kid at the beginning it
would change it would give you the same
different number of outcomes so you have
to be careful the reason this matters is
because you can only have one oldest kid
all right
maybe that's not particularly
illuminating but this is really right
girl right so if you're guessing boy
sorry
better you're putting a judgment on it
as to whether you're going to get the
answer right or not I guess let's say
you're always going to guess boy then
you're then if somebody tells you that
the oldest one's a girl you're down a
fifty-fifty shot if somebody doesn't
tell you the oldest one's a girl then
you should be guessing boy if they don't
tell you information then you have a
better bet but that's not so surprising
sometimes giving you more information
what you want to bet on in fact that's
how the stock market works the more
information there is the less likely you
are to be able to make the right
decision
it's just random but more information
there is in the stock market the more
random the stock market will seem the
more completely perfect every price will
be so that a few bet on either side it's
just going to be a random bet it's it's
the less information you get that
actually lets you leverage well now
we're really getting yeah somebody shoot
that guy and put him in a box right
that makes it a one-third chance that it
that the other ones a girl if she tells
you the oldest one no sorry if she tells
you the oldest ones a girl that changes
it to 50/50 that the other ones a girl
if she does just tells you that's my
other kid who walked by then it's only a
one-third chance that the other ones a
girl no yeah ixnay on the twins if she
said it was the youngest you would still
yes I know there is sure why no there is
sure I mean what if I had a whole block
full of twisted families and every one
of them right but we are assuming that
that the chance of them having a boy
girl girl boy boy girl is completely
arbitrary completely random right so
right right that's right the primary
subject there's an equal number of boys
and girls in the world and every person
who has two kids can a boy boy boy girl
girl boy girl girl equally
you talking about statistics you're
talking about if you take a sample how
do you know that that sample is a
reasonable reflection of a real random
sample and how do you test that and you
can calculate probabilities that a
sample you took is really is really
reflecting the the bigger population but
of favorable to total that it works out
as long as Y naught but this isn't
biased these are boys and girls and
there's a 50/50 shot all right I'm not
really sure
importing the idea that there is that's
true and and we're also basing it and
the same assumption the fact that a coin
is going to be half heads half tails
we're assuming that's true what's the
chance a number from one to twenty
inclusive for those of you who don't
like the word between problem one to
twenty is divisible by three what's the
probability and number one to twenty is
divisible by three there's 20
possibilities for the number how many of
them are divisible by 3 3 6 9 12 15 18
603 tenths now let's switch it a little
bit given not that the other ones a girl
or that one's a boy but given that a
number is divisible by five what's the
probability same questions that a number
one to 20 is divisible by three you're
given that a number is divisible by five
I'm granting you that fact the number is
definitely divisible by five what's the
chance that a number picked between 1
and 20 is going to be divisible by 3
assuming that it's divisible by 5 let's
calculate it how many possibilities are
there for the number it's divisible by 5
so 5 10 15 and 20 right forth and how
many of them are divisible by 3 5 10 15
20 only 15 so in every one of these
examples I'm just trying to motivate for
you that the definition of conditional
probability really does just cut down
the total outcomes and then cut down the
appropriate number of possible things in
the numerator as well but there's
something general that's going on here
that I want to show
in this example that generalizes in a
way that you can't always just use this
simple approach on the top here are the
number that are divisible by five and
divisible by three and are between one
and twenty and there's one of those
numbers right the number divisible by
five visible by three in between one and
twenty and on the bottom is what the
number divisible by five and between one
and twenty so based on this based on
this there's a different way to look at
this very much going to be the same
answer but what's the chance given a
number between one and twenty that it's
divisible by five and three that's going
to be one out of twenty and what's the
chance that out of the numbers one and
twenty that you get things divisible by
five that's going to be four out of 20
and that's the same as one for two
different ways to look at it one is
counting all of these explicitly
counting all of these explicitly and one
is counting the probability here and
dividing by the probability here here's
our total possibilities here are the
ones that are divisible by five and
three here are the ones that are
divisible by five so I want to write
normalizing over some base case but now
I'm going to write up a formula that's
the basis of all conditional probability
and then we're going to end with this
the probability of something happening
conditional that something else has
already happened the probability of a on
condition of B a in this case is
divisible by three
this is the condition this is the
probability you're looking for it's
equal to the probability of something
divided by the probability of something
else what's on the bottom what's on the
top base this example to construct this
rule for yourselves on the bottom is
going to be the probability of the
condition and on the top is going to be
the probability of the intersection of
your two events both a and B this is the
famous theorem about conditional
probability I present it to you in this
way because I want you to see that it's
intuitive that it's not something
arbitrary they have to memorize it just
makes sense we'll do one quick example
then we'll quit today
same thing given divisible by five
what's the chance the number is
divisible by three but this time I'm not
going to tell you that the numbers
between one and twenty any number at all
everybody with me so I'm giving you that
a number is divisible by five what's the
chance that the number's divisible by
three what do you think that chance
should be if I gave you any number
what's the chance that it's divisible by
three
one-third either it's divisible by 3 or
divisible by three remainder one or
divisible by three remainder two they're
all equally likely so we'd figure it's
one-third if I tell you that the number
is divisible by five that doesn't seem
to tell you anything about whether it's
a visible by three or not it just seems
to be picking a random sequence or is it
well let's calculate this is for any
number what's the chance that a number
is divisible by five
that's the condition that goes in the
bottom what's the chance that a number
is divisible by both three and five if
it's a visible go three and five that
means it's divisible by by fifteen
that's the only thing it could be so
this is one fifteen and that equals a
third so really is a third this worked
because three and five are relatively
prime
can definitely divide the number by
three so it should be a hundred percent
let's use our little formula and just
check out the limit cases it's always a
good thing to do the chance that it's
going to be divisible by six is the
condition that goes in the bond and
that's one six what's the chance that a
number is divisible by six and the
number is divisible by three now in this
case they're not relatively prime so the
chance of a number being divisible by
six and being divisible by three is
exactly the same as the chance of it
being divisible by six so you got a six
divided by six the intersection here it
just collapses and becomes uninteresting
and you get one okay this is what you
really need to know to do any of the
conditional probabilities that I gave
you in the pset most of them are a lot
more involved in these basic examples
and maybe I'll have taro try to do a
couple examples of this go over the exam
talk about the let's make a deal problem
we're up to here we are at what days of
today we got Monday we have two days
left this week here's what I'd like to
be at the end of this week I have one
important lecture on generating
functions which is a topic in and of
itself that will relate back to those
Catalan numbers that'll take a daddy
then I'm really ready to start off on
the last week's material so we're more
or less ahead and we can slow down a
little bit I'm gonna have Terra and
maybe I will also at the end of this
week kind of do a review of all counting
of all probability to make sure
everybody's ready for number theory and
cryptography problems that sixes do
before you go away for Thanksgiving get
it done finish it problem set seven
seven there's only one more problems
that there's a roaming card trick
problem set those do problem sets we'll
do any time before the end of the month
all right so pace yourself try to get
the card trick one done early in the
week leave the other one for later the
final is a very last day of a month and
it will cover it will be comprehensive
but it will be much more toward the
things that I haven't tested on
so we'll cover things about probability
and Counting it will cover just a little
bit maybe one question about logic and
one question about recurrence equations
but it'll be mostly about counting and
some stuff about number theory at the
end okay that's the big picture
all right unconditional probability I
think there must be a section right
there's a more there's there's a good
section in the algorithms book in the
reverse book the reverse book like I
said has this chapter at the beginning
on discrete math which is really dense
but but is actually in many ways a
complete introduction to discrete math
even though it's very fast and I know
there's a second