I'm ready to start in a second other
questions about anything before I get
going three o'clock enough time for
people to get back from wherever you are
and still get here no nuts well you can
hang around and ask questions but it's
our actually it's probably going to show
up so we can do informal things but
there's no formal recitation okay
of something that the book cooks in a
place where where I think it shouldn't
be exactly it is a technique that that
connects to solving recurrences it is
one more way to solve recurrence
equation it's a really really powerful
technique but it's hard to appreciate
generating functions until you already
understand everything you need to know
about counting what generating functions
really are is a way to leverage what you
know about algebra to apply to counting
it's a way to make a connection between
counting problems and algebraic formulas
so that when you manipulate the
algebraic formulas by the stuff you
learned in high school you try to
understand how that relates to the
counting problem that the algebraic
formula was connected to so it gives you
the ability to take all tool that you're
very familiar with the algebra tools and
yankem on counting problems and really
get some interesting things so for the
first I don't know hour or so you're
going to see it applied to situations
that you could have solved without
generating functions but at the very end
of this lecture and a half for as long
as it takes me we're going to solve that
recurrence equation about the
parentheses and about the binary trees
that goes on and on and along some that
we couldn't solve with any other method
and the generating functions will really
show their power and you'll see where
the algebra connection really comes in
so we're where you'll see it's really
really uses in that problem which we
couldn't solve in any other way up till
now all the other problems are kind of
like it intro until that alright so
first I got to give you an idea of what
this is all about and what's happening
here so other questions so far
recurrence equations you know a
recurrence equation you solve it for T
of N and then you can plug in various
ends you get T of 1 is this T of 2 is
that T of 3 is this if it's like
Fibonacci numbers for example you know
the the values go 1 1 2 3 5 8 if it's
triangle numbers they go 1 3 6 10 15 so
you can think of counting problems or
solving recurrences in some ways as
generating sequences generating function
is a way to represent a sequence in a
way that seems completely twisted in a
way that seems more complicated than you
would need but a way that actually pays
back later with all the complication
that you use with a lot of power so
here's what I mean let's say you have
the sequence of triangle numbers 1 3 6
10 15 20 1 etc so a way to represent
this as a generating function here's
what a generating function means it's a
polynomial whose coefficients on here's
what it is
terms are the same as the numbers in the
sequence this is the generating function
for the triangle numbers so in this case
if we call these triangle numbers T this
would be T zero this would be T 1 this
would be T 2 this series here no we're
not no in fact that's you never do that
you're right you don't solve it for zero
you just use them and you manipulate
them and you get new functions that have
new numbers on the coefficients that's
how we're going to use it you'll see how
we'll use it in a couple minutes well
yeah be patient so here's the thing in
front of the X to the 0 you get the T
zero number in front of the X to the 1
you get the T 1 number in front of the x
squared you get the T 2 number okay it's
just a way of writing a sequence in
terms of a polynomial now why would you
want to do that you'll see in a little
while questions so far okey doke let me
ask you one here is Pascal's triangle
what's the generating function for that
finite sequence
happens to also be the same as this
right
what's the generating function for the
third row of Pascal's triangle
how multiplying this out gives you the
same as these binomial coefficients that
was the binomial theorem so one thing
that you already know about generating
functions is that if you want the K
throw of Pascal's triangle and it's a
finite sequence of numbers and you want
the generating function for that K throw
it's exactly the function one plus X to
the K okay so you can have infinite
generating functions you can have finite
generating functions and the actual
coefficients here as you probably know
are K choose zero K choose one K choose
two all the way up to K choose K right
that's the K throw in Pascal's triangle
that's some review but make sure
everybody remembers this generating
function generates these coefficients on
each of the terms as you go from the
constant term up to the X to the K term
okay questions so far good
it'll get somewhere soon okay here's a
counting problem
you want them to add up to 20 and each
of the numbers has to be in between 0 &
8 remember these kind of problems we did
a lot of these kind of problems remember
how to solve these the the greater than
constraints were easy to handle right
the greater than constraints just made
us take it a little bit away from this
number and we were able to solve it it
was the less than constraints that were
pain-in-the-butt right the less than
constraints we solved it in two
different ways one way was reversing it
and doing inclusion exclusion churning
it from from Anne's to ORS and doing
inclusion exclusion and the other way
was just doing lots of cases if an eye
has to be less than or equal to 8 okay
so n1 can be 0 do all the cases and 1
can be 1 do all the cases and 1 can be 2
and that's a sometimes very slow way but
it would also work that's a direct way
we did it both ways when we solve this
problem we did it the direct way where
we did it in cases that we did it
inclusion exclusion now we're going to
do it using generating functions now I
got to tell you that the method that I'm
going to do here is not going to be
easier than either of our methods it's
simply going to show you a connection
between counting and generating
functions it's not going to be so useful
as far as the calculation of the
computation goes it'll be just as hard
to get the answer with a generating
function as it was with inclusion
exclusion or with the cases but it will
make a connection between these two
seemingly separate things so here is the
connection and I'll explain exactly how
it works in a second but first let me
give it to you here's a function 1 plus
X plus x squared plus X cubed all the
way up to X to the 8th come on almost
there it is alright and I'm going to
multiply this by itself 6 times
polynomial and when you're all done look
at what's in front of the X to the 20th
term that's the answer to this problem
I'm gonna explain why in a second but
first get the connection here's a
problem that's completely a
combinatorial problem it's a counting
problem I turned it into an algebra
problem here's a polynomial to the sixth
power multiply it out when you're all
done look at what's in front of the X to
the 20th that's the answer to this
problem now let's see why what happens
in the algebra mimics what's happening
in this counting and that's why we're
leveraging the power of this algebra
because there might be an easy way of
doing this multiplication and getting
this number in fact there is no easy way
but in other situations there is an easy
way of leveraging the algebra in this
case it's just this big of a pain to
multiply this out and find this number
as it is to solve this directly but
that's not the point the point is I want
to make the connection between the two
seemingly different subjects a
corresponds to how many solutions the
right of this equation how many
different ways we can solve that
equation
this intuitively and then I'm going to
do an example in much more detail so
you'll see exactly why these two things
are really the same
so first intuitively what's going on how
do you get an X to the 20th term from
multiplying something from here times
something from the next one times
something from the next one you've got
six things you multiply together six
possible X's give me one way to get X to
the 20th you could take say X to the 8th
X to the 7 X to the 5 and then Y 1 times
1 times 1
all right good but rook gave me six
different things I took X to the 8th
from the first one of these I multiplied
it by X to the seventh from the second
one multiplied it by X to the fifth from
the third one multiplied it by one one
one from the fourth fifth and six when I
multiply these all together I get 1x to
the 20 ok what does this correspond to
this corresponds to as far as counting
four five six are zero every possible
combination of multiplied nonno meals
God knows I never thought I'd use that
word it just means one of these X's
every possible combinations of those
corresponds to a choice of a value for
one of these ends where the choice of
the value is the exponent that you chose
1 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 0 through 8 for each
one the choice of each of these six can
be 0 through 8 corresponding to the
exponent on the X that you chose when
you choose six of these if the exponents
add up to 20 that means these numbers
added up to 20 if the exponents add up
to 20 then when you multiply that
together you get one more
x2 xx turn how many different ways are
there to choose these exponents so that
you get X to the 20th
that's exactly how many values are going
to be here that's exactly the number
that's going to be here how many
different and ones and twos and threes
and fours and fives and sixes make this
equal to 20 that's going to be the same
number that appears in front of that X
to the 20th I'm going to do this again
in a smaller example but I wanted to
give you a general intuition first so
let me stop for a second this is a deep
idea and you can get it right away or it
can take some time to sink in so let me
stop for a second
other questions so far yeah done meaning
what mean cludes every possible way for
me to choose an one being zero through
eight sure that'll be counted as another
one and it should be because that means
I chose zero for n 1 and 8 7 5 4 4 5 6
yes it will count it and it should count
it yes cuz all these n i's are distinct
right yes order counts in this answer
these are distinct yes other questions
about this John where I got this from I
X to the 20th term from so there are six
multiplications that occur one from here
and then etc six different things from
each one of these terms get multiplied
together well there's a lot more but if
you want to just pick out one X to the
20th term you can pick out say an X to
the 8th from here and X to the 7 from
the next one and X to the fifth from the
next one and a 1 and a 1 and a 1 from
the fourth and the fifth and the sixth
represents a choice of one of the nine
values in one of these terms and we have
six of those choices so I picked one of
the nine values for each of the six
choices and I wrote them here every
unique choice of those values six times
corresponds one-to-one correspondence to
a set of values for these N 1 through N
six and vice-versa if you give me a set
of numbers here I can come up with a
polynomial choice from each one of these
six terms and what's more since these
numbers have to equal 20 those X values
exponents will add up to 20 and that's
exactly what I mean by counting up all
the X to the 20th so makes sense are
there other other questions it's a hard
idea other questions yeah Tony what do
you think yes so let's do that right now
okay and in this one I'll really do the
example in more detail if you're still
not with this idea yet so same kind of
problem we're going to distribute 8
cookies mmm to three kids each kid gets
two to four cookies how was camp today
it was great when you got two cookies
all right this is the same kind of
question it's like this x1 plus x2 plus
x3 equals 8 and the constraint is that
every kid is bigger than or equal to 2
less than or equal to 4 I just wrote it
like this for the heck of it to remind
you that these things correspond to
distributing indistinct things to
distinct things okay so this is what you
meant right Tony this is yeah
oh yeah I wouldn't have used it either
to use tea for Tony they're great all
right there we go we can also change
these constraints for every tea and
we'll see how to do that in a second -
but what would this be like try to make
the analogy even if you don't understand
the idea you can probably get the
analogy down if you really think about
it what would the polynomial be like
here that's going to generate this in
front of the first of all what's it
going to be in front of which term not
x2 the 20 this time but X to the 8 right
squared X cubed X 4 because your choices
here are not 0 through 8 like they were
before your choices here are 2 through 4
how many times do you have a choice 3
different kids you have to make a choice
for each kid ok so this is the
generating function for this problem
yeah what's your question we're gonna do
that we'll do that in a second you get
this so far let me go through this in a
little more detail to make sure
everybody gets this idea and then we'll
do an example where the constraints just
differ one by one and the number in
front of the X to the 8th would be 6 so
it's a whole bunch of things plus 6 X to
the 8th and 6 is the number of ways you
can distribute these things in 2 to 4
confuse a kid all right now let's see
what that means the way to understand
this if this wasn't clear before if this
argument wasn't clear is - in your head
call these things a B and C just so you
don't lose track of where they are and
let's go ahead and write down every
possible combination in this cube that's
going to give us an X to the 8th turn
let's write them all down
there aren't so many there's only six so
we could write them down I don't know
how many there would be in that example
be too many so what's one we got X a
squared X B squared we could use and
then we need X C to the fourth let's
just be very methodical about X a
squared X b cubed X C cubed next one X a
squared X B to the fourth X C squared
how much more no well you have three
more shouldn't you so bad X a cubed x B
cube X C squared X a cubed x B can I do
that's can I just do xB to the well I
guess I miss one X B Square and X C
cubed which one did I miss X X a for X B
squared and X C squared these are all
the possible combinations as I go
multiplying one from here multiplying
one from the net second one to
multiplying one from the third if I
combine them all these are the ones that
add up to eight with the exponents a
from the first B from the second C from
the third a from the first B from the
second C from the third a B and C
represent the particular X I'm talking
about and these exponents represent
which one of them I chose so is that hmm
that's not going to help I really mean
this
your first time you choose annex B your
second time you choose annex C your
third time so this represents that you
choose the square from the first one you
choose the square from the second one
and you choose the fourth from the last
one you can thread your weight through
there's only so many possibilities that
add up to eight and these are all of
them but labeling the X's in each
subsequent term gives you a chance to
see exactly what's happening all right
some I didn't mean ABC there that's a
mistake so fix that sorry Teresa that's
true that's true and the moral is that
sometimes notation becomes really
powerful if it connects to a whole bunch
of other tools that you already know
work for that notation so we're just
throwing everything we did before in a
new language the language of algebra but
you know all sorts of things you can do
with algebra and soon enough
there's going to be something we can do
with algebra that will take us into the
realm of solving a problem that we
couldn't solve before so by changing our
language this language is better for
some things that our old language was
and it's going to take us to new places
so you're right in some ways we're just
restating what we all knew before in a
different language
all right questions about this God or
you have a question thinking let me go
back here I'll ask you guys another
question back to this problem
7 X 2 has to be between 0 & 8 oh yeah
and sorry
using D for Donna now okay let's say I
make a combination of constraints you
all probably know that you can solve
these kind of problems using a
combination of permutations combinations
and inclusion exclusion
it's a horrible kind of a problem to
have to do it it's lots of lots of cases
you have to think about it but now we
can just put it all in terms of
polynomials what polynomial is going to
generate the answer to this question
it's still going to be what shows up in
front of the X to the 20th
but what polynomial do we actually
multiply out to see what's in front of
the X to the 20th what do we use for n1
the polynomial exponents go the choice
is X cubed x 4 x 5th
X 6 and X 7 times what do you get for
this one 1 all the way through X to the
8th what do you get for the next one X
to the 6th plus X to the seventh and the
last one
fourth because you have two three or
four that can be the values there and
you have three of those
so I cube that times x times this long
long polynomial is the generating
function that would give us the answer
to this question if we looked at the
value in front of the X to the 20th term
right is this a better idea
Teresa was saying well now you just turn
it into some algebra thing but it's
really the same idea and if you actually
try to solve this you'd end up doing
very similar to what we've been doing
before you'd multiply it out you'd see
all these cases it isn't much easier to
multiply this out than it is to do all
the cases of the counting in the first
place granted that all may be true and
the power isn't shown in these examples
it's just the way of letting you see the
connection between algebra and counting
yeah these are multiplies yeah those are
multiplies not X's right this times this
times this times this
see you remember the stuff you did with
streams and scheme the stuff you did
with streams is going to start landing
into this topic in about ten minutes and
it's going to come in in a really
striking way questions about this so far
Todd you look pensive you have I don't
know is the short answer
let me think about it I'm not sure good
question
equal to n2 or twice and sewers I guess
I can try to convert it into a set of
constraints like this but I'm not sure I
don't see any way to do it automatically
always hands and it gets a little
complicated I'm sure there's a nice way
to think about that but it's yes yeah
sure oh yeah oh sure yeah this stuff
this kind of symbolic calculations were
originally in a program I guess called
called maxima many many years ago may be
in the mid 70s or early 70s this started
to get done and and since then like
things like Mathematica have just become
you know huge commercial projects where
where they do much more than than this I
mean they'll they'll actually manipulate
this out and give you numbers in front
of these try to give you closed-form
formulas in front and do all sorts of
clever things
there's even new mechanical techniques
for taking any kind of a sequence and
mechanically computing the recurrence
equation from the sequence which is
which was always thought to be something
in the realm only of mathematicians that
it required cleverness that there wasn't
a mechanical way to do that but there is
it turns out and that's not at all easy
that's that's in the last five years so
there's a lot of neat things you can do
with computers yeah yeah ok so that's 20
years ago probably no might be more
maybe 25 all right questions more
questions
yeah what is what are you guys doing
here
gotta go ride the redline I was gonna go
to edu but I heard the red lines even
better except they don't have a turd or
our chairs on the red line all right all
right I gotta come up with some
functions representing sequences the way
you got a sequence from a function is
you just plug in the number 0 1 2 3 into
the function and see what comes out so
I'm going to write some functions up in
the board and you tell me what the
generating functions are these are going
to be going from easy to hard so here's
one function I have N equals 1 anything
you plug in you get 1 what's the
generating function look like if I plug
in 2 I get 1 if I plug in 3 I get 1 it's
not just one it goes on and on and on
okay here's the generating function for
this particular function that means if I
plug in an I go look at the term that
has N in the exponent and I look at the
coefficient in front of it and other
coefficients always want this is the
sequence 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 11 I mean
okay yeah no all right let me say it
again this is a function you can make a
chart here's n here's the value of the
function 1 1 1 1 1 that's the sequence
I'm talking about that represents a
function
you look at X to the N and you look at
what's in front of it so the generating
function for this has a n in front of
the term X to the N if you wanted to
write it it would look like this that's
the generating function I didn't want to
write this symbol down before because
it's probably more confusing than it's
worth but it just means this it means
that the coefficients of these values as
n ranges from 0 to infinity show up in
front of the appropriate term of the
polynomial so if the coefficients are
all ones then one show up in front of
all the polynomial values well here
we're not even connecting its accounting
here we just went back to generating
functions so right and if there's no
constraints an accounting problem
presumably right if there's no
constraints on on this counting thing it
might go forever right
constraints in the function it just goes
on forever right in this case right okay
here's something that you should know
from algebra that makes these kind of
infinite things suddenly turn finite
back in I don't know the first week of
class or something there's a lot of ways
to prove it you can prove it by
induction you could prove it by
multiplying it out what happens when you
multiply this times this you get a copy
of this - a copy of this shifted over
one to the right all the X's fall out
you get one multiply this out and you'll
see that it works so that's something
you should know this very basic
generating function is equal to
something that's more finite looking and
we're actually going to use this in the
opposite way we're going to come up with
generating functions that solve problems
and then convert these generating
functions when we see one minus X we'll
know that that means 1 1 1 1 1 here's
some other ones that you should be aware
of you might be able to figure this out
on the spot you might not what do you
think this one turns into
trick multiply this out and everything
shifts over one and cancels out so if
you have a two down here instead of an a
one then instead of one showing up here
you get 2 and then 2 squared and then 2
cubed yeah yeah you can't just plug in
numbers because this doesn't really work
for numbers in certain ranges right it
only works for numbers between 0 and Y
it only converges for numbers between 0
and 1
it'll it diverges for other numbers like
if it's negative 2 Oh negative half it
it works okay sure I think it I think it
works for negative again it works
between negative 1 and +1 it works in
that radius of 1 okay what do you think
it is if it's 1 minus say ax
plus 8 cubed X cubed
this is not this shouldn't be some kind
of weird mystery how do you know the way
to figure out what's going to work here
is completely algebra it's got nothing
to do with counting it's got nothing to
do with a new idea of generating
functions multiply this through you get
one copy of this multiplying it through
again by ax is going to just shift
everything over 1 and you subtract
because it's a negative so all of the X
terms cancel out and you get 1 so here's
a few you should remember this is the
most general case of it that if you see
a generating function 1 over 1 minus ax
you know that the coefficients that they
generate are a a squared a cubed that's
very very very useful because we're
going to solve problems later and we're
going to be gearing and aiming toward
getting things like this because we know
what they actually generate here's a
situation where we don't have to figure
out how to multiply the thing out we
know exactly what would happen if we
multiplied it all out it look like this
so here's what we're going to be heading
towards later on things like that yeah
borough exactly this is a geometric
series with ax as the multiplicative
factor absolutely right right so it's
really just an example of geometric
series the corresponding right
right so the corresponding function here
is instead of 1 this would be a of n
would be 2 to the N and here a of n
would be a to the N good and this is
really 1 to the N same as 1 so if you
have these functions here are the
coefficients that they generate those
are going to be our ABCs for generating
functions
writing out as a polynomial on purpose
because I want you to try to figure out
what the coefficients that this
generating function generates what are
the coefficients in front of the 1 and
the X and the x squared and the X cubed
and how would you figure it something
like that out look over here this
generating function is this one times
itself it's 1 plus X plus x squared dot
times 1 plus X plus x squared
dot dot dot multiply those two together
term by term
what's the constant term gonna be 1
what's the X term gonna be how'd you get
that how do you get all the X terms how
do you know it's two of them x times one
x times one there's no other way you can
get X from multiplying those two things
out how many x square terms do you get x
squared times 1 1 times x squared X
times X 3 how many X cubed terms do you
get 6 how do you get sex counting for me
no good guess the next one will be a
triangle number how many X cubes do you
get right Alex 4 right 1 times X cubed x
times x squared X cubed times 1 and an x
squared times X in general what do you
get for the next term B 5 X to the
fourth 6 X to the fifth
what's the function that corresponds to
this we'll call it a of n again
what is it and if I want well what is it
if I go here to the first term the
exponent one it's one more than that if
I go here where the exponents - it's one
more than that so the functions n plus 1
function is a of an equal n plus 1 I
want you to think about how we got from
here to here again and I'm going to
write it down in more detail I'm going
to write down the coefficients here in
this way I'm going to call this instead
of I'll call this a of N equals a of N
equals 1 I'm going to give this a new
name we'll call it be a zeros 1 a 1 is 1
a 2 is 1 a 3 is 1 etc now how did we get
B of 0 don't tell me that it's one I
know it's I know it's 1 but how do we
get it we took a of 0 times a of 0 right
zero times a 1 plus a 1 times a 0 now
what we took this one here it's too hard
to chew tricky ok oh yeah
ding those bells what's the next one you
start with this coefficient you multiply
it by the square coefficient a 0 a 2 A 1
a 1 a 2 a 0 B of n now we're going to
use this notation I'm going to write
here B of n this is important we start
out with a 0 right and we connect it
with something out so let's let's call
this I equals 0 we start out with a 0
and it gets connected with what if I is
0 we have and here I is 1 we have n
minus 1 if is 2 we have n minus 2 the
sum of these two things have to add up
to n
starting at zero all the way until I
gets to to end that represents the event
important idea and it's complicated in
its algebra so take a look at it and
think about it again then I calculated
the coefficients in that new expansion
and now I'm telling you exactly how I
calculated each coefficient that if I
wanted the fifth coefficient I got it by
taking the first one from here and the
fifth one from there or the zeroth one
from here on the fifth one from there
plus the second one from here on the
fourth one from there plus the third
from here in the second from there plus
the fourth from here on the first from
there plus the fifth from here on the
zeroeth from there add them all together
and that gives me the fifth on my new
function now in this case all the A's
are ones so when you do this every one
of these products is one times one so
that's why B of two ends up being equal
to not to be F to ends up being three
because you start from zero you go to
two zero one two that's three times you
add ones up together every single time
you do this starting with all ones you
end up getting n plus one so in our case
V of n is equal to the sum I equals 0 to
n of 1 and that equals n plus 1 and
that's how we got this n plus 1 the
reason I did it first in the brute force
way and now in this general is because I
want you to see what happens when you
multiply two generating functions
together when you multiply two
generating
actions together the new constants you
get can be computed according to this
formula and this kind of weird
convolution should remind you of all
those hard problems that we haven't
solved yet right of the of the binary
tree recurrence of the parentheses
recurrence and of the matrices
recurrence they're almost the exact same
thing you start with a 0 you get a n
minus 1 used to go to a 1 you get a n
minus 2 so it's very similar to what we
did there and that'll come back and
we'll do that later but let me stop for
a second again this is what happens when
you multiply two together I think I need
to do another example of this judging
from all the phases so now we're gonna
do this let's say I swear it again so
now I have 1 minus X to the 4th I'm
going to take this sum and square it
without writing out the X's ask yourself
what is the number in front of say X to
the fifth everyone understand what I'm
saying we're gonna do this by working
through our idea before about how to
multiply two generating functions
together I have two generating functions
1 minus x squared 1 over 1 minus x
squared and another 1 minus 1 over 1
minus x squared I'm going to multiply
these two together and try to figure out
what's in front of X to the fifth how do
I do it we'll call that we'll call this
C these what's C of 5 what's the thing
in front of X to the fifth it's going to
be B of B of 0 times B of 5 what does
that mean I guess I couldn't go back to
here to show you what does that mean it
means this one x times the number in
front of the 5 which is a which is a 6
that gives us 6x to the
multiplying this times this the first
thing you do is take the 1 and multiply
it by 6x to the fifth that gives you 6
that's 1 times 6 plus the next thing you
can do to get X to the fifth is to
multiply what's in front of the X by
what's in front of the X to the fourth
so that's going to be 2 times 5 or what
we call it B of 1 times B of 4 B of 2
times B of 3 B of 3 times B of 2 B of 4
times B of 1 and B of 5 times B of zero
there should be six terms all together I
went from 0 to 5 let's add these all up
5 times 2 4 times 3 7 17 29 39 41 51 57
somebody check it stop well it's tough
to get 57 huh 56
these numbers are the sums of n plus
wine right as as n goes from what to
what as then goes from sorry n plus 1
back up I equals 0 to n what is B of I B
of I is I plus 1 what's B of n minus I
and minus I minus 1 what we're really
doing here is make doing this sum now
you could go ahead and multiply this out
and do the sum using all these other
techniques we did at the beginning of
the course too but here we just did it
with numbers and we got 56 all right so
that's one of the hardest things about
generating functions is to see that when
you multiply them together the new
coefficients are calculated in this way
let me do some easier things I jump to
the hard thing and I'll do some easier
things to ease your minds I can see that
this is just this is tough this will
relate back to streams that you did last
year
I know that last year yeah we had a
whole year to let it sink in
formula have an equal one you know one
minus x squared is this formula a of n
equals n plus one what happens if you
just if you just keep multiplying by by
1 over 1 minus X what happens when you
multiply by 1 over 1 minus X in a
recurrence in a generating function this
is a little easier than general
multiplying because it's a very specific
function you're multiplying by let's do
this example specifically what happens
when you do this now's your chance Doug
happens what happens what we did this
the first time upon you in a second John
just hold on when we did this
multiplication we all know we got this
thing here now we're doing it again yeah
John no no I'm I want to do this one
now I'm going back and doing 1 minus X
cubed I'm just doing something different
before I was showing you what happens
when you take two functions and you
multiply them by each other in general
and here I'm showing you what happens
when you just multiply by a very
specific function this one 1 over 1
minus X because this does something very
very natural that comes up in the
streams assignment that you did in in
scheme what does this do to this as far
as coefficients go
before right it does what you call
before partial sums right if you stop at
one you get one if you go to terms down
add up the coefficients one plus one
that gives you two if you go three terms
down add up the coefficients one plus
one plus one it gives you three why does
it do that it's because multiplying by
this is basically taking all of these
terms that are here and kind of pushing
them over to the right each one one at a
time so multiplying by this gives you
partial Sun so if we multiply it by
again we get more partial sums if you
multiply this by this and you want to
know what you get the first coefficient
will be the first one here the second
coefficient will be the sum of the first
two here which is the third coefficient
will be the sum of the first three
four etc these are the triangle numbers
anytime you multiply by this polynomial
the coefficients become the partial sums
of the previous set of coefficients and
you did exactly this when you did the
assignment in streams you did something
exactly like this but now you can see it
in terms of algebra if you did it again
you'll get what's sometimes called the
pier of in numbers you'll get stacks of
triangles like the way you stack
cannonballs right you have a triangle of
three and you put a cannonball on top a
triangle of 1 that's the first triangle
number plus the second triangle number
that's a small stack of cannonballs
what's the next stack of cannonballs you
have ten on the bottom right no six six
on the bottom three on top of that one
on top of that that gives you ten
cannonballs then you can have 10 on the
bottom six on top of that three on top
of that one on top of that that gives
you the next stack accountable
you can only stack cannonballs in
triangular pyramids if you try to stack
them in square pyramids they just fall
down so yeah I think I don't think you
can stack them in square pyramids I
think they're good right you didn't see
the Egyptians use a nice square blocks
for their I mean nice uh round blocks
for their pyramids alright so something
else you should have when you multiply
you get what happened before when you're
multiplied by a particular function you
get partial sums 1 over 1 minus X gives
you partial sums multiplying by that
alright this is probably the hardest
part of generating functions you can do
to make it a little easier I'm going to
do just one little diagram and then I'm
going to skip to something a little
different
this is Pascal's triangle again I showed
you how to get generating functions for
each row
those were finite generating functions 1
plus x squared 1 plus X cubed 1 plus X
to the fourth what if you want a
generating function for the diagonals
what's the generating function for this
function for this 1 over 1 minus X
quantity squared look what happens in
the diagonals of Pascal's triangle the
next diagonal is the partial sums of the
diagonal immediately above it and to the
left 1 plus 2 gives you 3 1 plus 2 plus
3 gives you 6 1 plus 2 Plus 3 plus 4
gives you 10 we never noticed that about
Pascal's triangle before but it's
certainly true the next diagonal is the
partial sums of the diagonal immediately
above it that means we've now got
generating functions for every single
diagonal of Pascal's triangle not only
every row but every diagonal questions
about that all right
this is even easier than before but if I
multiply by X what does the new
generating function look like this
particular one here is 1 over 1 minus X
cubed what happens everything gets
bumped up 1 slot so instead of 1 plus we
get X plus these are X plus 3 X plus so
it doesn't change all that much right it
simply changes that whatever used to be
if we call this say d of n whatever used
to be d of n is now d of n minus 1 it
just shifts everything over it basically
just moves the base case up 1 it doesn't
do much at all multiplied by X but it's
a trick we're going to use later so keep
it in mind if I take say this one and I
add it to this one
and I'm wondering hey what's that new
generating function generate just look
at the coefficients here which are 1 the
coefficients here which are n plus 1 and
them together you get n plus 2 and
that's the new formula for the
coefficients of your new function so
adding is easy you just add up the
formulas for the coefficients
multiplying is tricky you have to do
that convolution of running through all
the possible partial things and adding
them multiplied adding all the
multiplied pairs together that's much
harder but adding is easy
Doug's asking this he says if I multiply
this by X that's just the same as
subtracting 1 from that's what you said
right is it true that's right so doug
has now discovered a 8th grade algebraic
identity through a graduate-level topic
and generating functions you're right
what you said is right you said this has
to be true because of an argument
generating functions that if I shift the
generating function by X it's the one I
started with take away the first term
and well we all knew that from much
simpler ideas I mean just do the algebra
there it's true
so you're right and it seems funny but
it's true it may seem funny but it's
true yes good all right everything's all
the same in math deep down there is no
new idea we're going to do one example
this example is in the book I'm pretty
certain at least it's not an old edition
of the book so well sorry it's that much
it just watch and think is you can find
this in the book the other two examples
are probably exercises in the book but
they're not in the book and I'll do
those next time and you can just take
careful notes on those but here's up
through I want to do the one I'm going
to do today is just a cool counting
problem that turns into a generating
function we're going to get the
generating function make it look like
one of the ones we just analyzed and
then get the coefficients from that
that's our goal that's what we're going
to do the next 10 minutes or so then
we're going to use the same technique to
solve a closed form for Fibonacci
numbers which we've done in a million
other ways we're going to do it using
generating functions and then finally
the end of the whole topic is we're
going to use these generating functions
to solve that parentheses problem
that binary tree problem to get an
explicit number for how many of those
things there are and that's going to be
a long thing it's going to be generating
functions coming up with constants a
funny horrible function finding the
constants is going to need Taylor series
that's going to need about 45 minutes
and that you need a fresh brain for so
so I'll let you clear out for a day
before we do that but now let me just
work on this basic example that
everything's going to come together in
more or less of a not too long of a way
so here we go how many base 10 numbers
are there with n digits and an even
number of zeros it's a counting problem
you can write a recurrence equation for
this you could solve the recurrence
equation using linear non homogeneous
techniques you can solve the recurrence
equation using substitution you can do
all sorts of things with this problem
from previous parts of this class you
could try to analyze it just straight up
with counting we're going to turn this
into a generating function problem
manipulate the generating function
derive the constants get an answer so
this will be an example of using
generating functions to solve counting
and recurrence equations in this case
it's both it's a counting problem and a
recurrence equation ok so far ok get on
with it you think all right so here's my
recurrence equation I'm going to call
this number a sub n a sub n is a number
of base 10 numbers with n digits an even
number of zeros and first let's come up
with a recurrence equation for this this
is sometimes the hard part this is the
part where everybody says well I don't
know how to come up with the recurrence
equation so let's do it
I'm trying to get a base 10 number with
n digits I'm trying to have this depend
on base 10 numbers with smaller numbers
of digits
well let's say I know how many base 10
numbers with n minus 1 digits there are
that have an even number of zeros I can
add on another digit as long as it's not
a zero how many base 10 numbers of n
minus 1 digits with an even number of
zeros are there well we don't know but
we just call that a n minus 1 right it's
the number of answers to our problem
with one less digit and each one of
those we can add on the number the digit
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 or 9 so we have to
multiply this by by 9 but that's not all
of them right because what if the first
n minus 1 digits did not have an even
number of zeros in them what if it had
an odd number of zeros in it then we
would have to add on a 0 but now we have
to figure out how many n minus 1 digit
numbers are there that have an odd
number of zeros in them how do you do
that the total number of n minus 1
digits - the ones that have an even
number of zeros it's that compliment
trick so add on the total number which
is 10 to the N that's the total number
10 to the n minus 1 that's the total
number of n minus 1 digits in base 10
take away the number that have an even
number of zeros that gives us the number
with an odd number of 0 how many with an
even number of zeros a n minus 1 that's
a recurrence equation we're going to try
to solve that now we turn our counting
problem into a recurrence equation and
we'll try to solve it sorry no that's it
of zeros for the first n minus 1 digits
Chris then we have to put a zero here
there's no other choice to make it an
even number so you only multiply by one
that's it the way it is okay so far yeah
we're going to simplify it we'll do it
right here
so a n equals 8 a and minus 1 plus 10 to
the n minus 1 okay that's what you get
and what's the base case here what's a 1
how many one digit numbers are there
we're gonna say it's nine let's define
it to be nine there's nine there's nine
numbers that okay the only the only
single digit that doesn't have an even
number of zeros is zero itself which is
an odd number of zeros okay
all right you take it or leave it that's
how we're defining it we're going to try
to come up with a generating function
for this sequence for the sequence you
know a 0 a 1 by the way what's a 0 got
no digits we have to decide what this
means what we have no digits at all how
many no digit numbers are there with an
even number of zeros in them so we just
say that there is no a zero no a zero
okay so we'll start with a one fine
should know that when you do define a
zero people define it to be one okay so
if you wanted to define how many are
there with no digits at all
that have an even number of zeros there
is one no digit number with an even
number of zeros the no digit number I
mean it is one of them so so here's what
the generating function looks like one
no digit numbers nine one digit number
anybody know how many two-digit numbers
there are without zeros use this
recurrence equation figure it out I got
one eighty two eighty two other people
say eighty two should we do one more
just the torture or zero in the yeah
sure sure
82 is 6 56 plus 107 alright these
numbers get pretty big fast let's not do
any more instead let's try to come up
with an actual function that G of X is
equal to turn that into something that
looks like 1 over 1 minus something that
we can deal with and then get an actual
closed form for our a n that's our goal
look now to manipulate something like
this we're going to need to use the
summation notation because it's very
hard to manipulate this stuff and see
what's going on without it so this is
going to be a little maybe about five
six lines of algebra and then we'll get
our answer so watch what we get the
summation and zero to infinity of a and
X to the N that's the fancy way of
writing it it just means the
coefficients are the a ends and the
polynomials are the X to the ends those
are the first few terms of this okay a
zero is one let's do a little algebra
where I shouldn't motivate this a little
bit instead of making it seems so
magical but the idea is that when you
have recurrence equations that are based
on one less we're going to take this
function and multiply it by X because it
shifts it over and then things start to
cancel out and be nice just kind of like
the geometric series subtraction trick
so in order to do that the first thing
we do is take the constant out and then
you're going to see that we can factor
out an X so we take the constant out now
what's left let's write this out and
doesn't go from 0 to infinity anymore it
goes from 1 to infinity and what's
inside let's actually write out this
recurrence equation in place of a n
we're going to write this there's the X
to the N and in place of a M we're going
to write what it equals a a and -1 plus
10 and to the minus 1 okay I didn't do
much yet but if I have to manipulate
this with dot dot dots it would get ugly
so I'm manipulating it this way
from each of these terms because then I
get back to a situation where I start
with a constant so G of X minus 1 equals
me do it step-by-step I know I'm going
to lose everybody if I don't just do it
nice and easy
second piece okay I just split up the
two sons I separated them out okay next
step now pull out an X and in this case
1/8 from these terms what do I get in
the first timer if I pull out an 8x
X and minus 1 right because I factored
out an X so all the X ends turn to X and
minus ones and here what do i get if i
factor out an X 10 to the N minus 1 X to
the I minus 1
believe it or not
bit here if my end starts from one and
goes to infinity and this is a n minus
one X to the N minus one then what are
the actual values of the indices here
when n is one this is a zero and
therefore I'm really starting here at
zero and going upwards so I'm just going
to rewrite this a little bit
instead of writing n equal 1 and minus 1
here I'll write N equals zero to
infinity and I'll change these n minus
ones to ends because this will look a
lot like what we've had before cuz you
don't because like eyes I've been using
ends the whole time all because well
because I use n here no I'm not yeah I'm
not doing anything fake and here right
right I'm just changing all the N minus
1 stand because now n is starting back
at 0 instead of 1 in other words these
are really generating functions again
that have constant terms and I want you
to to see him that way
recurrence equation that I started with
that was the whole idea of doing this
algebraic manipulation is to shift over
plop around and get what I started with
this is the sum of all the a n starting
from zero going to infinity in front of
the X to the N polynomial terms and it's
a 0 a 1 a 2 a 3 that's just what I
started with so I get ax times GX that
trick is very much like doing geometric
series you take away the constant term
you factor out the X you look really
desperately for what you started with
and you hope you find it well but now I
got this thing on geez
10 to the N in front of the X to the nth
term what's an easy way to write that
function 1 over 1 minus 10 X so that
infinite sum now turns into something
finite that's why I spent all that time
at the beginning reminding you that
we're looking for stuff like this we're
looking for stuff where the something to
the N goes with X to the end because you
can convert it back reverse into a
geometric series which gets rid of the
infinity if you're thinking God knows I
can barely follow this step-by-step how
would I ever do it on my own
that's a completely natural feeling this
is a deep topic it really is and you're
going to get two days on it and you'll
see some cool things with it and you'll
be expected to do a couple problem sets
with it you're not going to be expected
to be expert with this stuff but you'll
appreciate it at least it's a really
cool topic here's what we get now GX
minus 1 equal 8 x GX plus x times
something finite we're almost finished
we're going to get a value for GX in
just a second all right
I don't enjoy doing really complicated
things and making to feel like you're in
the jungle I don't like it I just
there's no other way to do this the
first time it's just hard let's solve
for G of X here let's go to all the G of
X's on one side so I'm going to pull
this over here what do I get
x over 1 minus 10 X plus 1 ok I put all
the G's on one side when I factored out
the 1 - ADA and now I get G of X look
we're almost done look at this this is
so cool
let's here add this together for me
somebody won - 9 x over 1 - 10 x all
right ok so now I get G of x equals 1 -
9 x over 1 - 8 x times 1 minus 10 you
wish to guy we were done right now where
we're gonna be what are the coefficients
of that we didn't have a slightest clue
but now I can refer you back with a
one-step deal because I know you all
know how to convert this into partial
fractions right remember that you don't
remember it doesn't matter well who is
that I missed a good one right add those
two on the right together you'll see you
get the thing on the left I'm skipping
the steps of how you'd find it you'd
find it by partial fractions you'd set
this up into two fractions you'd find
out what the top pieces are and you find
out that both top pieces are a half you
can multiply it out and check it better
work yes you have 5x it better work all
right now why do we want to do that
because these things you know what
coefficients they build right those are
those basic building blocks that I spent
time explaining before at the beginning
of the day 1 - 8 X 1 over 1 minus 8x
that generates
powers of 10 so here's what I'm going to
do I'm going to factor out a 1/2 get 1
over 1 minus 8x 1 over 1 minus 10x and
finish up like this therefore my
coefficients a n are 1/2 whatever this
generates plus whatever this generates
this generates a to the N and this
generates 10 to the N