selection of different ways to solve
recurrence equation z' you're going to
add them to your two set of tools and
we're going to talk about a whole
you'll be able to solve pretty much
anything that will come up in most
computer science applications recurrence
equations come up most often in
algorithms and they come up most often
particular kinds of algorithms where you
split the problem into two halves or
three thirds where you divide it not
where you break it up into n in n minus
1 and 1 or n minus 2 and 2 that's
usually a bad way to break up a problem
the best ways to divide it that makes
the algorithms generally faster and
those kind of algorithms which are
recursive algorithms that split a
problem into two different fractions
those are called divide and conquer
algorithms there's a whole two three
weeks we'll talk about this in
algorithms and we'll talk about how to
solve these recurrence equations so I
get up to it in algorithms I'll say hey
remember how to do this you'll say no
but I'll be able to review it in five
times the speed is if you've never seen
it before so that's the idea you're
going to see it now first all right
questions so far all right so let me
give you the big picture I'm going to
write down all the different methods
that I'm going to go through with you to
solve recurrence equation Xin the order
that we're going to do them and the
order that we have done them so these
are methods for solving recurrences in
doing this today we're going to come up
with a lot of algebra don't get too
bogged down in the algebra if you lose
track of the algebra don't lose track of
the technique that's behind it
methods for solving recurrences one the
one that I call repeated substitution
and knowing what sums add up to
of developed that name over the last few
years because people have called it that
in a book the first time I ever saw this
theorem it wasn't called the master
theorem and I'm not sure anybody really
knows who created this I think it just
kind of grew with lots of different
people contributing to it I'll tell you
what this means but this is basically
somebody went ahead picked a whole class
of recurrence equations did repeated
substitution and wrote down and proved
what the general complexity of the
answer was based on things that you
could look at before you bothered even
doing the substitution so it's a
shortcut for bothering to do all the
sums and it takes care of a whole whole
class of problems that you normally
would have to do with method one and
I'll talk about that later so this is
usually used for the class of algorithms
called divide and conquer this is the
one that you see most in computer
science that's why they call it the
master theorem and algorithms next
method a change of variables sometimes
when you change the variables of a
recurrence equation you take something
that looked ugly at first and then it's
something that's a lot easier to work
with you can solve the second thing that
you came up with and then convert it
back to a solution in the original thing
by reversing the change of variables and
I'll show you a couple examples of that
for guess the answer and prove by
induction
concentrate primarily not on the perfect
closed form for the answer but on the
overall complexity the master theorem
and guessing the answer improving it by
induction is guessing the overall
complexity improving it by induction so
I have a recurrence equation I don't
have the slightest idea what it would
sum up to but I have a good feeling
that's a linear time recurrence equation
I think it's order n so I go ahead and
guess that and I could prove it's true
by induction even though I don't have to
actually calculate the sum so that's a
very nice powerful technique
there's two more there's a whole class
of recurrence equations that don't come
up that much in computer science come up
less frequently than the divide and
conquer
but do come up nevertheless and they're
a class that is completely well
understood and has a mathematical theory
just like differential equations has a
mathematical theory and we'll go through
this this will be the standard kind of
calculus stuff where you just learn
mechanics and you do a few examples and
you repeat them this is relatively easy
from a math point of you don't have to
discover much you learn the technique
you repeat it and it's called linear
homogeneous equations no genie Hattie's
bahama genius close enough I'm a genius
all right all right linear homogeneous
equations and then finally as if you
thought you'd never see it again
doing diagonalization ok so you all are
going to have to go back and remember
how to do that and I'll do one example
of this here in class we're actually
going to solve the Fibonacci recurrence
equation using linear algebra like you
did like you did last semester two
semesters ago all right so here are the
methods we've done this one check we're
going to do this one right now and if I
have time today I'm going to go through
these two because the ideas they are
easy and then on Monday
I'm going to try to finish these two and
then Tuesday I can move on to some
different things that's my goal worst
cases we get through the end of this
Tuesday okay that's our big picture for
the next couple of days you'll get all
of the intuition behind the proof that
you ever wanted through these two
examples so in some sense it'll be proof
by example which is no proof at all but
if the examples general enough it really
is a proof so here are the two examples
that we'll start with well actually make
it three here's one here's two
that turned up with these recurrence
equations you can tell they're dividing
conquer because the smaller case is a
fraction of what you started with rather
than something subtracted from it
because it's divided by two divided by
two could be divided by three or divided
by ten there's a lot of other things it
could be but in these cases it's divided
by two the numbers in front here for
dividing conquer algorithms need to be
constants not ends otherwise it's just
too many subproblems so you'd like to
keep this two two and three and then
there's this combining factor which is
the amount of time it takes to take your
subproblems and combine them together so
if you're doing recursion these
represent the recursive calls and this
represents the amount of work your
algorithm does in between recursive
calls or before after the recursive call
keep in mind every recursive algorithm
you write has a recurrence equation
associated with it that says how much
time it takes every recursive algorithm
you write has a proof by mathematical
induction that it actually does what
it's supposed to do you assume that the
smaller case does what it's supposed to
do and you're connecting code make sure
the bigger case does what it's supposed
to do so induction is the proof on any
recursive algorithm recurrence equation
is the time complexity in any recursive
algorithm they all go together and these
are all dividing conquer algorithm by
yourself into to the gate yes for the
purposes of doing the computation will
confine ourselves to powers of two but
it won't actually affect the overall
complexity if we could just put floors
and ceilings and and it will just look
Messier but let's assume that our size
of our thing is always two to the K so
we can just go ahead and do n over two n
over four and never worry about
fractions it's a good question all right
ah this comes from a real-life algorithm
actually so does that but this one's
very well-known this comes from an
algorithm sometimes called merge sort in
merge sort
you're going to sort a whole bunch of
elements okay and here's how I do it I
split it in half I give half to Teresa
and I say go sort this for me please
and I
have to Tony I say go sort this for me
please they each sort it they come back
to me and now I have two sorted lists
each half the size and what do I do with
them I'm er I get I give him the Michael
Michael merge these for me and he takes
these two sorted lists and he merges
them which is a much faster process than
sorting because merging it's kind of
just like they're you compare you keep a
pointer at the top and whichever ones
bigger goes interleaving the cards as
you go it's proportional to the time
that it takes to run through both lists
it takes linear time to merge so this is
the merging step and here are the two
resource of calls each half the size
this comes from merge sort there's lots
of lots of algorithms that have the same
recurrence equation here's another one
with the same recurrence equation we'll
call this I made it up on the spot sort
all right we take a list of numbers we
want to sort it so I find the median
that's the number that's that's the
middle number not the average the middle
number I take all the numbers that are
bigger than that and I give them the
Peter and I say sort these for me I take
all the numbers that are equal or
smaller than that
and I get in the Neil and I say sort
these for me and they come back with
sorted lists and what do I do with them
I just stick them together and I'm done
so where's the work still two problems
each one is half the size still this is
the same but where is this n come from
right finding the median it's the work
that I have to do at the beginning to
find that middle that middle spot to
find that center element it's not
obvious at all how to do that in in
linear time but you can do it in linear
time real clever algorithm does it in
linear time so that's another algorithm
that that has the same recurrence
equation we're going to solve this see
what it equals
you should still know how to do what
we're about to do but it would help it
would help to be able to short-circuit
it if you can we're going to do the same
thing here I'm not going to talk about
algorithms anymore but this comes from
problem where you can split it into
halves but you have to give it to three
different people it's a little bit like
that towers of Hanoi that doesn't work
problem right split it into half through
three separate half towers of Hanoi and
then do a little work connecting them
technique again is to get rid of these
capital T's I'm going to do this just
enough to get a pattern and then we're
going to write down what our pattern is
so 2t n over 2 is 2t n over 4 plus n
over 2 that's using this equation again
in order to get a value for T n over 2
and now we're going to take that value
and substitute it in place of T n over 2
and get a new equation for T of n it's
going to be 2 times all of this so it's
2 squared T n over 4 plus n plus 2 and
divided by 2 that's our pattern ok so
far if I do it many many times who
thinks they can see the pattern already
anybody see the pattern already I know
Sam sees the pattern already even though
he's not telling me who else sees the
pattern who thinks they know it Chris do
you know it if you do in our times this
becomes 2 to the R T over 2 to the R and
then what is a Sun look like let's try
to leave in all the details we can so n
plus 2 n over 2 plus how far does it go
what happens next
am i messing you up no I just
2 squared let's do it maybe it is Tony
you're way ahead of me right if you do
this twice you got two ends if you do it
three times you're going to have three n
so not let's actually rewrite this easy
to to the R and over two to the R plus R
times N and we'd like to make this T
disappear how do we make this T
disappear we need n divided by 2 to the
R to be equal to 2 1 that means N equals
2 to the R and R equals log base two of
n there's a convention that I mean base
two I'm just going to write LG it saves
me from writing the little two
underneath all the time so R equals log
base two of n let's put it in this
becomes one T of 1 is 1 to 2 the log
base 2 of n is n so when R equals log of
n I get n plus and log in and that's big
theta of what big theta n log n because
the end part is smaller than the n log
in part you should know that theorem
that if you have the sum of a lot of
different functions then the big theta
of the whole sum is big fate of the
biggest one you can prove that theorem
and you probably know it intuitively
already just reminding you so this is
big theta n log N and that's no surprise
because as you know sorting algorithms
that are good generally take n log n
that's the best you can really do you
just said that you only have to look at
your biggest term series I
oh when if you have a son I should say a
finite well you're talking about this or
this and you're saying this is big theta
N squared and this is big theta and
cubed and well a good point I wasn't
talking about things like this I was
talking about things that look like this
things are not in terms of n so there's
there's an implication here that there's
something else going on but good right
try to imagine that there was an N
squared here also because that's the
third example I want to do so that when
we get to that third example we don't
have to go through the whole thing from
scratch but we can change the
appropriate places more quickly we're
going to do one example here with n then
we're going to do an example here with N
squared okay here's the first step as
before TN over to here let me get some
help
what's TN over to going to be we're
going to substitute in for this so we
need to know what TN over 2 is 3 to the
n over 4 plus n over 2 every place you
see an ad you put in your n over 2 and
now we're going to take this value and
put it back into here so Anthony it's
good to see you here instead of watching
me virtually find out what I got here
good
multiplied by that through so you get n
over 2 plus and plus 3n over 2 good
would happen three cubes T and over two
cubes plus n plus three and over two
term comes from the fact that we
multiply these old terms by 3 over 2 so
this became 3n over 2 this became 3 over
2 squared N and then we had the original
n from our equation the next time it
would multiply each of these again by 3
over 2 so let's write down our general
result here in terms of our T over N is
3 to the R T and divided by 2 to the R
plus N and I'm going to factor out the
end because it appears in every place
exactly once let's write down what we
get 1 plus 3 halves plus 3 halves
squared all the way up to what's the
last term this exponent here is one less
than the exponent there so we go all the
way up to 3 halves to the R minus 1 good
that's an R all right so your geometric
series experts should be able to add
this up it goes up to the next exponent
3 halves to the R and you divide by the
difference between what is 1 between 1 &
3 halves the distance between 1 & 3
halves is is 1/2 you divided by 1/2
that's multiplying by 2 so this whole
part here is 2 times 3 halves to the R
- this thing and it's one right if
you're not sure where this turned into
this we've done it a few times and you
can go back and review it separately
make a note to yourself review geometric
series the trick is to call this X
multiply both sides by three halves - a
subtraction solve for X and you'll get
this you could all do it I know if you
had the time and focused on it most
right so here again we want our to be
equal to log in same thing as before
because we want this to turn into t of
one and you want the t of one to
disappear so you get R as log ins 3 to
the log n plus n times 2 to the 3 halves
log n minus 1 LG means base 2 but they
are all in base 2 definitely they're
definitely in base 2 and they're all
relative to each other a constant so it
probably won't matter
going to prove it right now in a couple
seconds and remind you of that you
learned it before a couple months ago
this is a good thing to know that if you
have a number raised to the log to to
some other number that you can basically
swap these two and that's identical so
how do I convince you this is true I'm
going to resort to something else that I
think you will remember you probably all
remember this because I made a big deal
about it
B of C anybody remember that identity
log base a of C the B's in some ways
cancel that's an e good you can prove
this with the rules of logarithms or you
can just remember it but this is going
to immediately imply that this is true
and there's a lot of ways to see it this
is one way let's look at these equations
and take the log base 3 of both sides
the reason we're going to do that is
because log base 3 of 3 to the something
equals just the exponent so take the log
base 3 of this left side what do you get
log base 2 event taking the log base 3
of both sides the log base 3 here is log
base 3 of n to the log base 2 of 3
question mark question mark the log of
something raised to a power is the log
base 2 of 3 times log base 3 of n ok I
just brought the exponent out in front
that's true and the threes cancel yes in
a way so the fact that these two are
equal depends completely on the fact
that this equation is true and this
equation is true because you all
remember that from two months ago
whatever you remember is true get used
to the fact that when you see stuff like
this you can switch the numbers I'm
completely serious because you want to
think of it notation wise notation helps
a lot the fact that you can switch these
numbers is going to make your
manipulation fast don't go into the tank
and rediscover this every single time
you use this make sure that if you have
to convince yourself it's true you can
but once you do turn that into a black
box turn the neurons off as far as why
it works and just start thinking about
this mechanically get it to be automatic
because then you'll recognize patterns
so now we're going to go back to here
and try to put our automatic gears in
gear and use this information let's see
3 to the log base 2 n becomes what and
to the log 3 well that's something it
looks reasonable and to some number you
can do log base 2 of 3 and your
calculators you can figure out what it
is plus 2 n times what is this going to
be n to the log has
now drop the - water what about these
two which one is going to be bigger the
same let's check LG right well we'll
check it in a minute but before we check
it I want you to notice the following
thing that happens when you do these
problems you always get two pieces in
your final answer you get the piece that
came from this part and you get the
piece that came from this part this is
the part that winds up your recursions
that keeps track of the structure and
this is the part of all the work that it
takes to glue those pieces back together
sometimes the gluing is the dominant
factor I do a lot of work when all my
friends come back and give me the
answers and if I include all the gluing
that their friends did when they got
their answers it all adds up to this and
sometimes the gluing is trivial and
nobody does anything except just pass
results back and then the actual
construction of the tree and how many
people are actually involved becomes a
dominant factor this is the number of
people and the number of recursive calls
in the structure of it this is the
gluing that gets done at each step the
master theorem is a way of deciding
which one of these is dominant if either
one and then quickly deciding what the
big theta should be we're doing it by
substitution here we haven't hit the
master theorem yet but we'll hit it soon
we're going to compare these two in this
case and see which one is bigger so this
is n to the log three and let's simplify
this a little bit Sam's right we don't
need the minus one that's noise in the
big theta picture this is two to the N
times n to the log three-halves so it's
2 to the n log 3 over 2 plus 1 ok
2 is equal to 1 so minus 1 plus 1 is
going to cancel and these two are
exactly the same so what's the overall
complexity of this algorithm neither one
dominates they're both the same well you
know what the master theorem is going to
tell you to do in these situations it's
going to tell you hey forget about this
sum why bother adding it together if
this is going to be the same thing where
did this come from
here's the original equation where did
that number come from came from there
base here it just disappeared but it's
supposed to be there it's log base 2 if
you knew that this was going to be the
dominant factor you could just say the
complexity overall is n to the log this
base of this number that's what the
master theorem does it checks it all in
advance and it says in this kind of
situation you can just look at these two
numbers and that's your big theta and
that's what happens here and I'll give
you the criterion and when you can do it
and we'll do a few examples
quick quick quick just by looking at the
numbers but right now I want you to see
the summation so you see the distinction
all right questions so can we really
ignore the two enter yeah adding any
power that's greater than 1 however
small that's good I mean you have to cuz
you have to get an enormous and good to
be insignificant you're saying can I
ignore this 2 here well I was just
saying what was it is a minus 100
absolutely mark 3 is so close to end
you'd have an enormous number of n but n
n is strictly a small Oh n to the log 3
this is really bigger than this
asymptotically obviously and I agree
that that you need big
to see that happen but but theoretically
this is a worse algorithm this is a
worse algorithm than this linear is
better than this
I should mention one thing just because
this is coming up now before I go on to
the N squared case and show you what
happens I want to say this because this
gives you a big picture about algorithms
and the maybe the difficulty that theory
sometimes has for catching up with
practice this is good theory and it
gives you a way of organizing algorithms
into a hierarchy but let me give you an
example of an algorithm that's a
real-life algorithm that has a
particular complexity and the complexity
is worse than linear but for all intents
and purposes in a real physical life
universe it will be completely linear
even though the theory says it's worse
than later so that means a theory in the
practice are kind of breaking down there
but it's still interesting and I'll show
you this in just in a couple seconds
this function takes a number and raises
two to the power in a stack as many
times as that number is so for example f
of 1 means you have just one stack of
two's on top so that's 4 f of 2 is going
to be good F of 3 is going to be no 2 to
the 16 just the way I defined it that
the number of twos in the stack F of 3
is 2 to the 16 right it means I got two
and then three twos in a tower to the
two to the 2 to the 2 so 2 to the 16
64,000 something 65,000 536 all right
powers of 2 people
all right F of 4 yeah I'll just get my
recursive friends to help me this number
is a huge number this number is bigger
than the atoms in the universe probably
it's a big number
ok you're not going to ever make a
computer that has this much memory even
if your gateway right Pentium inside but
2 to the 65,000 is a big number so once
you get to 4 or 5
this is just a huge function now here's
the inverse of this function it's called
log star n if I put in 65,000 and 2n
here this tells me 3 if I put in 2 to
the 65,000 and 2n here it tells me for
this number for all practical sized
inputs in the universe or in any
conceivable universe is less than or
equal to 4
it's just never bigger than that I know
conceivably it grows without bound if
you put in 2 to the gazillion this
number will sooner or later get as big
as you want but not in real life
in real life it's 4 or less there is an
algorithm that uses a set data structure
that I talked about briefly when we
talked about sets called a union-find
data structure you construct sets and
the two things you're able to do with
this data structure is given an element
find the set that it's in and given two
sets merge them together it's a data
structure that you could have as an
assignment and scheme you could store it
in lists if you wanted to but the way
this data structure is implemented is
that it's very fast and when you go
ahead and solve the minimum spanning
tree problem with this data structure
instead of the usual n log n time
algorithm for minimum spanning tree you
get an N log star and algorithm for
minimum spanning tree so somebody writes
this up shows a good use of Union fine
gets a PhD says I have improved the N
log n to n log star n good job did they
come up with a linear time algorithm no
this is theoretically worse than linear
time practically speaking we all know
that this is for an or less for anything
in the universe so practically speaking
it really is less than linear time so
this begs the question of what a better
theory might be when you get into
strange things like this but it's
something you should be aware there are
weird functions that that you really
don't see the asymptotic stuff
describing what really happens and
there's one example back to this problem
again we solve this and we said it was
big theta n to the log 3 and now I want
to know what happens
glues it together instead of being n
turns out to be N squared I warned you I
was going to do this in advance maybe
some of you actually did it I am getting
a little tired of going through all the
details of the algebra you're probably
getting tired of it too so if you don't
mind me short-circuiting this I'll tell
you what you get in that T of n step
with the R times and we'll compare it to
what we got before I got the same thing
for the recursive part that part doesn't
change at all the only part that changes
is the glueing part but here's my new
some for the glueing part instead of N
on the outside I get N squared and on
the inside instead of one plus three
halves plus three halves squared plus
three-halves cubed all the way up to
three-halves for the r minus one what i
get is one plus 3/4 plus 3/4 squared
plus 3/4 cubed plus 3/4
ahead and solving this geometric series
which one of these terms is dominant
this one is it doesn't give to squats
what this ends up being as long as it's
bigger than one or as long as it's a
constant as long as it's bigger than
zero this adds up to some number times N
squared this is less than N squared
right it's one point something so we
don't care about this it gets dominated
by the gluing part the master theorem
keeps track of which part is going to be
dominant tells you in advance and
mentions therefore that in this case
where the gluing part is dominant the
complexity has nothing to do with these
numbers but is simply the same
complexity as a single gluing stage big
theta n squared okay who has a question
so far so there's two possibilities
either this part's dominant or this
part's dominant so far we have those two
possibilities the third possibility was
the first thing I did today when I did
2n over 2 and I added n what was the
answer to this recurrence equation it
was big theta what and log in what
happens there is that neither one really
dominates you kind of get the perfect
balance of splitting and gluing and what
results from a perfect balance of
splitting and gluing is this gluing
function gets an extra factor of log n
algorithm and you know all these things
in advance you should know how much
slack you have as far as how many
subproblems you're going to divide if
you know what the complexity is going to
turn out to be based on this number in
this number then you know if I divide it
into two parts how many different pieces
I can have and still keep the algorithm
under N squared how much my gluing
procedure is allowed to take before it
ends up being so dominant that it
doesn't make a difference how carefully
I split the problems knowing this
in advance helps you design algorithms
not just analyze them when you're done
but it helps you plan how you want them
to be it's really important so that's
what the master theorem is going to
summarize and I'm going to put it up on
the board right now and you got to be
careful because there's a lot of
conditions in this theorem let me be
very specific now I said that one of
these is going to dominate and the
master theorem tells us which one when
everything's perfectly balanced it turns
out that the sum also dominates the
recursive part but it doesn't dominate
it equal to itself it dominates it with
an extra factor of log N and in some
sense that's I think the ideal kind of
balance you could you could wear one
doesn't well you could but in those
cases we know we just pick one of them
you could they could be equal a good
time yes so this is big fade up and
square because that's dominating that
sum of there's four times three quarters
to the N minus 1 yeah this is what I get
exactly did I mess up I don't know I
don't know either I thought this just
ended up being something smaller but
maybe I'm wrong let's let's check that
in a second here's the master theorem
recurrence equations that look like this
division of the size of each of those
subproblems some function for gluing the
answers together and it divides it into
three categories category 1 2 & 3 and
the categories compare this function to
some combination of these numbers a and
B here's what it compares case 1 F of N
equals big theta n log B eggs if F of N
and n log BA are the same that's one
case the other two cases are when one is
bigger and when when one's smaller we'll
do an example in a second let me just
write down the other cases by bigger and
smaller here
I mean asymptotically bigger and smaller
asymptotically or one smaller ones
bigger in this case the overall
complexity is n to the log B a times log
n that's like the first example I did
today
where you get that extra log n factor in
this case it's just playing that's right
big theta in this case it's just plain n
to the log ba that's like the second
example I did that's like the 3 T n over
2 plus an example and in the third case
I meant to do an example where the other
one was dominant namely f events those
are the three possibilities this saves
you all the boring work and summarizes
it all in one nice result let's do some
examples which one of these is bigger
and squared is bigger therefore this
should be N squared is bigger therefore
this should be big theta n squared so
the answer to your question is probably
where I said take my word for it you
shouldn't have taken my word for it I
probably got that some wrong or I did
something incorrect there but it should
have worked out to N squared and I'm not
sure what I did geometric sequence
dr. was free water mm-hmm unit yeah yes
yes yes - one mmm
one - oh and then the one multiply N
squared would be the done oh yeah that
would have been more helpful yeah yeah I
understand what you're saying Burroughs
right right but Rho said I reversed the
the minus one it should have been one -
and and you may very well be right
whatever was I the mistake was an
algebra mistake and I know that the kind
of mistakes you all come to me and say
well why did you take off for that well
I make these mistakes and I apologize I
should have been more careful right in
the Sun okay let's try each of these we
need to compare the functions to log of
base this of this number so let's try to
do it Hey Joe what do you know help me
out we're comparing n to the log of of
what ends of the log base 3 of right
what's the log base 3 9 3 2 right so 3 3
you shall count to 3 neither shall you
count to 4 except on we're going to get
that movie next time log base 3 of 9 is
2 so that's N squared so N squared is
bigger that means which case are we
talking about talk about case two this
guy is bigger that means that the order
of this algorithm is N squared
but you should know when you're
designing the algorithm oh I've got this
built-in you know if it was 4 and 2 it's
also B squared okay get used to if these
were equal if it was 3 & 3 what would
happen then 3 & 3 log base 3 of 3 so
it's n that means the two are the same
you don't average them too the two are
the same no you get n log n okay if you
had three problems of size three each
with an N gluing factor you get n log n
as your result if you have sick if you
have nine problems it ends up being N
squared what if you had five problems
five sub-problem it'd be log base 3
five is that bigger or smaller than n
asymptotically it's bigger and what
would the asymptotic complexity of your
algorithm be if the end to the one point
God knows something and that's why if
you ever read in the textbook or in a
paper the complexity of this algorithm
is n to the one point seven three two
and you're wondering well what kind of
weird fractional loop gave this guy end
to the one point seven three two
it comes from these kind of recurrence
equations right not every complexity is
just the loop in a loop so that it's N
or N squared or n cube you get it from
here one point six something all right
this one what's the deal here can you
use this
of it as you have to write it as n over
B so if you write this as n over a
number it's n divided by 5/3 so it's the
log of log of one log base five thirds
of one how do you get one anything to
the zero is one so the fact that this is
3/5 is kind of just the red herring
could be any fraction at all
log base of anything to the one is zero
and to the zero is a constant this is a
constant they're the same so the
complexity of this algorithm is a
constant times log n this is big theta
long again this is big theta and squares
this is just as good as binary search
you don't have to divide something
exactly in half and glue it together
with one guess that's what binary search
is you can divide it into something a
little bigger than half in fact if this
was 9/10 and it would still be log n as
long as you're taking a constant
fraction away
eh even if it's nowhere near half you're
still getting a log n complexity the
last ones yeah yeah because you have to
write it as n divided by a number you
have to match that that pictured row so
so 3/5 n is the same as n divided by 5/3
ok that's a good question I should have
made that clear this so you have to get
the number down there somehow although
you should keep in mind that in this
particular case it wouldn't really
matter either way because any number to
the 0 is 1 so you get constant and
constant what about here what do we
compare in here log base 4 of 3 to 2 n
log n log base 4 of 3 is what between 1
& 2 right no smaller than 1 less than
linear and this is bigger than linear so
this is bigger so the complexity of this
algorithm is going to be n log n hook
question all right so now I have to wait
on a right question now I have to tell
you what I really mean by these less
than equal signs and greater science I
kind of fudged one little thing less
than greater than I kind of fudge it and
I said well asymptotically and I let it
go and nobody needled me because it
wasn't obviously wrong but now we're
getting up to this problem and I want to
tell you exactly what I mean and what
the theorem says the theorem says that
if you're greater than or less here it's
got to be by some polynomial amount it
can't be just bigger by a log n factor
it's got to be bigger by by an end to
the something okay otherwise a theorem
won't work there only works when this
greater or less than is by a polynomial
factor so let's go back and compare this
one here we get n to the one point
something say 1.3 and we have n times
log n
is it okay to use our trick is it
polynomial e bigger
is point point eight or something right
so is this polynomial e bigger yes or no
well it's certainly log in bigger but
it's also n to the point two bigger
right it's n to the something bigger
it's the difference between log base
four of three and one so you do have
that little bit extra that you can still
grab on to if this were exactly n then
you couldn't use the master theorem
because they only have a log and extra
factor but we still have enough to get a
polynomial time a polynomial improvement
let me write it up here and to the point
eight versus n log n this is n to the
point two times log and bigger that's a
polynomial and that's okay the
difference between point eight and one
okay if it was just log in you couldn't
do it so let me give you an example that
you can't use the master theorem for and
then I'll tell you what you do when you
can't use it so if this was an N log and
you couldn't use it absolutely exactly
exactly
good Michael good we have a question
you're thinking about something no okay
let me do one example where you can't
use it so everything we did so far is
right but you got to know what that
means
there's also by the way there's another
condition here that I'm not even going
to tell you some particular condition
about f of n it's an obscure condition
that you rigorously need to have be true
for this theorem to work but it's almost
always true for any functions that
you'll see and I won't bother even
telling you what it is and it'll never
come up but you should realize it that
the real theorem has some peculiar
condition on F of N and and that exists
too and I'm not even sure our book even
goes into it I know the Rivest
algorithms book would tell you what the
condition has to be in Africa but I
don't think I think our book just says
assume F of n is some polynomial because
they
they're all the right functions this is
just n this is my guess this is a login
factor large or asymptotically but
that's not enough for us to use the
theorem it does not fit into big theta
it does not fit into less than or
greater than polynomial e there are gaps
in this theorem this theorem does not
divide every one of these recurrence
equations into one of three categories
you can fit into one of these three or
you could be out in limbo this is an
example that's out in limbo
it's neither big theta of each other nor
is it a polynomial time greater it's
just log n greater so this doesn't work
and what do you do you got to go back to
your substitution drawing board and
actually go ahead and calculate it okay
in doing this you get a really really
interesting sum which comes up in a lot
of other areas and it's good technique
so I think it's worth actually doing
this one seeing what it gets and when
we're done doing it I'm going to give
you a theorem that actually works for
when you're a log n factor bigger and
then you'll never have to do this sum
again but you should at least know that
the master theorem doesn't cover this
alright questions about it who
recognizes this recurrence equation
solved this we we did repeated
substitution and then we got a long
geometric series and that's when I first
told you how to sum a geometric series
so here's how we're going to do it today
we're going to change variables I'm
going to create a new variable relative
to the T's here and I'm going to get a
recurrence equation that's the simplest
one you've ever seen
just like the compound interest when we
did in the very first day so here's my
new change of variable s of n it's my
new variable equals T of n plus 1 how is
this going to help let's go ahead and
change this equation in terms of s event
that's the same as T of n right equals
C of n is s of n minus one so every
place you see a T of n here you put an s
of n minus one so T of n minus 1 is 2 s
of N minus 2 minus 1 plus 1 there we go
let me do it again since if i flubbed
with the chalk you're going to think
this is harder than it really is we
change the variable and if you're
thinking why the heck did he change the
variable that way and you're probably
wondering why I haven't explained why
and I will in a minute because this is a
magic trick I change this variable I get
t of n equal s of n minus 1 and every
place I see T of n I put an s of n minus
1 except here I messed it up a little
because here I have 2 T 2 times s of n
minus 1 minus 1 this is T n minus 1 is s
n minus 1 minus 1 SN minus 1 minus 1 is
in place of T n minus 1 and then I add
one from that one now let's fiddle with
this a little that might as well I'm
putting that over there so what you get
if you fiddle with this just a little
bit all the constants go away and you
get the simplest recurrence equation you
ever saw in your life this is just like
compound interest
this says that s of n is just twice of
the one we for it what's the solution to
this if I say s of 1 equals 1 by the way
what is SM what's T of 0 0 right what's
s of 0 you can figure out your base case
just by translating it through your
change of variable so if T of 0 0 then s
of 0 is 0 plus 1 so the s of 0 is 1 how
do I solve this recurrence the repeated
substitution here doesn't even develop a
sum it's the easy as possible one you
just keep multiplying by two and by two
and by two and by two so what's the
final answer s of N equals two to the N
so what's T of n 2 to the N minus 1 all
right so much easier doing a geometric
series or doing this this is easier but
how did I know that this would be so
pleasant
well the real way I knew is because I
knew the answer is 2 to the n minus 1
right and I know that 2 to the N comes
from a simple recurrence equation so I
just go backwards and I know the change
of variables is going to work and I run
it through and I make it look like magic
but Sam's right I can do this backwards
the first time because I knew what the
ending was I know the end of the story
so I make the story look good but if you
get good at this you can start guessing
in advance that the end is going to look
in a certain way and changing the
variables before you get into the crazy
sum and that takes ingenuity and it
takes practice and it takes experience
so how do I expect you guys to do it if
you're just beginners we will be
mathematically
by the under just take these pills the
kind of problem I expect you to do
that's the style is I'll say here's a
ridiculously looking hard recurrence
equation try this change of variable and
see what happens
you'll see things like that and then
you'll learn to appreciate this
technique without being in the position
of gee how do I get it because it does
take experience and it really isn't so
easy to guess the change of variable but
you should at least get the intuition
here this particular change a variable
what it's really doing is just kind of
doing the geometric series in advance
the geometric series is is double
everything with that extra one term on
the end so let's just add the one term
now so everything would just be double
that's kind of what's going on so let's
say this was plus four and you do the
same exact change of variable what do
you end up getting yet SN minus one
equals you tell me Joe you thought of it
you're stuck now
n s of N equals to s of n minus 1 minus
2 plus 4 plus 1 is that it minus 2 plus
4 plus 1/3 yeah
Jesus hope we're a little better
more than once right and if you notice
this gets you to something a little
better maybe we could change the
variable again and change the variable
again and then you might wonder well
maybe we could do all these changes of
variables all at once oh good good
you will be mature give me back the
pills we did change of variables we did
the master theorem we did repeated
substitution we're not going to do
linear algebra stuff today we're not
going to do linear homogeneous today I
still owe you that one sum for the one
that didn't work for master theorem
maybe I'll ask taro to do it in
recitation as a review the good news is
recitations from now for the next few
days are going to be nothing new they're
going to be let's do lots of these until
everybody feels they can completely do
it all right so they're going to be a
lot more recitations typically are we
don't have to catch up where we're right
here so bring in a problem you don't
know how to do it bring in a Sun that's
tough you can talk about it it's it'll
be it'll be nice I don't know how long
that will last but at least for the next
few days we're set this is this is about
this will be a 10 15 minute topic then
we're done for today
okay let's have chalk fly traces that's
what I got for my sixth graders good I
got that guy got that guy and they get
real excited when their flake wins geez
equation and proving it by induction is
a great example of the power of
induction it lets you use your intuition
you get used to recurrence equations
after a while you get a sense of oh I
think I know what that one is but I
don't have the slightest idea of how to
prove it so I'm going to take a darn
good guess and maybe I could just verify
my guess by induction and you don't have
to get the exact close formula all you
have to do is guess a big theta and
verify that by induction and you get
what you want with a lot less effort and
you can rely on your intuition so it's
cool the example I'm going to do is an
example that comes from algorithms a
real-life example I'm going to put a
recurrence equation up on the board and
I'll tell you the algorithm that it's
from we're going to look at it scratch
our head say God knows I don't want to
do this with any techniques because we
don't have any techniques that are going
to work we're going to guess an answer
because I'm going to tell you what I
think it should be and then we're going
to figure out how to prove it by
induction the big picture we're going to
try to prove it by induction I know if I
did it the right way the first time
you'd say I think I get that and then
when you try to do it yourself you'd say
I got what you did in class but now that
I try to do it myself I can't do it so
I'm going to do it the way I think you
would try to do it the first time which
is I'm going to do it wrong okay I'm
serious I'm going to do it and it's
going to mess up and right when it
messes up instead of having for you to
come to me you'll be here already
and then I'll fix it and we'll do it
right and I think that way you'll learn
it better okay now it's not really wrong
it'll just be a bad guess the first time
and will improve our guess so it'll be a
good experience a good experience
algorithm for finding the median of n
elements don't ask about the details of
the algorithm it's quite a complicated
algorithm we'll spend a day on it or so
in February whenever we get there but
it's an algorithm that takes n elements
and finds the middle guy now you can
always find the middle guy by sorting
the list right and pulling out the
middle guy that takes n log n so if
you've got any idea of how to pull out
the middle guy it better be better than
n log N or I can just send it to my
sorting man this algorithm therefore we
hope is going to be linear time
proportional to the looking at every
single element exactly once it's not
obvious how to do that it's not clear at
all how to do better than sorting but
you can and it turns out in the details
of this algorithm we solve a problem of
1/5 the size we solve another problem
70% the size and then we do 15 and steps
to glue them together well for one thing
we don't have just one set of
subproblems you know three subproblems
and over two we have two different ones
for another thing if we tried
substituting we get these long ugly
summations where two things would start
developing we just don't want to go in
that route it's just going to be ugly so
instead we're just going to guess that
this is linear time and try to prove it
by induction
so our proof is going to be by induction
on the size of the problem we're going
to assume that it's linear for smaller
problems for say things less than N and
we're going to try to show that it's
actually linear for size n using the
inductive assumption working our way up
and the only thing we know to help us
besides the inductive assumption that
it's linear is we know this we know that
T of n is no bigger is less than or
equal to TN over 5 plus T 7 n over 10
plus 15 n so I'm going to guess a wrong
guess just because I have no clue what
this complexity is and I'm going to
guess that this
T of n is less than or equal to 60 times
n and don't ask me why I pick 60 because
I picked it for no good reason I just
picked it I'm hoping that this is less
than something linear times n so I
picked the number 60 n I'm going to try
to prove this by induction I'm going to
try to prove the T of n is less than 60
n less than or equal to 60 M by
induction assuming this is true
everybody with me so far it turns out
that you can't do this we're going to
get stuck but the point that we get
stuck is a point that we can backtrack
and use a better number and get it to
work here's my base case T of n is less
than or equal to 5 as long as n is
smaller than or equal to 6
is the algorithm if it's got less than 5
elements can do it in if it's got 6 or
fewer elements it can do it in five
steps ok you give me 6 or sorry strictly
less five or fewer elements I can do it
in five steps
something like that that's the base case
this by induction here's what I know
n over 5 is a smaller problem everyone
agree then n I'm trying to prove TN is
less than or equal to 6 TN I'm going to
assume by induction that CN over 5 is
therefore less than or equal to 60 and
divided by 5 right or 12 minutes by the
same inductive assumptions T of 7 and
over 10 is smaller than or equal to 42 n
those two things I get for free by my
inductive assumption and now I'm going
to go ahead and use the one thing I know
for how to combine things and relate
them to T of n to see if I get a
conclusion hello Donna
oh no we're just lecturing backward
today we'll be finishing at 9:00 if I
can spend my feet fast enough for the
world to go around at the speed of light
this is smaller than 12 in plus 42 n
plus 15 N and that equals 69 and and
that's smaller than 60 crap right crap
it would have worked perfectly if that
69 turned out to be smaller than 60 but
69 is bigger this week than 60 so it
doesn't work so we have to come up with
a better constant so one thing might
happen this we might end up not being
able to find any constant maybe this
isn't linear time maybe we guessed wrong
and you'll find that out after a few
more tries but rather than keep trying
vaguely and randomly let's do this whole
trick again and instead of using 60 n
I'll just call it KN and I'll just make
the K whatever I need it to be at the
very end to work instead of guessing so
if I had started this whole thing and
I'd say okay so let's let T of n less
than or equal to K n I yeah maybe you
would get it maybe you wouldn't but I
think this is clear but now everything
gets more complicated my inductive
assumption TN over 5 is less than what
now
hey and over 5 the minute the specific
example goes away and things get general
you'll lose it unless you have some kind
of picture of the specific example in
your head that you can graph the
generality on so here you go 7 k and
over 10 and let's go through the same
steps so now let's figure out what this
says let's add it together cane over 5
is the same as 2 K n over 10 true so I
get 9 K n over 10 plus 15 and
hoping that this is us that are equal to
KN I'm hoping if this is so if I want
this to be true I've got complete
control over K right I picked you so I
can pick them to be anything I wanted to
be or her oh yeah it's I'm hungry too
let's move all the chaos on one side
say I'm tell me what to do but today
it's such a good idea
alright take all the ends out I agree
take the ends out let's put the case
together so I get how many k's on the
side hey over ten and here I get fifteen
so K has got to be bigger than or equal
to 150 so if I just picked 150 at the
beginning and ran through the whole
proof and everything would have worked
and I'd say seize therefore T of n is
less than or equal to 150 times N and
it's linear time and you wouldn't have
ever bothered asking me how I came up
with that number 150 until two days
later when you hit another problem set
and you'd say well how did you ever come
up with that 150 so now you know right
you don't really come up with it you