we're going to work on it's called the
alright here's the here's a problem
Josephus problem
Josephus is was a was a Jewish general
back in the period of time around the
beginning of the Common Era and and he
was a historian and he wrote all about
the wars and the very very interesting
period of time around the birth of
Christianity and and when Judaism
changed its character
it's a really fascinating part of
history but we're not going to talk
about the history of it today we're
going to talk about the math and in one
of his books he has a little description
of this particular game or puzzle where
basically there are people in a circle
and you want to determine which person
gets saved from from death and you do
every other person pulling them out of
the circle and sending them up to be
executed and you continue around the
circle pulling out every other person
until there's one person left and that
person is the one who who is saved so
Josephus as he tells the story made sure
that he was in the right place and hence
we have all these nice history books
it's a good story
a lot of Josephus stories are good
stories and history back then is not as
clear as history's today it wasn't such
a discipline and it's all an interesting
question about how history well
historiography as its changed back from
ancient times till now but we're gonna
do this puzzle and what we're gonna do
now that Jose come now I got 31 people
in this room and his name is Chow here
just sitting spot number 15 you'd like
to know if there's a certain number of
people in the circle we're to sit right
especially if you find yourself you know
sent back in a time machine we're all
your clever methods of persuasion are
not going to get you out of some
barbaric Roman deciding that
have to play the circle game you want to
sit in the right spot so how do you
decide we're gonna solve this problem
you give me a number I'll tell you where
to sit all right and we can do it
quickly here it doesn't take too long to
actually do this puzzle so let's assume
that we're go left to right I'll tell
you that if there are if there are 31
people you want to sit and spot 15
okay I'll for example and I think we
have 31 people so the 15th spot 1 2 3 4
5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14
so Tom gets saved let's do we have
actually 31 let's just double-check 1 2
3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
include all right sorry so here we go
here's what you do if you're if you're
dead just just just put your head down
on the desk if you're yeah
all right so we'll do every other person
you're not dead yet you're number one
it's the even numbers right dead dead
dead this is the fun part of the job is
plenty of you want now let's go let's
make sure we got the right order here
we'll just go the back third row so so
Andrew you're next dead dead I need to
know who's dead because I won't know
next time EJ okay now we're gonna go
around this way so Blake Rob Joe okay
now we're coming back around so you got
skipped so Mike I'm skip I did include
Alex in the in the
still shop safe so Sean's dead who's
Anthony you're dead who's that
peter is still alive now Peters dead
Gary's dead puros dead Chris is dead
this is out of control
alright alright yeah there's 36 people
there are 30 there's 31 people now no
number 15 would stay alive I'm pretty
sure all right let's see alright so
let's I can see this is getting a little
chaotic let's go on the board here let's
let's do this puzzle with seven people I
had so much fun I don't have to think
give me a few minutes alright let's see
this puzzle was seven that's true
killed who gets killed next one who gets
killed next five who gets killed neck
three so seven there's a live let's do
another example make sure everybody gets
it I can't do 31 it's long I'll do I'll
do 11 okay seven will survive I think
three should survive let's see 2 4 6 8
you're right 3 and you love 7 survives
should be 7 I'm now 31 yeah I did 31
wrong what did I say now 37 I did wrong
you're right you're right yeah okay well
what is this oh it's me
Josephus has another story all about how
a particular general was going to be
elected but of course they lost the
ballot so they had to do a recount and
they just killed the person who asked
for a recount
I made that completely not true but it'd
be a better story yeah let's let's see
how we can handle this this recurrence
equation we could fiddle with this all
day long looking for angles but I'm
going to show you one particular angle
that that really gives us a lot of
leverage and then from there we're gonna
write down some some data we're gonna
make a good guess because we'll be able
to see what the pattern looks like and
then we'll prove that guess by induction
that's our plan all right so first let's
let's get a little leverage on this
problem
I'm gonna go back to the seven case
this problem right this is one variation
of the Josephus problem right it depends
a number of skips you do it depends on
where you start but let's assume we're
doing just the problem we go every other
one and in that case you don't get any
even numbers ever staying alive the
question is what happens after that so
we did this example before and when you
do this example you all know I can knock
them off here two four six we'll do it
again one five three and then seven-slot
all right so let's just write that down
we'll call J of 7 equals sunny that
means if there are seven people the
seventh one is saved okay now what I
want to examine here is the following
interesting angle let's consider a
number of people that's double this and
the reason we're going to do that
where's the motivation for that is
because after we finished one cycle as
Brooke just just imply
half the people are gone and the problem
looks very much like it looks at the
beginning except the people re numbered
okay let's see what I mean by this so
let's try 1414 I have to try that again
it looks so bad that looks a little
better
okay let's cross these out but stop
halfway to goes for goes six goes it
goes 10 goes 12 goes 14 goes and now we
are right here ready to skip over one
this is right where we were at the
beginning it's the same problem again
right recursion induction it's the same
problem again except now how many people
are in my seven people in my list but
they're not numbered 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 now
they're numbered 1 3 5 7 9 11 13 but you
know which one of these is going to end
up being saved it's the 13th guy right
the guy number 13 because he's the same
as the one that we called 7 here so if I
knew that the answer for the 7 person
was 7 that would imply that the answer
for the 14th person is going to be 13
what I need now is a way to write this
down formally in general so before I do
let's say that for the seventh person
the answer would have been 5 is saved
what would that of correspond to here
would have correspond it to 9 that's
different we'll get to that this works
when we start with an even number when
we start with an odd number there's a
little bit of a twist and that's a good
thing to think about well think about it
in a second what I want to do now is
write down what we've just done in
general to take what we've noticed
logically and turn it into an equation
which is just six symbols long that
looks like
a recurrence equation so here's what it
looks like if you take something that's
an even number and you want to know
which person is saved
that is J of 2n okay we want to know
what this equals you go through the
stage and you cut off all the even
numbers and now you look at what's left
and it's half the numbers left and you
ask yourself what is that what is the
person that's saved in half the numbers
and you go over here and it tells you
it's the number seven and now you want
to take that answer and transfer it back
to the numbers here how do you transfer
it back if it's seven it turns to 13 if
it's five it turns to nine right what's
the connection twice this minus one and
that's not an accident because that's
what these numbers are right the numbers
here are doubled over there and then
it's just the one before it
so let's write this down figure out the
answer to your half-size problem
multiply it by two and subtract one that
is the general summary of what we just
noticed by stopping after the first
round and relating the josephus problem
for 2n to the josephus problem for n we
can try this out and a couple more
examples but before we do I want to do
the example where it is an odd case the
thing that Doug just asked ok so before
I do that other questions this is the
most complicated part of the whole
lecture today the part I just did the
part that makes this equation if you get
it then it's and it's coasting down here
then it's Heartbreak Hill and you just
got three miles down to to the finish
line
could be odd right that's why we need an
equation for the odd cases and we're
going to do that right now let's do the
same thing here and come up with a
similar relationship here we have an odd
number okay so we cross out two four six
eight ten Wow 14 right and now one gets
crossed out but then we want to sweep
this doesn't work out so easily right
we'd like to start right before one but
now we have two so now I'm here to start
the next one what happens now
so this would be like one in the new
problem and this would be like two and
this would be like three so if the
answer for this new problem is one then
we want the answer to our problem to be
three if the answer to this new
half-size problem is two then the answer
here should be five so you want to take
this number I'll write them down here
one two three four five six what's the
relationship between these numbers 1 2 3
4 5 and the numbers that we're going to
have to write down for our answer there
twice plus 1 and this part here how many
elements do we have here relative to 2n
plus 1 we have n elements we started
with 15 2 times 7 plus 1 and what's left
should be 7 elements left 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
because we did half of them off and the
extra one at top so we again have J n
that's nice but this time we multiply by
2 2 times 1 and we add 1 to x 2 add 1
add one here are the two relationships
we get these relationships are gotten by
inspecting this idea and knowing that
this angle would would lever just this
nice cool relationship I should mention
to you that you could stare at this
problem a long time before you realize
this idea and before you thought of it
so what would make you think of it again
you always want to think of a problem in
terms of a smaller problem so you're
looking and you're hoping that you can
do a little bit of work on here and make
it look like a smaller problem if you
have that as a goal it is not too much
of a leap to go once around and then
start to scratch your head and say okay
I pretty much have what I started with
here how do I milk that into something
and if you have that as a goal then this
comes next
alright so now that I've tried to
motivate it here it is here's our
recurrence equations and now we can look
at some base cases and we could actually
build up from the bottom up some tables
and see if we can come up with some kind
of formula and that's what we'll do
right now all right so let's make a
table J of N hears N one two three four
five six seven eight nine ten 11 12
who gets saved one one if we have two
people who get saved one now I think we
can use this recurrence equation why
couldn't I use it just by well maybe I
could have just used it could I have do
any one base case or two base cases
that's the question this this works for
even cases and it works on the one
that's half its size right
this works on our case is working on one
that's a little less than half its size
so two is going to depend on who's going
to depend on one does it does it does it
work so I didn't really need to do this
as a base case I could have done it as
from our recurrence case what about
three three is in this spot and it
depends on one so two times one plus one
is all right let's fill out some more
what's four gonna be four is even so
it's twice the two case minus one
yeah we only need one base case right
to get that jf four is going to be jf 2
which is 1 2 times 1 minus 1 is 1 all
right let's fill this in who's got some
more values you can just use either one
of these equations depending on whether
it's even or odd that takes care of all
the possible numbers so if it's 5 you
want to use this one for 6 you use that
one
make sure we get it right three and this
comes out to be five
we know that seven turns out to be seven
takes in we have a formula for J of n
that relates to J event we have we have
J of N and we have J of and in terms of
itself so we have to just use this
column we'd like to be able to plug in
and get and get a straight answer that's
our goal and we're going to get that
soon so eight is going to depend on four
right we could try to solve this but
look we've got these two cases so we'd
have to do a substitution and then back
substitute the other way and maybe we'd
get something nice we would I mean we
could do it but we're not going to do it
that way today we're going to try to
avoid that because the the closed form
for this is really horribly ugly and if
we just look at it in a more logical way
and prove it by induction we're going to
get a we're going to get a formula
that's really much nicer okay so so then
nine is going to be nine is that what
you say
one so nine is gonna be three ten is
gonna be five eleven is going to be and
twelve is going to be look at that so
isn't this one one three one three five
look one three five seven nine eleven
thirteen look at these repeated
sequences of odd numbers they repeat at
different sizes right here we have one
here we have two here we have four here
we have seven I should go on now to see
when it goes back to one let's just do
that to make sure since you're all
convinced that be a good idea fifteen
and sixteen I'll do 15 is going to be 15
and 16 is going to be one so that's
where it really ends one two four eight
time so let's try to write down some
description that will let us figure out
J of n based on what we know and then
we'll try to prove that description by
induction without ever dealing with a
substitution idea and killing ourselves
okay and how do you know when to do
these things you don't
that's what ingenuity is all about you
try different things I wanted to show
you this is just another example of a
recurrence equation that yields to a
different attack all right let's try to
write down what this means
hit 2 to the K that's true so then why
don't I let me try to write that out in
a way that we can summarize this says
that if you want to know who's the
survivor in any number that you can
write in two pieces here is the biggest
power of two and here's what is left
over after that biggest power of two
okay because you said we restart after
every power of two so figure out the
biggest power of two figure out what's
left over and when you get that amount
that's left over you take that amount
say it's the second one it's the third
one the fourth one you want to get odd
numbers from the one two three four so
you want to take that number if there's
of two so there's nothing left over then
your answer should be one let's say
there's one left over after the power of
two then your answer should be three if
there's two left over after the power of
two your answer should be five figure
out what's left over after your power of
2 and then multiply it by two and add
one that's our conjecture it's more than
a conjecture it almost screams that it's
got to be true it's way too coincidental
for these odd numbers to show up but let
me review this again we notice that it
starts repeating after powers of two so
let's go down to the powers of two
here's the first power of two that
occurs if there's nothing left over if
there's zero left over there then our
answer is right there here's the next
power of two that occurs that would be
zero here's the next power of two that
occurs that would be zero left over
those are all the value
for the peas it's what I did I should
have won here here's 2 4 8 yam economy 8
right well I got solid lines there I got
but here's fine you can put them
anywhere you like but the idea is that
when you're done with a power of 2 you
want to figure out how much is left over
if there's one left over after that
that means the answer is 3 if there's 2
left over after that it means the answer
is 5 so go to the power of 2 that you is
the know is the biggest power in your
number and start counting after that as
many slots as there are after that twice
that many plus 1 is your answer ok so if
you're in the third slot after a power
of 2 1 2 3 your answer 7 2 times 3 plus
1 this is a conjecture we have to still
prove it and we're going to prove it by
induction because proving in any other
way just seems like it's just going to
be impossible how are we going to get
this from scratch it just might not be
so easy but by induction is going to be
really easy we're going to prove this is
true then we're going to notice
something really cool about this problem
that we're going to let it go and do
some other induction problems
all right questions about it all right
so let's sum now that we've got this is
met sure everybody knows how to use it I
want to make sure let's say there are
the leftover is 1 that means your one
past the biggest power of 2 that means
your one pass one of these dotted lines
that means your answer is 3 take 129
divide it into a power of 2 that's
biggest 128 128 plus 1 the P is 1/2
times 1 plus 1 gives you 3 so you want
to sit in the third spot and if I asked
you two times 120 the biggest power of
264 56 is the difference is the pee
twice 56 is 112 add 113 so if there's
120 people and you want to sit more to
the end well it's a circle you got
partial credit if you're sitting right
next yeah yeah you'll want to sit next
to the guy is sitting in 113 I'll be
right next to my hundred 12 oh I got
partial credit well I'm getting chilled
in the first round here's what we want
to prove that this is true we ever want
to prove that this is true for any value
of n this is what we want to prove and
we don't have any slight idea why it's
true we just picked it out of this
pattern well that's cool because we can
do experimenting and find patterns but
we do know that this is true and we do
know that this is true so if we try to
prove this by induction we can assume
that this formula is true for smaller
cases and we have to show that it's true
for the next case so we're going to try
to do now in doing this here's what
we're going to do we're going to assume
now we want to show that this is true
and we'll assume it's true assume that
it's true it's yes
have to take the floor of it and get the
remainder of it there's a reason I write
it this way it would really be much
uglier if I wrote it the other way this
is a much easier way to write it you're
right Anthony you could try to do it
with logs and floors but you have to get
the remainder of that lot it's not the
log number itself it's what's left over
after you take the log it's the mod yeah
yeah it'd be ugly that's as soon as it's
true for smaller cases for smaller cases
than n a lot of your use in induction of
going from n to n plus 1 but it's
completely the same to go from anything
less than n to n you just want to go
from the smaller cases to the bigger
cases so I'm going to assume this is
true for all the smaller cases than n
and I'm going to show that it's true for
n that sometimes called strong induction
I'm assuming it's true for all the
smaller cases not just the one
immediately below me not just the n
minus 1 k s-- but for all of them and in
order to do this we have to show that
this formula is true and since this
helpful
relationship has two cases even and odd
I'm probably going to have to have my
induction have two cases even or not so
let's try the following and is even and
we'll do here n is odd
okay we want to show that this is things
going to be true for any end in the
world I'm going to assume it's true for
smaller values of n I'm going to assume
these two things are true I want to get
this formula being true
all right who's with me so far yes raise
your hand if you're really with me so
far I want to see how many people are
are thinking yeah here now it's rigorous
okay
I think it's rigorous right yeah so it
has to be written like this where P is
the smallest P is smaller than the
biggest power but you're right Anthony I
have to be careful but what I mean by
this right it just you all know what I
mean but I should write it well maybe
you don't all know what I mean
I mean take the biggest power of two and
see what's like now you know what nobody
alright let's try to do this here's what
we get we're assuming and is even now so
that this is even we want to show that
this equals to P plus one we can't use
this formula we can only use it if we
have smaller cases well let's take this
and turn it into something that's a
smaller case and then use this formula
how do you take this and turn it into a
smaller case it's built-in for us here
it is this tells us how to turn it into
a smaller case all right so what do we
get we get 2 times J of half of this
plus 1 sorry minus 1
how do you write half of this two to the
M minus one plus plus P over 2 no no P's
not P's even right so we can P over two
might be odd but P is even right okay
what's next
this looks like a horrible mess right
look right this is a smaller case
everyone agree that the two to the N
minus one plus P over 2 is smaller than
this one because it's half the size so
now I get to use my induction assumption
to go to my formula okay I get to use it
that's the whole idea of induction take
what you start with turn it into
something that's a smaller case using a
relationship that you can get either
through a recurrence equation or through
some other argument use your induction
on the smaller case and then move on so
let's do the induction on the smaller
case what is the formula tell us here's
the highest power of 2 here's the
leftover it tells us that we're going to
get 2 times this leftover plus 1
minus 1 2 P plus 2 minus 1 that better
be 2 P plus 1 good that's what we want
we want this to be 2 P plus 1 and it is
so I've proved that when this number is
even if I start here I end up here
there's two steps in the proof one is
using my recursed currents relationship
to get it into a smaller case the next
step is using my induction assumption
that's the whole power of induction
that's where the whole proof becomes
easy and then I just simplify it and
they get my conclusion yeah Jo the
algebra from here to here look at this
this says J to the 2m minus 1 plus P
over 2 2 to the M minus 1 is the biggest
power P over 2 is there leftover and the
formula says multiply the left over by 2
and add 1 the leftovers P over 2 2 times
P over 2 is P add 1 is P plus 1 and
that's why I have P plus 1 in place of
that does that make sense well I think
well we proved it enough I think I
didn't write a formal proof on the board
but I think I convinced everybody that
it was true no we're assuming these are
true we're assuming these are true we're
proving this this is what we're proving
absolutely right you could prove the
pair of these by induction you could and
it would require some argument similar
to the one we did but I think you could
also prove it just straight these two
don't scream out for induction like this
one does
explained when I explained the idea that
makes these two formulas come up there
was nothing in particular about the idea
that that doesn't work in general I give
me it give me a circle
I go around once and that's the
recurrence equation it's right there so
there's really no there's no need to go
to smaller cases in other words there's
nothing hard that happens as you go from
the enth over to cases to the end cases
the only thing that's hard as you go
around the circle once here it's a
little trickier I don't know I mean it's
a subjective thing weather proof screams
to do it by induction or not all right
let's do this one for two M plus P being
odd which one of these things apply this
one applies so we get that this equals 2
to 2 J something plus 1 now we need to
get the right value here right this is 2
times something plus 1 and we need that
something here if we write this as 2
times something plus 1 what do we get
here in the parentheses all right since
I know n is odd I'm not gonna let PE be
an odd number 2 cuz I know this numbers
even so P is some odd number 2 times k
plus 1 and now I can write it a little
more easily so this equals 2 to the M
plus 2 k plus 1 okay this equals 2 times
2 to the n minus 1 plus K plus 1 2 times
something plus 1 so here's the here's
the something ok
is is p minus 1 over 2 all right let's
go through the next step of the
induction proof we're going to assume
this works by induction here's the left
over we get twice this left over plus
one twice this K two times twice the K
plus 1 the K is P minus 1 over 2 so when
you multiply it by 2 you get P minus 1 P
minus 1 plus 1 is P so again you end up
with 2 P plus 1 it's the same proof as
before there's some details in the
algebra you need to work through it's
the easiest way I think to see it is to
write P as 2 k plus 1 remember Sam came
up with a really cool way of thinking of
our Chinese ring problem with binary
numbers if you do the same thing here
and write out the J events for binary
numbers you'd also notice a pattern
different from the odd numbers a pattern
that just has to do with binary numbers
and that you'll see makes a lot of sense
but since we're doing computer science
and binary numbers come up all the time
I thought this would be a neat thing to
show you and then we're going to move on
and do some more proofs by induction and
and finish off the topic Rob you have a
question I am I'm going to write the J
of ends in binary
theory if you have a theory we'll do it
one okay what do I get here
works for all practical cases maybe we
need to see some some bigger cases to
see really what's going on but it's Sam
has already found the pattern yes yes
you're right and you're right and you're
right but let's let's write up a couple
of yes here let's do this here's an
here's Javon let's go from here seven
here's 14 7 is 1 1 1 14 is 1 1 whoops I
promised I would do this 1 1 1 1 1 how
do you write 14 1 100 right right 1 1 1
oh good because otherwise pattern
wouldn't work all right so Sam noticed
the following pattern he says if you
take this number here your n your binary
number and you just take the leftmost
bit and pull it around to the right end
you get your answer let's see if it's
true if you take this and you cyclically
shift it cyclical shifting is one of the
typical built in machine language
commands in any processor shift your
bits left right it's easy to build a
circuit that the cyclical shifting you
can write a boolean algebra formula to
take 3 bits and shift them cyclically 3
come in 3 come out ok it could have been
on a test
it wasn't what happens here
shift this over you got one you shift
this over you get the same you shift
this over you got one you shift this
over you get o one one you shift this
over you get 101 you shift this over you
get one one one you shift this over you
get one again look over here one one one
zero you shift the one over you got one
101 if you just show this pattern of
bits and said these relate to these you
might be able to notice that they relate
by a left cyclical shift without knowing
anything about the recurrence relations
or seeing anything else this cyclical
left shift corresponds to this rule
let's understand why what happens when
you do a cyclical left shift to a number
let's say the number starts with a 1
which it always does we don't have any
leading zeros when you do with cyclical
left shift what are you doing to the
number okay shifting over one to the
left means doubling the number and then
adding one take off the biggest power of
two strip off the one you're left with P
take your P double it shift it over one
spot
remember base ten you multiply by 10
when you shift over one spot base two
when you shift over one spot and put a
zero on the end you double it if you
take that zero and turn it into a 1
you've doubled it and added 1 this part
takes off the leftmost bit this part
doubles it by shifting it to the left
this part puts the 1 in its place
and you'll notice we always have a 1 on
the left end so shifting it cyclically
is always going to accomplish adding
that one and that's why left cyclical
shifting is the exact same thing as
pulling off the one pushing it over one
spot and putting a 1 on the right end
here because it would have some fixed
number of bits there'd be zeros lined up
here we'd have to write some kind of
code to strip away those zeros and and
move this to the left and the byte it
would be a little bit trickier to
actually implement it under computer
and the right stream code that you said
that's in most most processors wouldn't
no but we could do this and then
mask it through using those logical and
kind of things and and pull out the bits
we want and put them in new bytes you
could you could do that it could be done
alright questions about this in
recitation today taro will do some more
inductive proofs review any questions
you have in the problem set on
recurrence equations or recursion and
then we start new topic tomorrow
counting one example that I want to do
today well all the examples I'm going to
do relate to computer science in one way
or another one example is a really brief
example a two minute example that has to
do with the correctness of programs
showing that they actually do what
they're supposed to another example has
to do with binary trees and how to count
the nodes at the bottom the ones that
are called leaves another example has to
do with some number theory that will
eventually lead into cryptography and
it's similar to a problem you've already
seen before in a problem set I'm just
going to present it in a way that shows
you how to do it in general and we're
gonna nail that problem down the last
week of class in much more detail so all
these things will be things you'll see
again and you've seen before as well so
first thing proving proving programs are
correct this is a big area of research
and it'd be nice to prove that your
loops do what you think they're going to
do so there's a lot of work that goes on
here how do you describe what it is that
your programs supposed to be doing once
you describe it how do you formally
prove that it does what it's supposed to
do when you have loops you do what's
called loop invariance you say what's
supposed to be true about the loop with
respect to the index of the loop and
then you prove by induction that that
thing stays true it's really dry and I
won't do an example the book has some
examples but that's how that's done the
other way that it's done is for
recursive programs recursive programs
it's just completely transparent how to
prove that they work they work because
they're recursive and you do a
mathematical induction proof on the
recursion so here's an example
want to sum up the nodes to sum up the
nodes in a binary tree here's a picture
of a binary tree you've got a root you
got a left subtree and you have a right
subtree these are each trees themselves
if you remember from the cut from a
month ago and skiing you can represent
this in a list right with a car and a
cutter and there's the car of your list
and here's the cutter of your list and
then there's a value for the route you
guys did it right give me a big nod yeah
thumbs up okay not finger is that not
that finger thumbs yeah
not necessarily just the binary tree
with in any case it's got a binary tree
on the right and a binary tree on the
left so here's a program to sum up the
nodes in a binary tree call the program
again on the left sub-tree call the
program again on the right subtree add
the two answers together and then add
one everyone agree so here's how I'll
write it to sum up the nodes in a binary
tree sum up let's call the treaty sum up
TDOT left sum up TDOT right and add one
and return this this is not scheme it's
just some kind of pseudo code but this
these two things mean recursive calls
these two things mean do whatever you
have to to get the left subtree this
would be a car this would be a cooter
add them together add one there's your
answer how do we know this works we'll
prove it by induction
prove it by induction let's assume that
some tea left does what it's supposed to
do so this returns to us by induction
because it's a smaller tree the number
of nodes in the left subtree okay that I
get for free by my induction assumption
similarly for free since this is a
smaller tree this is going to return to
me the number of nodes on the right side
by induction how do I get the number of
nodes in a tree I take the left nodes
the right nodes and I add one for my
root node this Plus this Plus that end
of proof every recursive algorithm has
an induction proof on its correctness
all you have to do is show that the
gluing that you do to get your final
answer make sense and you'll know you'll
get the right answer for the recursive
solutions by the mathematical induction
assumption the same way when you write
this you know what's going to work you
have this leap of faith when you write
recursive algorithms that the recursive
calls are going to come back with the
right answers that's why and I was wrong
about this that I thought if you do
scheme first and you spend a whole month
doing nothing but recursion that you
would have completely internalized the
idea of mathematical induction before
you even saw it and I was wrong
it's not true I'm not sure why it's not
true but it's not
but mathematical deduction is sitting
here if you can write a recursive
algorithm then you've already thought of
the mathematical induction ideas you're
assuming these smaller cases work and
that's how your algorithm works yeah
question
I didn't prove the base case works
you're right Sharon I left it out and my
proof wouldn't be right unless I did but
in the real world my program would
actually have a base case and here I
didn't put one in there should be an if
here and that says you know if there's
no car no code or if there's no left and
right subtree then just return one and
it and actually I have to be more
careful I have to say if there's no left
subtree return one plus the right
subtree okay if there's no right subtree
then return what I have to do it in
steps yes
yeah you mean Leafs are nodes they're
just special kinds of notes so you want
to count them
alright questions about this the answer
is you should always there's no reason
not to and I don't know why they don't
just teach induction from the beginning
and in fact if you're really
concentrated and you look at my notes
back at the beginning I don't make any
effort to show that you go from n to n
plus one I say you go from the smaller
cases to the next bigger case and that's
what strong induction is so so I don't
think you should separate the two ideas
I think it is better just to be
presented is one idea but let me some of
you are probably thinking what two ideas
what is he talking about
there there are two ways of presenting
induction one way is assume it's true
for n show that it's true for n plus 1
okay the other way is sooo much true for
everything and and all the smaller cases
and show that it's true for n plus 1 the
strong one is where you assume that is
true for all the cases and in general
you know you don't have to pay any extra
to get all the smaller cases you get
them for free as long as you have a base
case at the bottom you get all the
smaller cases for free you might as well
assume they're true but sometimes you
have to use the strong induction idea in
this case for the binary tree we have
two smaller cases neither one of which
is size 1 less than what we started
they're both half the size of what we
started possibly so you have to use
strong induction there so in general I
think it's better to just think of
induction as an idea where you want to
show that it's true I always just pick
an N I want to show that it's true for n
I'm going to assume that it's true for
all the smaller cases n minus 1 n minus
2 and all the other ones I don't like to
reach toward n plus 1 I like to reach
toward N and assume that is true for all
the smaller cases ok that's my own
personal way to look at it yeah Brian
when I take an out it is an arbitrary n
but I get for free by induction that all
the cases smaller than this arbitrary
one that I pulled out already work down
to some base right it could be six right
down to some base right is it okay yeah
the web as Chris's musings and it will
have four million hits and people all
over the world in Korean Japan watching
crisco's today I thought about something
which i think is true and which I no
longer it's a great question this is a
question that Doug was asking me earlier
let me address this question because
it's fundamental and and a lot of people
say well how do you know like if there's
a flaw and a proof where does it go
wrong and you know there are subtle ways
and and can you give us like a list of
these ways so the the bad answer is or
the unfortunate answer is there is no
list and there is no check this this or
this but but I know what you're talking
about here and I want to address it
because it's important
Chris is referring implicitly to to a
problem
I had on one of the earlier exams that
looks like this I forget what it looks
like now something like this that's true
do I have it backwards is that true is
that right or not right okay okay this
is this is an algebraic tautology it's
true now there's also a base case when n
is zero
a to the zero equals one so here's a
phony inductive proof I'm going to try
to prove that a to the N equals one I'm
going to assume by induction a lot of
the smaller cases work
so here's n minus 1 here's n minus 2 1
times 1 divided by 1 equals 1 here's the
base case e to the 0 equals 1 and
therefore a to the N equals 1 so there's
a flaw here there's nothing wrong with
this algebraic equation there's nothing
wrong with this base case so where's the
flaw in the whole big picture the flaw
in the picture is that this here
when you write an inductive proof out
you have to make sure that your argument
is really a general argument that it
works for every single case bigger than
your base case all right sometimes if
somebody expresses an argument to you in
general and it works for an infinite
number of cases you tend to be convinced
and then you miss the one case that it
doesn't work for this argument doesn't
work in general for any value bigger
than zero it works for every single
example except the case when n is 1 when
n is 1 this says that a to the 1 equals
a to the 0 times a to the 0 that's fine
divided by a to the minus 1 there is no
a to the minus 1 and if there was we'd
have to have another base case for it
because it doesn't exist
proof a to the 0 is 1 a to the N equal 8
times a to the N minus 1
each of these are smaller right n minus
1 is smaller than n 1 is smaller than n
so they have to both be equal to 1
how come this proof doesn't work where's
the right each of them if you're just
right my magic world of right but I'm
trying to fool you here so okay I'm
trying to fool you what's wrong with
this proof I could have
no not this time it's not the problem
here's to their a to the N equals a to
the 1 times a to the n mine back and
this proof the problem was that for one
of the cases that I claim this general
argument works for it really doesn't
work I hid that in a general argument
but it doesn't work when n is 1 because
this turns out not to even make sense
you can say I could fix it if I add
another base case but that's not going
to happen unless there was another base
case and there isn't another base case
but you don't necessarily need a second
base case just because these two things
use that's really your question do you
need two base cases when this uses two
sub-problems smaller than one the answer
is yes
only when the general argument will
force you past this base case or
underneath it and the other and what we
did before the two trees yes that would
but doing it in half wouldn't
necessarily get you past the base case
right if you start with eight and this
depends on either 4 or 3 that's not
necessarily going to get your pasture
base case and in fact the josephus
problem is J of 2n in terms of J n right
you only need one base case for that
problem because they all get held up by
the bottom by Atlus N equals 1 and it
never gets passed there all right so you
don't always need more lots of base
cases just because you have your problem
based on two different subsets it's only
when those things eventually will pass
up that one base case that you're hoping
is going to be the foundation when
they're divided they you can't skip when
you when you have dividing conquer you
can skip when you have negatives when
you have subtractions yes the question
is if you're on a recurrence relation
that says you know T of n is multiplied
T of n minus 1 times T of n minus 1
divide it by TN minus 2 you better have
two base cases there are sooner or later
you're going to go past them
okay so it said the wrong what's wrong
with this if you don't have the second
base it would be fine to say you don't
have the second base case or would be
fine to say that the argument doesn't
work for N equals one somewhere along
the way you have to say that the
argument does not generally hold
assuming this is your only base case but
I agree you could write it that would
that be equivalent just as good a big
difference between these two right
there's a big difference that's right
what's missing here nothing missing this
is true so you agree that a to the N
equals one now right I'm trying to prove
that a to the N equals one again right
but that proof doesn't show that it
doesn't of course it doesn't right
because we know it's not true but why
doesn't it so what's wrong with this
proof maybe that's what you're trying to
say is I have this base case I have this
thing that's true each of these are two
smaller cases therefore they should be
one stop me there if that means n minus
one is always smaller than N and one is
always smaller than n so they're two
smaller cases and one is always smaller
than n throw a tomato one's not always
smaller than n right and could be one
and then one is not smaller than one
that's where this argument gets killed
if I gave you this proof the only real
way to say this one doesn't work is to
say you are giving me an argument here
that is not true for every n bigger than
zero it's only true for ends bigger than
one so even you give me an argument for
every end that's bigger than zero
including one or I keep the same
argument you have that works for any end
that's bigger than two and you give me a
base case for N equals one one or the
other but you can't have have both
angles
domaine this is true right this is true
for age this is true for n bigger than
two it's very cool to two it really is
true for n bigger than equal to well
that's one way to look right right the
induct the inductive idea here works for
n bigger than or equal to two the
inductive idea fails because I can't
claim that this one is going to be
smaller than this n for every single n
unless n is bigger than 2 so this in is
bigger than 2 that's true that's true
induction you just say well this doesn't
even have a chance period maybe so what
this there's a lot of pedagogical
reasons why people teach induction by
doing the N to n plus 1 way here's the
reason most people do it it's because
it's kind of easy to teach people how to
prove some formulas with induction here
it's true for n plug it in for N equals
n plus 1 and then try to make the
algebra work and I have seen people do
fifteen of these and have no idea what
proofs by induction are so I hate doing
it that way I always start with
different examples and and and maybe it
works that way maybe you need to do 20
of these sums and then you do get what
induction is but I've seen too many
people try 20 of them and still not get
the idea so I like to kind of do a lot
of different examples outside of sums
and even then it doesn't always work but
I don't know what works I'm still
plugging another tree problem a tree of
height
tree yes an organic tree of height n has
less than or equal to 2 to the N leave
what height n is here's a tree of height
0 okay
the height is basically or the depth
depending on how you want to look at it
is the longest path from the root okay
a 2 this is a 1 the maximum of the
length of all the paths that's another
way to look at it
everybody get what the height is it's
what I mean by the height of a tree a
tree of height and has no more than 2 to
the n leaves and you can kind of check
this I mean the most leaves you can get
is if you spread it out into a complete
tree so here's high two and high two has
exactly four leaves so you get equality
when it's a complete tree but you get
less than for any other subsets of that
show you have a question right so we're
going to prove this by induction and
we're going to do it in two different
ways one way which goes from say n to n
plus one and one way that does it by
strong induction and they're really very
different proofs and they're both very
short and and and painless
trying to get to rather than rather than
the assumption you're trying to work
from
maybe if in this time you said you're
gonna do it both ways maybe if we do it
to the same spot we well we well alright
so I want to show that this is true and
I'm going to assume that it's true first
of all for a tree that has height one
less okay I'm going to assume that it's
true first of all for trees of height
and minus one assume true for trees
height and minus one okay that's one way
we're gonna do it let's do it this way
all right I got a tree it's got n for
its height I want to convince you it's
got less than or equal to 2 to the N
leaves I'm gonna try to take this tree
and fiddle with it so it'll be a tree of
height one less then I'll use my
inductive assumption and I'll try to
argue about what happened as I went from
my tree with high tend to my tree of
height n minus one to show that I still
get 2 to the N leaves so I'm going to
take the tree I start with that has
height and I'm going to knock it down to
a tree that has height n minus 1 use the
inductive assumption and then work my
way back up to show what happened in
that process to show that I get no more
than twice as many lis right that's
that's the plan how do I take a tree of
height and and cut it down to a tree of
height n minus 1
two trees of hide n minus one so I cut
it here
I might get two trees of n minus one I
might not yes if I take off all the
leaves what happens then every single
path from the root to the bottom just
went down by one including the maximum
path so I can take off all the leaves
take off all the leaves from the trees
start with and the tree that used to be
height n is now height n minus 1 right
so I'm going to prove this is true take
off all the leaves the resulting tree
every single path from the root to the
bottom has now gone down by one
including the maximum path that gave me
high ten
the resulting tree has height n minus
one by induction how many leaves does
this thing have by induction this tree
the new tree has less than equal to to
the n minus one leaves
back if I went back now and put back the
maximum number of possible leaves to on
every single one that remains in this
tree how many leaves what I have in the
new tree twice this many right two for
every one of these so I'd have to to the
end but that tree has got to be at least
as big as the one I started with because
it's got all the possibilities put in I
took them all off there might have been
two on each branch that might have been
one on each branch so I took them all
off the first time but when I put two
back on each one I get a tree that's
bigger than the one I started with so
add back two leaves to each leaf and you
get a tree which is bigger or equal to
our original bigger or equal than our
original bla bla bla we're actually
writing the south formally which I hate
doing because you can't read it anyway I
just like saying it in English add back
two leaves to each leaf that's here you
get a new tree that's at least as big as
the one you started with because you're
adding the maximum number of leaves to
each remaining leaf this new tree has at
most this new tree which is bigger than
what we started with has at most two
times two to the N minus one leaves
because you add two for every leaf
that's there and that equals two to the
N so this bigger tree we have has
smaller than two to the n leaves
certainly a smaller tree is going to
have less than two to the end leaves and
that proves the induction yeah yes
twenty-one no this is hike this is high
too
okay so one note is height zero right
right right but but if I did redefine it
in your way the proof will all work just
everything that was n would turn to n
minus one and everything that was n
minus 1 will turn to n minus 2 and the
same idea would work
bigger or equal that's as big yeah well
if it does you can't get more than
adding two leaves to every tree and that
was the worst that could have been yeah
there's nothing to this recurrence or
question basically you know when you go
to the next height the worst you can do
is double the leaves so that's why you
only get a factor of two more but
there's a completely different way of
proving this yeah bar all right so let's
start with any arbitrary tree that's
high ten minus one you want to show that
any tree of height n has doubled leaves
so then you have to argue that in order
to get a tree of height n it means you
have to add a leaf to a leaf here right
right yeah I think if you actually wrote
it out it would be a little bit tricky
because in order to go to the next
height you have to specifically say
you're gonna put nodes on the leaves
that are height n minus 1 from the top
you could do it you could you could do
it forward - you can do it this is weak
induction because all we do is assume
that it's true for the N minus 1 case
but now we're going to do strong
induction and I left that the base case
here you can check the base case works
here's strong induction here's a tree I
want to show that it's got at most 2 to
the n leaves here's the normal way of
doing recursion on trees this is the
weird way this is the normal way you got
a left subtree in the right subtree
they're each smaller than the original
tree therefore they each have height
you're getting rid of one from each of
the paths from the root down of the
leaves each of these if this is high ten
then this guy and this guy cannot be
height and they have to be smaller if
either one of these was high ten then
this would be height and plus one and
it's not this is high ten so these have
to be at most high ten minus one so each
of these has at most two to the N minus
one leaves
thing have two times this because the
number of leaves in the big tree is just
the number of leaves on the Left plus
the number of leaves in the right so two
times add is two to the end and that's
the proof this proof is easier and this
is strong induction because we don't
know the size of these two sub trees
they could be much smaller than the
original tree they could be half of it
right so that's a more natural way to
prove things about trees and that's the
more natural way to do algorithms on
trees you almost always split the tree
into two equal parts if you can and do
an algorithm on each one to lower left
you mean this one in this one bye-bye
okay but we can't because it still has
high two you have to know we're just
starting as our starting oh it's your
starting tree okay so now you remove all
the leaves so now it's height one oh
yeah that's a good point
if you if you've gone back to the roof
mmm the argument still holds but but I
didn't carefully describe it Chris is
right there's something strange that
happens if the leaf that you took off is
actually connected to the root it
doesn't make it any worse because you
can only add one more here you can't add
two more so nothing changes in the
argument except that I should mention it
because maybe something might have
changed that's a good point I could say
add the maximum number of least possible
back and it's no more than two then
twice as many but you're right you're
right that's a special case you know to
do anything now the strong induction
right it's much easier to write this
proof down it's much faster Brian but
you wouldn't go from a zero tree to to
one loss because that'd be our base case
right so that wouldn't happen we would
stop at the base case and what you're
really saying is I didn't say with the
base cases here and I should have the
base case is when it gets to zero height
that's 100% right that's true yeah you
take a tree of height n a tree of height
n is made up of the root and the two
potential sub trees one of the either
one of these could be empty doesn't
affect the the argument by induction
each of these sub trees each of these
subjects is one height less than the
original it can't be the same height of
the original because then the original
would have been wouldn't have been at so
each of these sub trees is n minus one
height or less therefore each of these
sub trees has at most two to the n minus
one leaves by induction and if we add
them together we get twice that many
leaves which is two to the n leaves no
no that's not a leaf right if we're not
counting the nodes now Gary we're just
doing leaves so it's just left plus
right if we did have to add the top this
would crash like a like a lead balloon
right it would the whole thing wouldn't
work
we add them back together than we had
less than or equal to two to the n
leaves nice two to the M right make
sense yeah Michael strong cuz you're
just you're saying because these guys
these guys are not n minus one he's got
oh I take it back we don't know for sure
that they right right this one could be
n minus three
but the point is whatever it is it's
going to be smaller than two to the N
minus one right so so they might be
smaller height trees we know one of them
is n minus one that's for sure
otherwise that would never be M okay
other questions all right your cue tired
I can't do any more and what I'm going
to do is I have an important induction
proof that that is on number theory that
I'm going to throw into the recitation
I'll have Tara do that and she's going
to show you how to do it it's the one
with with ad you ball she's going to
show you how to solve any of those by
induction and much more than that she's
going to show you how to get the numbers
at work and how to construct an
induction proof kind of by construction
and create the numbers at work and we're
going to go into that problem in much
more detail and solve a completely in
the last week