Euclid's algorithm and greatest common
divisors and going through some basics
of number theory understanding the idea
of arithmetic modulo other numbers and
we spent yesterday talking about
what we're going to do today is kind of
build on that go through one of the nice
elementary theorems in number theory
which turns out to be it's very abstract
theorem it's very interesting it's very
elegant but it turns out that nowadays
it's at the heart of what makes these
public key cryptography systems work and
we're going to go through this theorem
leave it on the side make sure everybody
understands what it says we're going to
prove it because it's a nice proof and
then we're going to switch gears and
talk about cryptography as a topic as a
subject and there's a lot to talk about
you can do a whole course in it I'm just
going to give you a little brief history
of how people used to encode things and
decode things and then jump right into
how people do it today and basically the
way people do it today is extremely
secure is a way which is virtually
unbreakable and the reason it's
unbreakable is based on the fact that
nobody knows any good algorithm
two-factor very very large numbers into
their primes if somebody had a good
algorithm to do that then all these
cryptography methods that are popular
nowadays would crumble and be easily
breakable and you'll see why you need to
factor large numbers in order to break
this code and until somebody comes up
with any method of factoring large
numbers it works these codes are going
to be essentially completely secure by
the way it's not known whether factoring
large numbers is really a hard problem
nobody knows whether it's np-complete
and nobody's got any good algorithms for
doing it there's a lot of research that
goes into that there are probabilistic
algorithms for trying to determine
whether a number is prime or not
algorithms that don't necessarily tell
you the right answer except they got a
good chance of telling you the right
answer so if you run them a lot you get
a pretty good sense of whether the
numbers primarily you don't know for
sure you know for sure you know within a
1/10 of a percent margin of error that
doesn't tell you how to factor the
number that just tells you whether it's
prime or not but actual factoring is a
hard
that nobody's got a good algorithm for
short of trying all the possibilities
and that's just too slow for the large
numbers we're talking about so that's
where we're headed the history of
cryptography a little bit talking about
where it started where it ends up where
we are today why it connects the number
theory and then doing some examples ok
questions here we go so we're going to
start with a nice theorem that it's all
based on sometimes called from Oz
theorem or from Oz little theorem this
is to distinguish it from from Oz last
theorem which is more famous here's what
from aw says he says take a prime number
P and let a be any number not divisible
by P here's what a theorem says then a
to the P minus 1 is congruent to 1 mod P
that's the theorem there it is up on the
board I'm sure it's in your book as well
it's in a pretty much every number
theory book look at it and try to figure
out what it says in the meantime I'll do
an example and you're already know what
it says if you look at the example so
let's pick a prime number let's say pick
your favorite prime know pick your vowel
pick it yeah you get 5 5 is my favorite
prime and pick any number that's not
divisible by 5 let's say 6 so this
theorem says that's 6 so 6 is a 5 is P
this says that 6 to the 4th is congruent
to 1 mod 5 6 to the 4th is uh 1296
through by 5 you get a remainder of 1 so
I want to make sure everybody knows this
notation this means congruent to 1 mod 5
that means when you divide by 5 you get
a remainder of 1 that's what that
notation means ok that's what the
theorem says and it's true and it always
works and the question is why does it
always work and we're going to try to
prove it and get an idea if you
understand the proof great if you don't
understand the proof it won't affect
your understanding of anything after it
so make sure you understand the fact
that the theorem is true we'll work on
the proof for about 5 minutes or so and
then we'll move on to cryptography I
just picked it out of a hat it's any
number a that's not the visible by P
let's try another number 11 to the
fourth well that also ends in ends and 1
right so some of these are easy to see
some are harder to see I picked 5
because it's easy to see that it's true
usually oh that should work as long as
it's not divisible by P anything less
than P should work there are 4 to the
4th what's that the 4th is 256 yeah yeah
I know it should work fine for things
less than people other questions all
right so why is this true the proof is
really kind of clever and it's a good
example of how you can kind of come up
with very interesting theorems and the
argument as to why the true is really
really elegant so I'm going to do this
argument in its generality I usually do
arguments with a particular example so
the things are easier to understand but
I don't think you'll miss the point if I
do this in general so here's what we're
going to do and follow me along we're
going to I'm going to convince you that
in general P is going to divide evenly
into a to the P minus 1 minus 1 that if
I take this one away from here then P
will divide evenly there that's the same
as showing that there's a remainder of
when I divide by pit so how am I going
to do that here's how we're going to
start I'm going to start out considering
this sequence of numbers a 2 a 3 a all
the way up to P minus 1 times a just
consider the sequence in the example we
just did that would be 6 12 18 24 we'd
go up 2 4 times 6 6 12 18 24 maybe I
shouldn't do a specific example while I
do the general example look at these
numbers with respect to 2 5 what are the
remainders of these numbers with respect
to 5 let's write them down 1 2 3 4
they're all different the first thing
you need to notice is that is completely
not coincidental it doesn't matter
whether the number was 6 and our prime
was 5 so we did it 4 times it with any a
and with any P this sequence of numbers
is going to give congruence --is mod P
that are all distinct let's try to
figure out why that's true doesn't
necessarily start with 1 but they're all
be distinct now why is that take any two
of these any two at all they differ by
multiples of what's the difference
between them multiples of a right to a
and 7a
they differ by a multiple of a what I'm
going to convince you is that if I take
any two of these and I look at their
difference that that difference will
never be a multiple of P if they're
going to have the same congruence with
respect to P then the difference between
them would have to be a multiple of P if
they're both Congre to 1 then the
difference between them would be a
multiple of 5 I'm going to convince you
that the difference between any two is
never a multiple of P the difference
between any two of these would never be
a multiple of 5 there
they have to be congruent to different
numbers with respect to Phi how do you
know that any multiple of a seven a six
a up the P minus 1/a
how do you know that none of them are
going to get the visible by my pity
it well that was lucky
right right right you're both right P
can never divide into a because that was
our main assumption without that
assumption this doesn't work so P will
never divide into a why can't P divided
into say the difference is like like
like 8 times it it won't go into a we
know that but maybe it'll go into the 8
well look at all these numbers that
could be the differences between these
guys right they're going to be either 1
2 3 all the way up to P minus 1 P can't
go with 2 something less than itself so
there's no way if you take any pair of
these and you subtract it that their
difference is going to be divisible by P
there's no way you could take any pair
of these and subtract them and expect
the difference to be divisible by 5 the
difference between these two is 12 the
difference between these two is 12
between these two is 18 the differences
are none of them are divisible by 5
therefore no pair could have the same
congruence with respect to that yes I
single one of them is divisible by 5
although I didn't mention it explicitly
that none of these could be divisible by
P and no difference between any two
could be divisible by P the difference
between any pair is very important
because that shows that the congruence
with respect to P of this one in the
congruence with respect to P of this one
are going to be different if they were
the same then the difference between
them would be a multiple of P and the
difference between them can't be a
multiple of P that's what we've we've
discussed because the difference between
any pair here has to be some multiple of
a
and it's got to be some multiple of a
that's less than P minus one multiples
the same reason that any individual one
can't be divisible by P that's the same
reason that the difference between any
two can't be divisible by P because the
difference between any two is the same
as one of these individual yeah Chun
mean it means it means the following
that somehow if I figured out the
conference's of all these numbers with
respect to P and I wrote them down I
have all the numbers how many congresses
do you have with respect to P you can
have one you can have two three four all
the way up to P minus one we're not
going to get zero here right it's not
ever divisible by P now they could be in
any order we want so we have to come up
with an argument here that doesn't use
any order so here's our argument so I
didn't write this down but you should
have in your notes every one of these
has to have a different congruence with
respect to P okay make that note to
yourselves and here's what we say then
so hence I'm going to multiply all these
things together
equation if this one and this one and
this one and this one all together come
up with all the congresses from 1 to P
minus 1 I don't know what order they are
so if I multiply them all together I
know that they're going to equal to the
product of all those conferences I just
don't know what order but if I'm
multiplying I don't really care about
the order so this is going to be 1 times
2 times 3 all the way up to P minus 1
mod p there's a seer but there's no A's
here what happened to it because I know
that each of these individually is going
to be congruent to one of these numbers
1 2 3 up to P minus 1 and each of them
is going to be congruent to a different
one so if I multiply these all together
and I check their congruence with
respect to P it's going to be equal to
the product of all the congresses
together I just don't know what order so
I might as well just write it in
ascending order okay yeah because we
know they all have to be different and
there's P minus one of them so we've got
to have one of each and that's the right
question to ask that's what makes this
argument so clever we've shown that
there can't be duplicates we know we
have to get P minus one of them so the
only choices are one all the way up
through P minus one all right so let's
check to make sure this works okay so
that what would this mean in the example
that we just did it would mean that six
times twelve times 18 times 24 is
congruent to so 1 times 2 times 3 times
4 mod 5 that better be true well we know
that 6 is congruent to 1 and 12 is
congruent to 2 and 18s congruent to 3
and 24 is congruent to 4 so this should
work and you can multiply it out and
check when you multiply these all
together you get all terms that have
multiples of 5s in them except for the
only term that doesn't necessarily have
a multiple of 5 is 1 times 2 times 3
times 4
all the other terms have multiples of
fives in them that's another way to look
at it okay yes Congress these two are
the same because if we don't care about
multiples of five they're equal this is
what conference means seven and two are
congruent mod five because they differ
by a multiple of five twelve and two are
talking to our Congress mod five okay
it's it's a way of saying that it's a
way of actually setting up an
equivalence relation on all the numbers
in the world two and seven and 12 and 17
and 22 are all on the same equivalence
relation they're all the same
anything that differ by five are all the
same right so what I'm saying is that
none of these are the same with respect
to 2p they're all different so it makes
sense okay Joe what's your what that's
what the definition means what this
means is that you subtract two from
seven and you see if it's the visible by
five check the difference to the two and
see if they're divisible by five okay
yeah they both have the same remainder
right so all the numbers in the world
are in five classes either they're
divisible by five or they have a
remainder of one or they have a
remainder of two or they have a
remainder of three or they have a
remainder of 4 every single numbers in
one of those equivalence classes and you
can prove that that relation of
congruent is reflexive symmetric and
transitive so it's so it's partitions
all the integers into one of five groups
you're very familiar with one thing just
like this
odd and even numbers right on and even
numbers are just numbers that are
congruent mod not - right okay so
there's two equivalence classes there
the odd numbers and the even numbers
yeah no I was saying yeah the reason
you're asking is the only every time you
have mod P in parentheses is at the end
of an equation to mean that this
equality is only true modulo P meaning
it's only true if we don't care about
differences that are multiples of P but
these two are the same if the remainder
is the same when you divide by P all
those are no I think that's the only
place that's the main place you would
see it yeah yeah well I mean it I don't
know I mean you probably you might see
it somewhere else but but yeah but
that's yeah you'd see it like this but
that's the same as that it's two equals
seven mod 5 oh and a computer program
you might see it as an operator right
you'd see it like this in a computer
program 7 mod 2 that is a completely
different meaning 7 by 2 equals 1 7
about 5 equals 2 right 7 mod 2 it means
what is the remainder of 7 when you
divide 2 into it no not unless it was a
computer program right
you see you'd see it like this right
it's a % right and in Pascal they
actually called it the word mod but
outside of the language Pascal I don't
think people generally use the word mod
as an operator generally not right well
if you think you'd have a different
symbol for it I mean you often talk
about the remainders of things and you'd
say you could you could use the word mod
you could use % you could use you could
use the greatest you could use the upper
ceiling but there's a lot of ways to
describe mod it's basically a division
where you subtract the whole number part
away so there's lots of ways to do it
and then and then round down and then
subtract you get mod all right are we
back on track other questions
we take these numbers we multiply them
through and presumably 24 mod 5 is going
to be what 4 so presumably if we
multiply these all together we'll get a
remainder 4 and you will and this is
true so where do we go from here we're
actually not too far here from here we
can actually get there in a couple of
steps and then the proofs going to be
done so the main logic in this proof is
going from here to here and writing it
down I'm going to regroup here a little
bit how many a is do I have P minus 1 a
so I got a to the P minus 1 right times
what
I got P minus 1 A's and I got 1 2 3 4
all the way up to P minus 1 that's this
side and I'll subtract the other side
off what do I get down the other side P
minus 1 factorial this is the difference
between the left and the right side and
if there are cron Grant mod P it means
and we write it like this and this means
that P divides this equally evenly so
this implies this this means that P
divides the difference between these two
4 mod 5 so when you subtract them from
each other there's going to be a
multiple of 5 between them so things
that are congruent to 4 mod 5 would be 4
9 14 etc so if you subtract any two of
them you get a multiple of 5 or in this
case a multiple of P joy you had a
question you had a look on your face a
second ago
now it's gone I could do that if you see
that fine then no reason that's fine you
get it completely I'm just trying to
well I'm trying to break it up into
smaller steps this implies this and
we're trying to get to this so we have
one more step to get there P divides P
minus 1 factorial times a to the P minus
1 do that right minus 1 there we go
that's what I'm looking for I factored
out a P minus 1 factorial so if P
divides this can P divided P minus 1
factorial all the numbers here are
smaller than P all right there's no
factor here that's as big as this prime
number so this prime number will never
ever divide anything in here so if it
divides this product and it can't divide
the first part therefore it has to
divide the second part okay it's like
saying a 5 divides into 4 times 3 times
2 times 1 times something else well it's
not going to be able to divine it to any
of these so it's got to be able to
divide into this one so this implies
that P divides into a to the P minus 1
minus 1 and that's exactly what this
says ok that P divides into the
difference between a to the P minus 1
and 1 so the main step in the proof is
going from here to here and then there's
just a little algebra let me stop this
ends this contained part of the lecture
today so we're done with this proof if
you have questions on it I'll stop now
if you if you don't get the proof it's
ok just understand what the proof says
understand the result and if you do get
the proof or you have some more
questions let me take them now yeah
Donna that's a good question whenever
those conditions you kind of want to
make sure that they're necessary right
why does P F to be a prime number where
did we use it in any step in this step
here right Barack thinks it helps here
what do you think you know what if this
number wasn't 5 what did this number was
8 that's not a prime number then I can't
say it doesn't divide here it could
divide this because 4 times 2 gives you
8 but when it's prime I know it's not
going to be able to divide any possible
combinations of these because there's no
way to split that number up into pieces
because it's a prime number so it's used
in this step from
going here to here and Gary maybe that's
the step that you kind of internalized
in your head but really needs a
description P divides the second part
because P can't divide this part and the
reason it can't divide this part is
because P is a prime number otherwise
you would get stuck here and there'd be
no guarantee that P divides this part P
might divide the whole thing only
because it divides this first part do
you get it Donna that's a very good
question and it's a very natural
question to ask are there other
questions you write down the alphabet
abcdefg all the way up to XYZ and now
let's just shift up all the letters by
some fixed amount say by 3 so like a is
going to turn into D and B you'll turn
into e f g and z would be c and this
would be B okay I mean kids do this so
you get on cereal boxes right this kind
of in chromatic decoders right magic
decoder rings right the same idea
now let's I encoded a message just like
this you had no idea how I encoded it
but but this is the way I actually did
it you know so I have a whole message
encoded this way how would you decode it
Ryan's only 26 combinations right
there's only 26 ways I could have done
it try all 26 25 of them will probably
be gibberish and one will be a message
and you're done you can do this by hand
in a few minutes if you had a computer
you can do it in a couple of seconds
right it's not a hard thing to do so
even in World War 2 this is obviously
not good enough even in ancient times
this isn't good enough you need
something a little better so here's a
way to make it much more complicated or
what seems to be more complicated at
first glance a way anyway to make it
more complicated is let's call this the
let's call this the D encoding okay
because I start with D and move away
okay so now let's what's getting code
this way I have a code word called
dumbbells how do you spell dumbbell 2
B's yeah dumbbells ok here's the way I'm
going to encode a message let's say I
have a message hello here's how I would
encode it I would take
eh and encode it using the D encoding
scheme so that would turn it into a K
and then I take the e and encode it
using the U encoding scheme whatever
that ends up being and then I take the L
and encode it using the M and the other
L and code it using a B and the O using
the other B and if the message goes on
and on and on sooner or later I hit the
end of my encoding word and then I wrap
around to the beginning everybody got
the idea this is much harder to decode
how many different possible things do
you have to try completely brute-force
to decode a message that was encoded
like this if you have no idea what the
code word is if you don't know anything
they're really in trouble so let's say
you get a spy and you figure out the
length of the cowork codeword twenty six
one two three four five six seven eight
right we could all count now that's a
lot what if you have a codeword that's
thirty five symbols long it's not so
practical to do this anymore okay
because it gets to be 26 to the 30
something everybody get the idea of why
this is better this really just shoots
it up an exponential amount but this is
exactly the kind of encoding the Germans
used give or take and it's exactly the
kind of stuff that was routinely broken
using a combination of computer help and
a combination of ingenuity so without
getting too much into the details how
would you go ahead and try to solve
something like this without just brute
force trying them all Rob Yemen
is actually one of the main ways they do
it maybe I should follow up a little bit
and being specific about Rob's
suggestion here's here's one method
every language seems to have some
frequency of how often the letters show
up in typical messages everybody knows
this if you watch wheel of fortune right
and it's like you know this because I'm
wheel of fortune when somebody gets up
there you know and I know what you have
to spend some money that to Tobiah to
get a letter or something so you got a
letter and you guess Z is there a Z and
it's just like the crowd groans get a
clue right Z hmm
no no I mean X I mean Q right so
everybody knows that some letters come
in more frequently and you can do this
very scientifically you can say say in
in in theater productions the letters
group in this way in letters one to
another
the letters group this way there might
the percentages might be a little off
and certain types of ways of expressing
yourself in a particular language you
get this many percentage of E's this
many percentages of F's this many
percentages of these you can do this and
you can get people to calculate it for
you so how does that help here's how it
helps let's go here to the H the H was
encoded using D right now let's move on
one two three four five six seven eight
the eighth letter is also going to be
encoded using D so you take the message
that you intercepted you take the first
the eighth the the ninth one two three
four five six seven eight right the
first the ninth the seventeenth you take
a whole equivalence class of letters
first nine seventeen 2635 to take all
those letters you put them in a big big
group and you look to see you look to
see what happens when you encode them on
each of the 26 possible decode them in
each of the 26 possible ways which one
gives you a collection of letters most
like the ones
you expect to have in the language that
you're decoding which one looks most
like German now when you do this you get
a lot that might look like German maybe
three or four of them look like German
instead of all 26 so now instead of 26
chances here we got it narrowed down to
just three and maybe here it turns out
that one is really strikingly like
German and the rest are not so this goes
down to one
suddenly the 26 to the eighth goes way
down to something that you could
actually do with a machine or by hand
and that's more or less how they went
ahead trying to break the codes in a in
a hit-or-miss kind of fashion ad hoc
hoping that by these percentage tricks
they could get it down to a reasonable
amount they could actually look at write
switch this key right you need a lot of
data to get good information so if you
keep the key for a long time you're
going to be dead because the people will
get enough data and be able to decode it
at the same time the other thing you
want to switch is the length if we don't
know the length of this keyword we can't
do this at all we don't know what the
equivalence classes are we don't know
that it's the first in the ninth and the
and the 18th and the second and the
tenth and the 19th we don't know what to
do
so getting the length is very important
predicting the length of the next
keyword is important and that was done
with a combination of espionage and all
sorts of other tricks guessing the
method they use to pick the length of
the next keyword
good so you can make backward inferences
as to what the length of the keyword is
based on unrepeated letters that's true
next stage
all of these encryption methods at least
theoretically with enough computing
power can be decoded if you guess well
enough and you have some he'll certainly
if you have a good spy you're completely
dead if you steal the code word then
decoding it is trivial all right you
just go backwards so the goal is to get
an encoding scheme where you can publish
the encoding scheme in the newspaper so
everyone knows how to encode the message
but even though you've published the
encoding scheme in the newspaper
nobody can easily use that to go
backwards now it seems like that's
impossible at first glance because if I
publish the codeword everybody can go
backwards okay adding numbers modulo 26
which is what we're doing with this
alphabet code is the same as subtracting
numbers modulo 6 there's no difference
it's the same arithmetic it's just as
easy so we need to come up with a
function that's different than adding
numbers modulo another number because
the inverse of that subtracting numbers
modulo another number is too easy we
need to go up with a function whose
inverse is hard okay so squaring numbers
the inverses square rooting numbers
whatever you can do forward it seems you
can do backwards so we need to come up
with an example that you can too easily
backwards all right and that's what is
done today you publish the public way of
encoding anybody can encode it but just
because that's published doesn't mean
anybody can decode it everybody is stuck
for decoding it so everybody can encode
something hand it to the person next to
them and ask them what was this when it
started and none of the people would
know even though they had just encoded
something themselves
all right that's the idea we're going to
show how this works all the details I
mean oh nothing will be left out all
right questions about this all right so
how do you use something like this if
you have something like this then you
can
my stuff on the internet even if you're
a paranoid lunatic right it doesn't
matter you can you can you can think
that the whole world is wanting to steal
your credit card and you would never
ever like leave a carbon in the old days
like in a garbage can you'd rip it into
shreds if you're a person like that
you're completely safe because you
encode your credit card with a publicly
you know printed algorithm and you send
it over the Internet and nobody can
decode it well somebody's got to decode
it right so there's so there is a way to
decode it but you need special
information that information is secret
that information is in the hands of one
particular person so say you have a
company and they want to take orders by
credit card they hold the secret piece
of information that helps them do the
inverse the decoding in a vault they use
that to decode and they publish in the
newspaper the way you encode it so
everybody can send them their credit
cards and only they can figure out what
the credit card numbers really are so
suddenly you can buy securely right
another way that this is used is a way
that doesn't seem obvious at first I'm
not going to show you how to do it yet
but I'll show you another way to use it
what if I don't want to just send secure
information what if I want to send
something to Chris and it's not
particularly secure I don't really care
if anybody sees it but I want him to
know that it's from me okay he sent say
say he went on vacation and he sent in a
problem set and he wants to know whether
I got it so I want to send a message
that says yes I got your problem said I
don't give a hoot if anybody sees that
message but I want him to know that that
message came from me and that nobody
just forged it and you know wants him to
think that his problem set got there you
can imagine this is very important right
I mean this is for signatures I want to
close a real estate deal right and
nobody really cares about the details of
the deal but you want to know that I
signed it that I saw this deal and I
said okay you're on the other end you
want to verify that it came from me
so how do you do that you can do that
with the same scheme even though it
doesn't seem like you can so here's the
trick we have this public
encoding that anybody can do
and we have this private decoding so
here's like here's how I can send a
message to Chris and make sure that it's
that it works I publish a public
encoding out on the on the world anybody
can see it it's on a webpage somewhere
and I keep the private thing for me and
I take my name Sai Simonson and I decode
my name with my private code I turned it
into something else
some encrypted ugly thing that it came
from and then I send that privately
decoded name over the Internet at the
end of my message and Chris sees it and
it looks like gibberish and he runs the
public encoding program to encode it to
see what it turns out to be and if it
turns out to be shy Simonson then he
knows it's for me
how come because nobody could
conceivably come up with the decoded
version of my name because they don't
have the private information nobody
could figure out what choice Ayman said
would look like if it got backward
decoded so I can guarantee that it was
me now the thing is if I routinely do
this and I just use my name it gives
people an infinite amount of time to
sooner or later
figure out what this is and maybe they
could figure out my private information
or steal it somehow and then they'll
know that that my name decodes back to
this particular XYZ queue and they'll
send X Y Z queue to anybody and they'll
Forge my name so the way this is
actually done in practices instead of
using your name to decode you send a
message some arbitrary message and you
make up some public function about that
message like count the number of e's in
this message and you turn that into a
number and then you decode that number
and send it to chris chris can count the
number of e's in the message he knows
how many there should be he encodes that
number I sent him and if the encoding
matches the actual number of E's in the
message then he knows that it came from
me because I'm the only one who would
know how to take that number of e's and
send it back to the originally encoded
message yeah burrow him
intercept your message well but if he
well he would intercept the message oh
and steal the but but and that's true
but if I but if I did it this last way I
just described
he could only intercept my message and
impersonate me for this particular
message he could send any message with
that number of E's in it if he knew that
right but that's public that
informations public so that Chris can
use it and right he could send any
number of he could send any message that
with that particular number of E's in it
right but the idea is that that
particular function I talked about you
know the number of e's it's typically
some hash function that that means it
takes this big message and turns it into
some number and say we change it every
week right if it could go to a lot of
different possibilities his computer
calculates which possibility ended up
being I do it too but I decode it and
he's the only one who can check that it
came from me well everybody can check
that he came from me but I'm the only
one who could have decoded it to begin
with so we're going to get this I decide
use a little tricky you can do both
these ideas if I have my own public
private scheme and somebody else has
their public private scheme I can use
their scheme to encode a message I can
use Chris's scheme to encode a message
publicly and send it to him he's the
only one who'll be able to decode it I
use my private scheme to decode my
signature or a hash function on the
message when he gets it he uses his he's
is my public encoding to encode my name
to see if it's the same as a hash
function and he uses his private
decoding to decode the message that I
encrypted so you can send messages
securely and you can have the name or
signature be completely verifiable this
version
is going to be possible if you have the
public information to figure out the
private information then I'm just going
to turn the dial up a little bit and
that version is not going to be easy to
get the private information so I'm going
to get you started on an easier example
where you could figure out the private
information if you had the public
information where you could decode if
you know how to encode and then I'm
going to show you how to just turn it up
a little bit and the decoding stuff gets
gets too hard
it requires factoring really big numbers
ok questions so far all right so here's
how we're going to do it in these
examples we're imagining that our
messages are all converted into numbers
and the numbers are then converted into
other numbers so so we send everything
as numbers it just makes it easier to
present the whole idea so if you have a
message of characters convert all those
characters to numbers in some particular
way run it through your encoding scheme
send the new numbers to somebody else
they convert them back to so the numbers
you sent and then convert them into
letters all right so here's how it's
done
you start by picking a prime number any
number at all let's say 17 and then you
pick another number
tschüss let's call it E such that the
greatest common divisor of E + 16 is 1
encoding choose an e such that the
greatest common divisor of E and 1 less
than this number the 16 is P minus 1 I'm
doing a specific example but you could
do it in general with any prime number
choose a number YZ such that the
greatest common divisor of e'en 16 is 1
so I'm going to pick equals 5 eg for
example e equals 5 this isn't too
involved so don't expect too much more
it's actually almost here this
information the five and the 17
published in the newspaper on the web
someplace where anybody can get to it
that's the information we need to do
encoding and I'm going to show you how
you do encoding yet so let's say it why
don't one code some number let's say six
power to the e f-- power now this is
what Tony's asking before the answer is
yes to your question do you ever use
Ahmad as an operator you do six to the
fifth mod 17 means what's the remainder
of six to the fifth with respect to 17
yeah yeah well here's a straightforward
answer finally I understand what you're
asking
six to the fifth mod 17 that means take
six to the fifth divided up by 17 and
tell me what the remainder is okay
anybody know what that is I know what it
is what is it yeah sweet that's between
0 and 16 so what is it it's sabot you
get a computer to do it for you
it now you know how to encode numbers
somebody publishes this information you
take the thing you want to encode you
raise it to this power your mind by the
17 the 17 is the prime this power is the
e you have to know which numbers which
you don't want to do six to the
seventeen not five you have to know that
this is Ian this is the prime so it's
given to you in order you're told that
this is the exponent this is the prime
that's how you do encoding all right
questions so far question is how do you
decode and with this we're going to come
up with a whole issue of how to make
sure the decoding is hard encoding is
easy if you have this information how do
you decode you get seven you're
wondering what message was sent mmm
seven I wonder what this person really
meant they really meant six but how do
you figure out that they meant six the
reverse function is very similar to this
function it's going to be seven to the
something mod 17 and in particular the
number here is going to be 13 that's the
secret code I'll call this private
information private info is thirteen
seventeen seventeen is really public so
I'm going to circle the thirteenth the
public needs one number and the prime
number the private person who's decoding
needs the public prime and another
special number if you do seven to the
thirteen mod 17 you get back to what you
started now I'm going to tell you where
that thirteen comes from and I'm going
to tell you why this works and then
we're going to figure out how hard it
would be to figure out thirteen given
just 5 and 17 ok so far right now this
is just magic you can check this and see
that it works but it but it does so
then I'll show you why this works let's
call that 13 D here's the 13 you want to
pick a D a private piece such that when
you multiply D and E you get something
congruent to 1 mod 16 if you're
wondering why the hell would you want
that it's very important this condition
is what makes this thing work and you'll
see why in a second but for now let's
just understand what it's saying in our
particular example a is 5 so we want a
number such that 5 times that number is
congruent to 1 mod 16 the 16 is one less
than the prime we started ok so if it
was a general prime would be P minus 1
there well let's do this in our heads
what number times 5 is congruent to 1
mod 16 well the answer is 13 5 times 13
is 65 if you divide 65 by 16 it goes in
4 times with a remainder of 1 that's how
you get D so it seem like it's hard it
seemed like it's easy we'll get back to
that in a little while okay but that's
how you would compute Z the fives of
public information right we'll get back
later and figure out how to compute D in
just 5 minutes but let's go back here
and see why this works are there
questions so far
add multiples of yep right you picked
the one between 0 and 15 its unique with
with mod 16 yeah
that's unique okay by the way there
doesn't even have to be a D if 5 and 16
are not greatest common devisor 1
remember I said 5 and 16 have to be
greatest common devisor 1 the reason for
that is that there's a solution to this
equation if 5 and 16 are not greatest
common divisor 1 if it's like 5 and 25
or something then there might not even
be a solution to this so it's important
that that condition is true at the
beginning so that we get a solution to
those we'll talk about this solution how
we do it in a couple minutes but first
let's go back here and convince
ourselves if this works the reasoning
that this works is the way that the real
one is going to work so concentrating on
this next idea is is going to help you
just zoom through the actual idea in a
couple of minutes why does this stuff
work here's what we have to show we have
to show that if you take your hidden
value let's call it m and you raise it
to the fifth six to the fifth and then
you take that you get a seven and then
you take that seven and you raise it to
the 13th that you get back to what you
started with so we want to show that if
I take m to the fifth and then I raise
it to the 13th so M to the fifth to the
13th that's M to the 5 times 13 that
that's going to be congruent to first to
the fifth end to the 13th gets you back
to and gets you back to what you started
with mod 16 mod 17 sorry
encoding followed by a decoding is going
to get you back to what you started that
this is going to be the encoding and
that's going to be the decoding that
they're inverse functions of each other
first due to the fifth then due to the
thirteenth you start with six you end up
with six why is that true I'm going to
convince you this is true and it's based
on for my little theorem questions so
far this five times thirteen what do you
know about it what do you know about
that sixty-five
know that there's going to be remainder
of one here right I constructed these
two numbers five and thirteen
specifically so that they would be a
total of one more than 16 that they
would have a remainder of 1 with respect
to 16 so when I multiply them together I
can write them as 4 times 16 plus 1
right that comes from this computation
so now I have that n times n to the 5
times 13 is M to the some multiple of 16
plus 1 well where do I go from there
I've used my one main assumption I'm out
of assumptions all I got left is for my
little theorem here I better be close to
done
16 times 4 times M what do you know
about this if this turns into one Conger
and some set mod 17 then we get M as our
final answer how do you know that this
is going to be 1 mod 17 how do we know
that M to the 16 times 4 is congruent to
1 mod 17 from Oz theorem says give me
any number that's not the visible by 17
then and to the 16th is congruent to 1
all right that's what form oz Last
Theorem would say that M to the 16th is
congruent to 1 but if M to the 16th is
congruent to 1 then if I multiply it by
itself four more times it's just gonna
be 1 times 1 times 1 times 1 it's still
going to be congruent to 1 so this part
is 1 this part is congruent to 1 by 4
mods last theorem so the whole thing m
to the 65 is congruent to M the whole
thing works because this piece here ends
up being 1 because of Verma's Last
Theorem questions about this M is not
divisible by 17 we pick a number so
large that our ends are always smaller
yes right if M was divisible by 17 this
wouldn't necessarily work so we make
sure that M is smaller than 17 and we're
safe yeah Brian
divide through by 17 is 1 right if I
take this say 6 to the 64th and I
subtract 1 and I divide up by 17 I get
an even value the clear makes sense ok
other questions about this
ok so let's review the public
information is 5 and 17 the private
information is 13 and 17 the 13 is the
number that satisfies this equation and
I convinced you if I first go through
and take my message and raise it to the
fifth to that II and I do a congruence
mod 17 and then I raise it to the D I
get back to what I started with because
the multiples of 16 here end up being
congruent to 1 mod 17 so the only thing
that's left over is an M which is what I
started with here so the whole thing
works
these two are inverses of each other
it's a really cool thing but the
question is how hard is it to figure out
D once somebody's published 5 and 17 how
hard is it to figure out 6 if somebody
tells you 5 and 17 how hard is it to
solve this equation how hard is it to
figure out 13 right well let's see let's
pretend we didn't tell you the answer
was 13 and we try to solve this equation
what does this equation say it says find
me D such that 5 D minus 1 is divisible
by 16 right equals 16 times pick a
letter P some multiple of 16 or find me
D and P such that v D minus 16 P equals
1 have you ever done anything like this
before
yes right that's what we spent the whole
day yesterday doing you know that 5 and
16 have a greatest common divisor of 1
that was a big assumption we made if it
has a greatest common divisor of
you can find a DEP to make this equation
equal one so finding D given E is as
straightforward as using Euclid's
algorithm and doing a backward
substitution in fact it's easy it's not
hard to get the inverse if I publish
five and seventeen than anybody with a
computer and about three seconds can say
hey the private one is 13 and 17 so this
is at the point where we need to just
turn up the volume a little notch the
same exact idea can be milked one step
further where the computation of the 13
becomes very hard instead of very easy
ok so here's the main idea and so stick
with me don't get tired right now this
is the most important part the next step
does this it publishes instead of
publishing 5 and 17 it's going to
publish 5 and some big big big number
which is not prime I'm not going to use
a big number because it's going to be
impossible to show you the example I'm
going to use a small number but you can
imagine that the number is very big I'm
going to publish the number 34 normally
you would publish a number which is a
product of two 128-bit prime numbers ok
a huge number which has huge factors
hard to factor I'm publishing 34 you
could all factor it to 2 and 17 I'm
going to convince you we're going to do
the same similar trick but when this
number is published we can't do anything
until this number gets factored since we
can factor this number will be able to
go through the whole thing and recompute
the private key but if you couldn't
factor this number you'd be stuck and
I'm going to show you why and what point
this all happens in just a second so
that's where we're headed questions
about this all right so the private key
is no longer known it's a mystery and
now we've published 5 and 34 just as
before if you want to encode 6 it's 6 to
the fifth but this time it's mod 34
instead of mana prime number now it's
not some other big number which is a
product of two primes I'm going to write
here a product of two large large prime
numbers this is not a great example of
that two and seventeen are not large two
is about the smallest prime number you
can get but normally these are two
really big prime numbers you multiply
them together so there's only two
factors in this huge number okay finding
them would be hard and you encode the
same way and you're going to decode in a
similar way six to something mod 34 and
I'll tell you the secret the secret is
that the private code here is also 13 so
you would decode this way actually this
ends up equaling did I do this one
remember but I'll just write it this way
I'll call this X I'll call this X so
encode you're raised to the fifth power
to decode you're raised to the 13th
power the question is how do you find
out this 13 the computation of the 13 in
this situation is going to be harder
it's going to have us require to be able
to factor these numbers yeah EJ you know
I'm just saying take whatever you want
and you decode it this way it now call
it Y yeah yeah yeah this would be M and
this would be M inverse yeah yeah I
should use a different letter okay
this one codes back to two six okay I
don't think we need it but but we can go
on okay where does this 34 a cut from I
said it comes from two primes in this
case you know the primes are we'll call
them P and Q 2 and 17 before we
subtracted one from our single prime in
the two prime situation we're going to
subtract one from each of these so we
get P minus one times Q minus one and
that's 1 times 16 and that equals 16 I
set this up so we get the same 16 that
we got before so we don't have to do a
lot more calculations that we get the
same 13 but normally you would find the
two primes you'd subtract 1 from each
you would get 16
problem five times D is congruent to 1
mod 16 same thing we did before and D is
therefore 13 by using the same methods
we did before the difference here is
that we didn't get to this equation
until we did this step over here we
didn't know this number 16 until we
first did what until we first took 34
factored it out subtracted 1 from each
and multiply them together you can't get
to this point until you factor a very
big number this step here is the slow
step we can't figure out D until we do
this factoring of this of 34 factoring
is a very hard thing to do you take two
huge numbers multiply them together get
something here and then give it to
somebody and say what two numbers that I
start with and they can sit for three
weeks and they won't be able to do it so
multiplying two prime numbers is easy
extracting them once they're multiplied
together is very hard so I need to still
convince you that this does the inverse
of this that if you do X to the fifth
and then you do X to the 13th that you
still get back to X even if you do it in
this peculiar way where the D is
computed via the 16 which came from a P
minus 1 Q minus 1 instead of just the
original single problem why does the
whole thing still work and that's going
to wrap the whole thing up so before I
do that let me stop for final questions
then I'll do that it'll take five or ten
minutes and we'll be done are there any
questions so far we set it up the first
way just relative to a single prime and
it turned out that it ended up with this
equation which we could calculate the
private value for the same way we did
before you calculate 5d minus 16 P
equals 1 you calculate two values to
make this true and that's what we did
yesterday with Euclid's algorithm
the same exact way we did it before the
question is how did we know it was
should be 16 and that takes a lot of
work because we have to factor to find
that 16 is a lot of prime numbers you
mean your idea of factoring to a large
number is to try every pair of primes
and see if they work that's an algorithm
and it would take a long time yeah let's
check this and see that it works and
then I'll stop for final questions and
we'll wrap up the 34 is what's published
now and the 16 is calculated from a
factoring that lets me calculate the
private code the private code comes from
a comes from this equation with respect
to 16 the 16 was calculated by factoring
the numbers and subtracting one from
each and multiplying them together right
2 times 17 234 the 2 times 17 came from
factoring the 34 so the only thing left
to show is that this whole thing still
works that that the that the X to the
third that the Y to the 13th is really
the inverse of the X to the 5 but there
really are backwards that they do the
opposites of each other so let's go
through the argument again because it's
the same argument as before with one
little twist 5d is congruent to 1 mod 16
5 times 13 65 is congruent to one is
remainder of 1 with respect to 16 the
same reason is before because of this
equation so up till here it's the same
argument as before and we want to show
now that this whole thing is 1 but this
time we want to show that it's one not
congruent to 17 which is immediately
from from AHS little theorem we want to
show that this is congruent to 1 mod 34
everybody see the difference that's the
only place where we have to make a
different argument so I'm going to write
this down over here get a little bit of
room
and analyze it because it's not too
tough we're hoping that X to the 4 times
16 is congruent to 1 mod 34 if that's
true we're all set now we know it's
congruent to 1 mod 17 because from Oz
less theorem says you put a 17 there and
X to the 16th is going to be one
multiples of it are also going to be 1
so now what happens with a 34 there are
we just dead I mean it still works out
so how can we prove that it works out
before what about this is that true
that going to be true that the other
prime number let's let's look at let's
look at EJ's idea you want to write 16
as in other words it's the same as 1
times 1 times 16 what EJ is pointing out
where did we get the 16 from it was P
minus 1 times Q minus 1 right so it's 4
times 16 maybe it's hard to see it with
the two what if it was let me stick with
the 2 that's 16 times 1 so let's try to
use for my little theorem again if
there's a 2 here what number can you put
here what exponent can you use one less
than it right so there is a 1 explicitly
there we don't write it in 16 times 1 is
6 P minus 1 times Q minus 1 so 4 Moz
Last Theorem little theorem says that X
to the 1 is congruent to 1 mod 2 so
multiples of that are also going to be
congruent to 1 not 2 this is completely
symmetric P minus 1 and Q minus 1 are
together making up 16 so they both
appear here times 4 this one's going to
be congruent to 1 mod 17 because 16 is
one less and this is going to be
congruent to 1 mod 2 because 1 is 1 less
I want to show that X to the 64th is
congruent to 1 mod 34 and all I've shown
now is that it's congruent to 1 mod 17
incongruent to 1 mod 2
let's remind ourselves what this means
it means I've got some big ugly number
here I don't care what it is call it
whatever you want X to the fourth to the
64th let's give it a name let's call it
B for big and ugly I know that B minus
one is the visible by 17 and B minus one
is divisible by two
okay the B is X to the 64th you got some
big number it's divisible by 17 that's a
prime it's a visible y2 that's another
prime therefore the biz X to the 64th
that's the B's if you ever have two
prime numbers and they each divide into
some other number then their product
also has to divide into that number you
can prove that if you want to but it's
kind of logical uh when is this not sure
what if they're not prime is it can you
give an example where it doesn't work
what if 4 divides into a number and 6
divides into a number does 24 divided
into the number 4 divides into 12 6
divides into 12 24 doesn't divide into
12 because they're composite so little
pieces of this can combine together in a
way that you wouldn't necessarily expect
there's overlap in the factors but if
these two are prime and they each divide
into here that means that prime factor
has to be a part of this and this prime
factor has to be a part of this so their
product must also divide into it
therefore 34 also divides into X to the
64th minus 1 34 also divides into B
minus 1 therefore this is true because
these two numbers 17 into our prime for
yeah
we proved that it would next to the 64
from Oz little theorem if there's a 2
here then anything to the 1 is going to
be congruent to 1 so X 2 they anything
is congruent to 1 X to the 1 is hung on
to 1 multiples of that will also be
congruent to 1 it may be not the best
example to see it with a 2 but pretend
this was a 15 instead of a 2 then the
numbers here would be 4 times 16 times
14 and then there'd be a 14 here and a
15 here and then it would work the same
way the trick here it's really kind of I
showed you the first case because the
first case was around before the second
case was and the real breakthrough was
really a simple idea it was just taking
the first case adding an extra prime
minus 1 instead of P minus 1 throwing a
factor of Q minus 1 and everything works
exactly the same as it did before except
now before you can solve for that D you
need to factor these numbers to get your
P minus 1 times Q minus 1 and it's that
factoring step that makes the whole
thing hard so is a clever way of taking
something that worked before that had an
easy inverse doing a teeny twist on it
and making it have a really hard inverse
and this is exactly what's used today
the numbers they choose are typically
this is what you go by in your new
browsers 128-bit encryption which means
that after you multiply these two
numbers together the two large Prime's
you get a number that's 128 bits long so
that's how many base 10 digits is that
base to its 128 bits so it's about 3
points something a 3 point something
digits for a 10 so 40 or so something
like that 40 some-odd base 10 digits so
it's a very big number and you have to
be able to factor that and I think
that's on the order of 50 years to
factor a 128-bit
that's centuries as far as anybody knows
maybe there's a good way to factor
numbers if you come up with an algorithm
that's polynomial for factoring numbers
that'd be really interesting and I got
to tell you for those people who sit
around and try to solve np-complete
problems you're a lot more likely to
find a polynomial algorithm for prime
numbers in some sense than you are to
find a polynomial algorithm for an
np-complete problem because prime
numbers aren't np-complete so maybe
there's a chance
I should say there's another reason why
you wouldn't expect a polynomial number
for prime numbers but it's a little
complicated the complement of the
problem is forget it but we'll do it in
theory of computation yeah I don't know
I don't know what's really done I don't
know what companies really do that's how
number it's using a different key to and
to encode it that's interesting oh yeah
I should actually when you when you
actually when you encrypt anything I
mean we did these examples with just a
single number are being converted to
another number
but what typically happens is you get
these kind of partial sums in a message
or your message is a is a collection of
these numbers so you encrypt the first
one and then you connect that with the
next one to give you a larger number
then you encrypt that and you connect
that encrypted one with the next one to
give you a large one you see you embed
the encryptions one in another rather
than just encrypting them I think one at
a time so if you have like like a
sequence of a hundred numbers you just
don't encrypt each number one at a time
and send them you encrypt one