talking in an office one trying to
if you listen to two mathematicians
convince the other of a new idea they've
come up with you'll hear words like do
you get what I mean you believe that
it's true do you think I have the right
idea all right that doesn't sound like
proofs right that sounds like two people
trying to convince each other of
something or trying to get an idea
across and that's how proofs begin they
begin by does it seem reasonable
does it seem plausible do you believe
that this is the right track the same
way somebody's running a novel might say
do you think this is a good idea for a
book okay but it doesn't make the novel
yet so the novel is only there once you
take your idea and you decide what
characters are going to be there and
what chapters are going to be there and
you actually start putting the
paragraphs down and you rewrite it
you're rewriting to reorganize it same
with a proof you think you think you
think you'll finally get the idea you
refine the idea you check the idea you
look for holes you plug the holes and
then you say now for sure I got the idea
then you write it up and the way you
write it up is an English class think of
the idea you want to say have a topic
sentence and step by step try to explain
in English what your idea is if it saves
you some time in the middle to use a
mathematical expression then use it now
this is a little vague so maybe I should
do an example I was going to do an
example from the homework which would
the thing I like about my problem set is
that every problem there's a lot of
different ways to do it
so if I just like go over one you're
going to think oh that's the way to do
it and I don't I don't really want to do
that but there are elegant ways of
writing proofs but they don't always
have to look the same do whatever you
think is clear whatever you think makes
sense so what's a good example of this
the one with the Adu ball should I do
one little proof of a tu ball how about
this I'll give a wrong proof of a tu
ball and and and you tell me what's
wrong with it okay here's a proof of a
GU ball you're trying to prove that you
can get more than 60 with combinations
of seven and eleven okay so I start with
61 because I'm experimenting how can I
get 61 equal to a combination of sevens
and 1100 you're trying to you have a
game where you can score seven points or
eleven points and you want to show that
some sequence of scores will get you any
score 61 and higher actually 60 or
higher as well so three 11s and how many
sevens let's check that 28 and 33 that
looks good all right fine so I did it
for 61 and now all I have to do is do it
for 62 63 and all the other infinite
number of integers and my proof is done
alright well that's a bad way to prove
it because we'd all be dead before the
proof is over we need a more general
idea and the hint here is to think
inductively now I'm actually going to
rip the guts out of this problem the
last week of class we're going to
completely analyze it from a number
theory point of view you're going to
understand the complete theorem you're
going to understand everything behind it
we're just going to take all the clothes
off of this thing but right now I just
want you to scratch at it
like it's this weird you know diamond in
the rough you found and just get some
sense about it so I said prove that this
particular example is true in the
general case it'll be any two numbers in
the general case we're going to have a
way of calculating exactly what these
two numbers are not just figuring out on
the fly but right now all we got to do
it is four seven and 11 and prove that
you can get any number bigger than 61 so
here's my phony proof by induction okay
so where's my phony proof by induction
I'll say well let's pick any number and
let X be a number greater than 61 okay
any number bigger I'm going to handle
all these cases at once now so by
induction I'm going to assume that I can
get all the all the X's lower than then
this number as combinations of seven and
eleven that will be my inductive
assumption and I want to show you that I
can get X as a combination of seven or
11 all right I'm doing this proof by
induction so I'm going to assume that
Jesus
what a noise I'm going to assume that I
can get any numbers smaller than my ex
with a combination of sevens and Elevens
well if I can get any numbers smaller
than my ex with the combinations of
seven and 11s I can certainly get X
minus seven by induction X minus seven
can be written as a times seven plus B
times eleven by induction I assumed it
because it's a smaller case everybody
agree I didn't do anything wrong so far
hence hence x equals so you talk about x
equals x equals a plus one times seven
plus B times eleven so I conclude X can
be written as a combination of 7s and
11s
and I picked any arbitrary X to start
what a simple proof right it's almost
too simple right it's too slick right my
base case is wrong it's a it's a subtle
issue here that my base case is wrong
but the point will talk about what's
going on with the base case in just a
second but look what this looks like
when I do proofs for you in class I'm
talking I'm sketching we have
interaction I rarely will sit here with
my back to the camera
writing the proof up just like I did
here this is not how I'm going to write
proofs in class if you want to see
proofs written like this go to the book
where somebody did that and then they
publish it in the book and you can read
it at your leisure it's too slow and not
useful for me to write proofs like this
all right I'm going to be talking and
filling in stuff in the board as I talk
hoping you're listening it's faster if I
talk in you're listening but this is a
nice way to write it there's nothing
fancy about this it's just you know
basic English sentences let X be a
number bigger than 61 by induction X
minus 7 can be written in this form
hence X can be written in this form
hence X can be written as a combination
of sevens and Elevens end of proof so
where did I go wrong well I didn't have
any base case so let's make a base case
so here's my base case
that's a fine base case right is that a
fine base case oh well no that's okay
that I want to show that it's true 461
and higher Doug so here's my 61 case my
base case and now here's my proof that I
can get anything bigger than 61 so
that's not a problem that's okay what
right right think about how to think
about how you get 62 if I went through
my argument I would take 7 away and
where does that end up right so there's
there's some subtlety with induction you
need a base case but you need a base
case that you sooner or later end up
back you don't want to skip over or pass
your base case otherwise this nice
little link of reasoning passes right
over the point that anchors you okay
it's like jumping and missing the
trampoline ouch
yes we didn't that's an assumption
the idea of induction is that we're not
proving the induction assumption we're
assuming it's true and we're going to
prove how to get from there to the
higher case and as long as we have a
place to start we can repeat that
argument and get all the cases so we
didn't prove this was true it's by
induction we assume it's true then we'd
be done now this this step is is valid
just because it's a smaller case than
what I started with if you're trying to
prove something by induction you can
assume for free it's like you all wrote
recursive programs for a whole month
right how do you know your recursive
programs work it's because when you call
the program again on the smaller case
you assume that ends up working right
why does that end up working for you
because sooner or later you have this
base case that bottoms it out and it
comes running up the stack right so I'm
trying to write a program to show you
that I can write X as a combination of
these two things I recursively assume
that I can write X minus 7
think of this is a recursive call I get
it for free just like you get your leap
of faith and recursion for free I'm
appealing to what you know from
programming to maybe give you a sense
about this but but this comes for free
base case for any number of the form 61
plus 7x that's true that's true so some
of the cases right so you covered some
of the cases the way you can cover all
the cases is you need 7 need a sequence
of 7 base cases so that means you can't
jump over it if you're taking away 7
you've got a land inside that big
trampoline of a base case so the size of
your base case has to change depending
on your argument there's a lot of
subtleties in induction and I gave you a
bunch of problems in about a week or two
where we talk just about induction for a
whole day and and you'll discover a lot
of these subtleties as you go along and
you'll discover them in this problem set
too this is the base case 61 this is the
inductive assumption because it's a case
that's smaller than the one I started
with probably the reason it doesn't were
making jumps of seven
yes that's exactly why it doesn't work
because in my argument if you check the
actual inductive argument is fine but
the base case isn't big enough to catch
it so as you go down by jumps of seven
you would actually pass the base case by
and and it wouldn't really work or the
way Sam looked at it this is true for
anything
that 61 plus multiples of seven and
that's that's not all the numbers that's
just some set of the numbers all right
so this was meant to be a little review
about how to write a proof and how to
ask yourself whether you've written it
if your gut instinct is oh I know it's
true but I just don't know how to
explain it then you got a long way to go
okay but if you really really know it's
true and you can't explain it to
somebody and you're able and you're
really positive you got it you can
convince somebody not the kind of
convincing you know I want you to go to
the movies with me and you want to stay
home the kind of convincing that you're
working together and you found the truth
if you've gotten to that point then just
go back to English class and write your
idea down in English and you'll nail it
down all right now the real idea of a
proof is sociological a proof in a
journal is as rigorous and strong as the
professional mathematicians who looked
at that proof and checked it and there
are many famous examples of proofs that
got passed referees into journals of
famous theorems that thirty years later
another famous paper says oh gee this
theorem was wrong there's a mistake in
the proof of this and then somebody has
to either fill up the whole or actually
maybe not fill up a whole one of the
famous examples of this is anybody here
of the four-color theorem there's that
if you have a planar graph you can color
the vertices with four different colors
so that every two adjacent vertices have
different colors or if you have a
picture of the United States you can
color it with four colors no two
adjacent states have the same color that
theorem is true was actually proved for
real in the mid 70s with the use of a
computer in a very very controversial
proof where you couldn't really verify
the proof unless you trusted the
computers calculations so it got the
philosophers talking a lot and the
mathematicians weren't really satisfied
because it wasn't much of an elegant
proof but
there was a beautiful elegant proof of
this back in the 1800s
which was in the journal for 15 years
before somebody else published a flaw in
the proof so people thought it was
proved found a flaw and the good thing
about the proof is that it still managed
to prove that you could do it with five
colors but it wasn't strong enough the
hole wasn't pluggable to make it work
for four and it remained as an open
question whether you actually could do
it with four all the time all the way up
until the mid 70s and then two guys from
University of Illinois proved it that
all right so it gives you an idea what's
a real proof it's what really is true
what's really true turn it all to logic
step by step by step so no human in the
world could conceivably figure out what
it means right that's not good enough
it's got to be a balance it's got to be
a balance between rigor and intuition
and our class has our own standard of
that humans have double-checked the
proof of the computer I don't think that
they've actually double-checked each of
the steps I don't think that's actually
been done right although although you
can write programs that check the
integrity of the program I mean it's a
really it's a philosophical issue I mean
what if that machine just had a had a
glitch here's what happens you get a
paper some editor that that that gets a
paper on a particular subject say I
published a paper on that subject before
and they say would you mind reviewing
this paper then they send you the paper
and then you spend hours and hours
depending on how sincere you are really
try to figure out what this person is
saying and sometimes it's very difficult
sometimes because they didn't write it
well sometimes because it's just
difficult material you go through it you
check if it's correct you check if it's
interesting all sorts of things but
mainly four correct and comparing it
against the current literature because
presumably the person reviewing it is an
expert and then you give an opinion this
is no good it's been done before this is
no good it's wrong this is good but it
needs to be rewritten
this is good it's pretty good as it is
this is good perfect and you give a
opinion back to the editor who then
communicates it to the to the person who
wrote it and there's usually two or
three or four depending on how serious
the journal is referees for each article
so look if you're really really busy try
to get tenure and writing your own
papers and getting your own grants and
suddenly you get this and it takes 15
hours to do this during your week and
you say oh well this semester I refereed
six papers no tenure committee cares
that you refereed six papers they'll say
they care if you're the editor they
might care but the editor does a lot of
the passing stuff back and forth and not
so much of the it let's this is just
stupid politics this is this is nothing
to do it alright let's let's do let's
get back to where we were okay I
finished up last time showing you that
you could take any boolean formula but
you can represent with the truth table
and put it in terms of ands ORS or not
so Chris Creek where is he he asks can
you do it with just ands and ORS and the
nots
can you do it with ORS and nots can you
do with ands and ORS some of you had an
idea we're doing it right on the spot I
said think about it
is there any consensus can you do it
with Ann's indoors
B how do you write a or B in terms of
hands and knots then I'll believe you
this knot not a is a flips this - or not
not B is B this is an identity you could
prove it with a truth formula you could
prove it with our manipulations because
you can convert every a or B into this
form then any place you see in or
operation in a formula you could replace
it with an x' or not so it's true and
the knots are a complete set in fact
everything is symmetric and boolean
algebra so or the knots or a complete
set and this identity is true right you
can always flip knots and oars and hands
and everything always stays true in
boolean algebra that's also search so so
so or is a knots or a complete set what
about ands and ORS what do you guess
about that you can have a hard time
getting a not gate or getting a not just
a - ands and ORS but I'll tell you a
really cool computer architecture
problem
what if somebody gives you one not gate
and all the ends and orders you want can
you simulate more than one not gate if
they give you two not gates - not
symbols you can only use two of these
two minus signs and all the ends in
orders you want can you create more not
gate so it turns out you can it's a very
difficult problem and it's really tricky
and it's a cool puzzle but it belongs in
the architecture how computers were
course not really in this course so much
anyhow moving on the method we use last
time to come up with a formula with ands
ORS and nots create something in this
kind of a form something like this
this kind of a form always comes out of
a truth table sometimes you have knots
on the variables sometimes you don't you
combine them together with an x' because
you want the whole row to have those 0
and 1 values and then you connect them
with ORS because you want either this
row or this row or that row this kind of
form is a name it's called this junk t'v
normal form the fancy name what it means
is this junk that basically means ORS
you or together collections of things
which are ANDed together right what's
more every single boolean formula has a
unique disjunctive normal form
that's some kind of a level I won't get
into too much of it but you can always
write it in this junk of normal form
there's a flip side of this instead of
taking things that are multiplied
together and adding them you can take
things that are added together and
multiply them all right so in this case
well let's not do this case well just
put any example up here this is an
example of the other kind of form this
is conjunctive normal form things
connected with ORS and then they're
multiplied together
they're duals of one another here where
you see addition there's multiplication
here where you see addition there's
multiplication back here okay so this is
conjunctive normal form this is
disjunctive normal form
they're both useful for different kinds
of things there's a problem set that
asks you to use the same method I did to
come up with this to come up with this
kind of form and that's what Sam was
saying the other day said concentrate on
the zeroes and push a double knock
through I'll let you work on it on the
problem set but you can always come up
with a conjunctive normal form and a
disjunctive normal form for any formula
right Peter no they're not the same
they're not the same these are just
showing you a conjunctive normal form
what makes the first one disjunctive is
the fact that is some love some blobs of
multiply things connected by word yes
together which are then Ord these are
things or together which are that ANDed
so just that in the first case it has to
be things that are ANDed together we're
going to have negative parenthesis with
bitter orange
defines
it's got to be things multiplied
connected by oars to be just junked of
normal form this is not things
multiplied strictly connected by oars
here's the or that's okay
but that's not okay because this is not
a single variable that's got a plus in
it so this is too complicated to be
considered in either normal form and
it's a very common thing in math to take
stuff that can look in an arbitrary way
and and use the fact that we can always
make a look at a particular way because
we can always say okay make it look in
this particular way because now my
arguments easier so the two particular
ways people generally use for boolean
formulas or cons active normal form and
disjunctive normal form and you'll see
this later because it's got to come up
on a computer science side in in 20
minutes
of that as like W times a times true
right right right exactly good Anthony
right if you distribute this out then it
would be in this junked up normal form
right you get R times R plus R times W
bar plus W and that would be disjunctive
normal form good right and you can
always do that you can always manipulate
it and get it into one of these forms
alright questions so we talked about
these complete sets of operators and an
or and the not as a complete set or not
as a complete set and the nor is not a
complete set are there any boolean
functions that are complete all on their
own and the answer is yes all right so
one example is an operator called norm
and here's the nor operator sometimes
it's written like this
same as let's fill in the chart what's
the values for the nor function
that's right let's check it
zero or zero is zero a not sign of front
turns it to one zero or 1 is 1 a not
sign in front turns it to zero that's
going to be the same what about 1 or 1
101 is going to be 1 and the not sign is
going to make it 0 right that's the nor
function it turns out that the nor
function alone can get you any other
function you want you can combine nor
things together and I'm going to prove
it to you and it's a really really
straightforward proof I'm going to prove
to you that I can get not by using nor
that I can get and by using nor and I
can get or by using nor that's true I
could based on Chris Chris's comment and
that's true
so let me show you how you get not check
this yourself if I took a variable and I
nor it with itself what happens to it if
it's 0 it ends up being 1 and if it 1 it
ends up being 0 so X nor X is the same
as not X every place you see a not X in
a formula you can replace it with X nor
X so that gets rid of all the knots in
your formula what else might happen you
might have an X or Y
through but you can do it let's try a
couple cases zero or zero should be
should be zero put zero zero zero zero
into here and see what you get zero nor
zero gives you one zero nor zero gives
you one one nor one gives you zero so it
agrees you have to check all the
possibilities to make sure that these
two are identical make a hole truth
table and double check you can also do
the and I'm going to put down the end
because it's so nicely symmetrical and
it will help you on the problem set when
I asked you to do this with a different
key that turns out to be equivalent to x
and y I here I have two x's two eyes
here I have X Y X Y it's very dual
--is-- is it right you checked it it
could be well we can check it let's
check it and here I could have made a
mistake let's check one and zero so that
means this is going to be one nor one
which is zero zero nor zero which is 1
and then 0 nor one which is zero so
that's not right right these are
backwards I got them reversed mmm
oh she shows it reverse - I wrote him
and the notes are right and this is
wrong not great you know the funny thing
about this is that when I first wrote
these notes I made the mistake in my
notes I corrected my notes I do this
lecture now I'm thinking oh crap did I
correct them incorrectly and I didn't I
corrected them corrected ly and then
copied it wrong this is correct all
right let me show you how to use this
how would you take any formula at all
and use this information let's say we
have a P or Q and not P so let's say we
want it to take this expression written
with ands ORS and nots and turn it into
something that just had Knorr in it
we're just going to work our way out
from the inside out and you could
actually write a program to do this I
didn't force you to but you can let's
turn the not first okay so P not ends up
being P nor P now I've got P or Q let's
do that
wrong way sorry I was standing on my
head for a moment we still have a NAND
gate left right or an and operation I
keep saying gates because I'm going to
do an example in circuits in a minute
how do we get rid of this we have to use
this expression but now the X is all of
this and the Y is all of this this is
ugly good but I'll do it
is equivalent to that teeny formula
there all right is it the smallest
formula with Knorr in it that's
equivalent to this no you can probably
do better okay it's just a way of
showing that you can always do it but
you can probably do better and the
issues of doing better are more
complicated but we could even start with
easier stuff true but but even with this
can definitely be reduced a lot let me
tell you something about why people care
about complete operators if you go and
think about circuits you can buy
circuits that do all these different
operations here's an and circuit or a
NAND gate two things come in one thing
comes out and electricity goes into this
little box electricity comes out zero is
a low voltage one is a high voltage to
high voltages come in high voltage comes
out anything else comes in low voltage
comes out it's just the physical analog
to what we've been talking about you
build computers out of things like this
now what's inside things like this well
it depends what decade and century
you're talking about if you go back to
2000 BC you can build these things with
streams of water running through and big
holes in the ground streams of water
running in and when somebody puts input
in they take a big rock that's one and
they cover the whole right so if you
have the stream of water with two
consecutive holes in it
then if two people cover the holes then
the stream of water will run
two ones come in two big rocks come in
the stream of water comes through right
if anybody doesn't cover their rock
their hole with their rock then the
stream of water goes down the hole and
it doesn't come out the other end so you
could build an and gate at a streams of
water and big rocks and holes in the
ground and if you built a computer the
scale of that size it would be you know
maybe the city of Cambridge and then
there's a timing issue making sure
everybody is running with the rocks and
covering things at the right time and
that's why nobody built a computer 4,000
years ago because the technologies got
to catch up with the idea all right so
if you're in that let's jump up to the
1940s all right then you get the what's
1940s vacuum tubes maybe 1950s vacuum
tubes 1960s transistors were invented
right more transistors invented 1961
somebody want us a Nobel Prize for
transistors right it's a huge invention
it's a big thing transistors basically
allowed these things to happen with much
less heat much smaller much faster and
nowadays the technology improves and
improves and improves every single year
they get better and better in how much
time it takes for electricity now to get
through a NAND gate something on the
order of a billionth of a second
nowadays a nanosecond a billion times
you can go through these gates in a
second and four thousand years ago it
took about five minutes for people to
move the rock and get through the gate
so it's it's on the order of you know 15
orders of magnitude faster today all
right which gate is actually the fastest
I didn't tell you how you build these
things you put transistors inside them
use VLSI use all sorts of electrical
engineering stuff which you don't need
to know about but inside as a black box
it does what a NAND gates supposed to do
but you should realize that if you go to
the store the fastest one of all these
gates is actually a gate called the NAND
gate which stands for naught and it
turns out that you can build this with
the minimum number of transistors and if
your time how long it takes the
electricity to get through a knot and
gate it takes the fastest so you'd love
to be able to build everything with just
these gates because then you get the
least delay through your circuit this is
real electrical engineering idea not so
much a computer science idea but it
relates
it turns out an and gate is also a
complete circuit just like an or gate is
but it turns out electrically speaking
it's a very fast one so there's a
trade-off because if you turn everything
in terms of NAND gates and then you get
a ton of NAND gates even though they're
fast what good is that so there's all
sorts of issues here theoretical issues
and engineering design issues and you'll
see it in computer architecture and how
computers work
all right questions about this it's a
knot and the same way an oar is a knot
or a NAND gate is a knot end so the so
it would be so it would be 1 1 1 0 that
would be a NAND gate there's there's 3
big applications of computer logic that
I want to talk about one has to do with
algorithms and with this idea of a
reduction one has to do with computer
architecture and the idea of building a
circuit and one has to do with AI and
the idea of fear improving all right I'm
going to try
oh jeez if you get through all of these
today which is the best one to start
with so I'm going to do circuits first
because we were talking about it and
everybody's freshly thinking about
circuits here we go we're going to talk
about how you can take stuff from an
electrical electronic catalog buy some
of these gates and build something that
does arithmetic right it's not exactly a
computer yet but at least it's getting
there Computers do a lot of arithmetic
so in order to do this we need a little
bit of a of an introduction not too much
numbers binary numbers are numbers that
are just zeros and ones and you can
represent any number in the whole world
with binary numbers quick intro with
normal numbers you go 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
9 you run out of symbols 10 right there
is no T for 10 so what do you do for 10
you put one in this column and then you
put a zero here this is so ingrained in
our heads that we never think about it
anymore right one is in the tens column
zeros in the ones column that's ten if
it's so ingrained in your head and you
get it just do the same thing for binary
numbers let's count in binary I took
away all your symbols except for zero
one when you get to one you're done zero
one you're out of symbols what do you do
now you can go one one right this is
like 99 you're out of symbols one zero
one out of symbols one one zero one one
one out of symbols again okay the
numbers get pretty long faster than they
did before but it's a perfectly fine
number system how do you add binary
numbers well the really goofy way is to
take the number convert it back to base
10 add in base 10 and then convert it
back to binary it's like what you don't
have to do that you can just add them
straight look what number 1 plus 0 is 1
1 plus 0 is 1 0 plus 1 is 1 this is the
number 3 this is the number 4 3 & 4 7
right the same arithmetic algorithm you
used to use works for binary who's still
with me easy ok
I didn't do a carrying here let's do
some carrying 1 plus 0 is 1 1 plus 1 is
carry 1 1 plus 1 is 0 carry 1 that's
also right this is the number 3 this is
the number 6 this is the number 9 ok
this is the ones column the twos column
the forest column and the eights column
instead of having a tens column and a
hundreds column and a thousandth column
going up by ten each time we go up by a
factor of two each time right yeah Brian
numbers at a time and then they had the
third one to the sum of those two and
you would never design a circuit well I
shouldn't say never but but they don't
do it that way and specifically because
of what you're implying with your
question yeah yeah diner yeah yeah I
didn't have to put it that right because
the truth is what you really do here
here's there's the next step
say you wanted to build a little machine
that does addition you have to decide
how big your numbers are so typically in
a computer nowadays the numbers are 32
zeros and ones long if you have a number
bigger than that you have to come up
with a better way to do it in fact in
scheme you see how you guys can do
arithmetic and scheme if you do 100
factorial that's way bigger than than
what the computer can store the computer
doesn't actually do arithmetic on this
circuit there it actually splits the
number up into pieces puts it in a list
reconstructs it it actually stores it in
lots of different numbers it does it in
a different way but if you want to store
just one number it's typically 32 zeros
and ones long so here's what an addition
circuit might look like 32 zeros and
ones come in here 32 zeros and ones come
in here and out comes how many zeros and
ones 33 because there could be a carry
right but if you're building a computer
where every number has 32 zeros and ones
that they go around wires you know that
are 32 in parallel like Red Rover
holding hands what do you do with a
number that comes out 33 bits it doesn't
fit on the
doesn't fit on the highway are you so
actually this extra bit has to go
someplace else so I'm going to write it
like this 32 and then one comes out here
go somewhere else and you do the
appropriate thing with it what's inside
something like this well I'm not going
to go too much into this because that's
really for next month but I will explain
to you how we can focus and build
precisely and we'll do it into the next
ten minutes a little circuit that's just
one column of this we would need 32 of
these circuits connect it together with
the carries sent to the next one on its
left and we can put all those 32 inside
here and we'd have this circuit but I'm
going to show you just how to build one
for one column of this addition we need
32 copies to really do it and what's
more just to make it easy I'm not even
going to deal with a carry I'm just
going to assume what you'll see I will
deal with a carry but I'm not going to
connect it I'm just going to show you
one column let's do it this little
circuit I'm building is called a half
adder and like any circuit or any
boolean function it can be represented
in a truth table two things come in
the other number and one thing comes out
called the result and one thing comes
out called the carry I have four
possibilities for the things that can
come in if I add zero and zero together
the result is zero and I carry zero if I
add 0 and 1 the result is 1 and I carry
if I add 1 and 0 the result is 1 and I
carry 0 and if I add 1 in 1 the result
is 0 and I carry 1 okay each of these is
a separate function I got to carry I got
the result we're going to design each of
these separately let's go ahead and
write a formula that actually gets these
one of them should scream at you because
it's just a basic one which one of these
is easier watch they're both kind of
easy but the carry is really
straightforward right what scary it's
and right so carry equals x and y okay
what about result X what X exclusive or
Y okay so we wrote exclusive or in a lot
of different ways let's write it with
just ands and ORS and nots how would we
do that
remember our trick we'd say not x and y
or X and not Y right same thing so let's
do a not x and y or X and not Y that's
exclusive or and that represents the
result
applause isn't or no symbol I was a plus
with a circle around it I had no reason
is because the only gates we have are
these ands and ORS and nots and we're
going to make a picture with ands and
ORS and nots and you'll see it in a
second so here's our circuit here it is
the way you write a circuit is you put a
little box here you put the inputs on
the top the X and the y I put little
arrows so everybody remembers what
direction things are going the
electricity is moving in a certain
direction
usually the you don't see arrows and
books you just get it from the context
but it's easier to see it there are two
things that come out of here
the result and the carry why don't I put
the carry coming out the side because
like I said you're going to have 32 of
these circuits next to each other and
this carry should probably go into the
next one so we can pass its result on
but right now let's just concentrate on
this circuit how do we do it the care is
the easy part it's just a hand gate
here's what an and gate looks like
circuit you see a black dot like I'm
trying to make here like a little that
means you just splice the little wire
off of here you just took it you sent it
over here
I sent the why over here the reason I
made those little dots is because I'm
going to have to take those X's and Y's
and send them down to another part of
the circuit in just a moment so I just
splice it off it's a straight back here
and a curved bottom that's a NAND gate
every angle like that conventionally a.d
a.d up site ID rotated yeah yeah okay by
the way sometimes it's hard to draw
these pictures without crossing lines if
the lines cross the implication is that
when you actually build the circuit you
don't let the lines cross because you'll
get a horrible short-circuit and things
won't do right so you raise them above
or below one another if you see a black
dot that means they really do connect
okay so anytime they cross without the
black dot they're not connected now we
need to do this it's a little harder the
way to do it is I just like to build it
from the bottom up so the last thing
that happens is it's or so an aura is
going to go into the result here's what
an or gate looks like
curvy top two things are going to go
into this or gate this piece and this
piece we have to construct those two
things we need not x and y so let's get
not x and y here's not X I'll pull it
down here here's a not gate there's a
little triangle with a bubble on the end
of it that's not X and here's why
comes this way they go through a NAND
gate not x and y comes down into the or
now I got to do this part X and not Y so
here's X coming into a NAND gate here's
not Y coming down from here through a
bubble and then into the or gate yes my
last questions the reason we don't use a
specific xor gate just that it's faster
to shoot it
combination answer no it's not and
actually if you went to the store and
bought an xor gate we would just have
one little gate here with an xor marked
on it it's just because you always it at
the beginning you always build circuits
showing ands and ORS or nots that's a
convention and you could do it another
way and there is no good reason yeah all
right let's look at this other questions
about how I constructed it here's what I
expect you to get out of this you should
be able to take a truth table construct
the formulas you should be able to take
the formulas and make that picture okay
working your way backwards once you see
the picture that's it you can give this
to an engineer they can build it and
it's something that does arithmetic with
electronics based on theoretical logic
from the 1880s
through this circuit if every single
gate you see takes one billionth of a
second you understand that question
computers take a certain amount of time
to run what slows them down what slows
them down is how many gates they have to
go through before something interesting
happens so let's see to get out the
carrier it only takes one billionth of a
second but here's one here's two here's
three there's a depth of three you can
think of this as a tree or as a graph
and knowing the depth of the graph is
important that's why people study graph
theory it connects and figuring out how
fast these circuits are going actually
you can see that this particular idea of
a circuit is really cruddy because how
do you really do this circuit like I
said you have another one just like it
over here right and you pass this carry
over there and that
going to take another three to get this
out and if you have 32 of these then
it's like 96 right there's no there's no
ALU there's no arithmetic logic unit
that is sold today that uses this idea
because it's just way too slow they use
better ideas and that's what you talk
about and how computers work you talk
about how to build better al use you
talk about how to build better pieces of
computer there's something else that's a
little wrong with my generalization how
would I send this carry over here when
this thing only takes two things right
I'll go back to my engineer and I go
dummkopf right I say you you do dope how
am I going to take 32 of these I need an
extra arrow coming in right so I need an
X I need a wide and I need a carry in
call this carrying out I need to carry
in what would the carryin be here right
the the one here on the right end would
always get a zero but all these would
really get something connect it yeah you
got to redo everything this circuit is
called a full adder it's not a half
adder it's different it's something that
really does something useful this is
just when you're teaching people to get
them used to the idea and then you say
oh it doesn't really work and then you
say now do a full adder alright so this
is called a half adder a full adder has
three inputs how many rows are going to
be in the table for a full adder with
three inputs eight you got all of these
you got to put a zero in front of all of
them and then you've got to put a one in
front of all of them so it doubles you
get eight it's a bigger circuit it's
more difficult alright we're not going
to do that now we're stopping here now
with circuits
said that we need to be able to produce
this diagram not this ugly one something
prettier that's because I'm about the
worst person to draw circuits I hate
doing it and I'm not good at it but I'll
show you what's going on
it comes down from here it splits this
way and it splits this way and it splits
this way splits three ways into the not
gate into this and gate into this engine
this why also splits three ways once
directly into this an gate and then down
here into this and gate and into this
not gate any place where you see a cross
and there's no big black circle then
there's no connection if there is a big
black circle then there is a connection
so there's only three black circles on
my picture one two three and all the
other crosses are really going over
under does that make better sense a
phony okay it's a good point
I should i gloss over my ugly picture
but it's right there another question
make sense all right good good by the
way I should mention it but I won't go
into the details the way computers do do
addition is just this way more or less
the way they do subtraction is also this
way they use the same circuit to do
subtraction as they do to do addition
and they use a method that you're not
used to in school because in school they
teach you to borrow when you do
subtraction and they teach you to
regroup when you do addition but you
could actually do subtraction through an
addition algorithm if they bothered to
teach you that it that way and it turns
out that that way is much more natural
for machines what machines do when they
do subtraction is they switch all the
zeros to ones and all the ones to zero
and they have this carry-in ends up
being a one for subtraction and it turns
out to be the exact same circuit will do
subtraction that used to do addition and
there's some that would take you about
15 minutes to really understand
if I had time to do it now but you'll
see it in how computers work and the
idea is to represent numbers in what's
called two's complement form sometimes
special ed teachers use this for kids
who have real trouble figuring out
subtraction somehow but we're really
good at addition and they just say well
here just learn how to do the complement
idea and then you can just do addition
again and maybe it works maybe it
doesn't but something for education
people to think about in the notes I did
another example of a circuit which I'm
going to which I'm going to beg off now
you can look at it in the notes I did an
example of what's called a threshold
circuit some people who do a to do a
neuroscience or who do a I like to try
to represent what brains do some do it
in a way that represents the the output
of a brain like writing a program that
plays really good chess even though what
they do inside is nothing like the way
chess players do things some like to go
right to the heart of things and let's
just represent neurons and see what
happens so more or less the way neurons
work is that they get things firing into
them and every neuron has a different
threshold and when it gets a certain
number of things that fire it in it
fires something out and that completely
simple idea somehow makes us have
consciousness and various other
incredibly high level and nobody knows
has any idea how it works I mean it's I
know a little bit but not all that much
about how the brain works so one cool
thing to do is experiment we can build
circuits that act like that we can build
a circuit that has three inputs and that
fires anytime it gets two or more in in
things can look at a circuit I did it
right here on the paper you can build a
circuit that has ten inputs and it fires
every time seven or more come in and you
can connect these up and let them run in
a lab and see if they do anything clever
well you can't kind of program these
things to do things that are clever like
one thing that humans can do that that
computers can't do very well that you
all can do is distinguish faces right I
mean I can tell 98% of the time glancing
at somebody whether they're a man or a
woman
even my three-year-old can usually do
that it's a very complicated skill try
to build a machine to do that the
machine can get fooled so easily build a
machine to do it and just put somebody
with long hair in front of the machine
and they'll probably mess
if you actually take out like like you
guys did it's beginning in a semester
like shave your hair off forget it
and what about actually recognizing the
same person you know so so you put EJ in
front of the Machine and you say this is
EJ in August and now here's EJ in
October and and the machine's supposed
to know that's EJ instead of somebody
else the machine is a hard time doing
this but actually if you build like a
neural net and you let the thing run and
run and run and run you can kind of
train it to recognize patterns and
sometimes it works sometimes it
sometimes it doesn't one of the main
things you do at algorithm is is
something called a reduction it's a way
of transferring the difficulty of one
problem to another that you're more
familiar with the the best way that you
can understand the idea of reduction is
from the silly joke that I found from
the funny book of jokes and riddles a
children's book I even gave you the ISBN
so you can order it off amazon.com the
question is why what do you feed a blue
elephant for breakfast answer blue
elephant toasties question what do you
feed a pink elephant for breakfast
answer you tell the pink elephant not to
breathe until he turns blue then you
feed in blue elephant toasties
so I'm reading this book with my kids
that I go well that's great that's just
what a reduction is the idea is you know
how to solve one problem so instead of
solving another problem you fix it a
little bit you do something simple to it
so it looks like a problem that you know
how to solve and then you just use what
you know how to do so it seems when I
tell you it that way that reductions are
used to solve problems to make them
easier and that can be the case but
reductions are also sometimes used to
show that a problem is difficult all
right so let me show you what I mean
let's say I have a problem a here's a
symbol this means reduces - I'll show
you why I use the less than or equal
symbol let's say I have a problem and I
reduced it to B in this problem the pink
elephant problem is reduced to the blue
elephant problem okay so that means if I
can solve the blue elephant problem I
can solve the pink elephant problem all
right so we would say
that this problem the pink elephant
problem therefore is no harder or less
than or equal than the blue elephant
problem okay it's no worse all right
show things become easier you can also
show things become harder so I want to
do two real-life examples here's a
problem called satisfiability it's a
problem that comes right from logic I'm
going to give you an example of
satisfiability and explain to you the
problem somebody gives you a boolean
formula it's in conjunctive normal form
it looks something like this
of these are ANDed together I write them
one under the other so I don't have to
go lengthwise this is conjunctive normal
form and of ORS you're given a formula
like this and you're asked can you come
up with true and false values for the
variables X Y Z W and V to make this
whole formula true in this example the
answer is easy can you do it or not it's
easy to do it X can be true W can be
true V can be true I don't give a hoot
about Y or the other ones it's really
easy to make this trip this has to be
true this has to be true and this has to
be true so make one of these true make
one of these true make one of those true
you can't always do this I could have
made the dependencies more complicated I
could have not introduced so many
variables the question that we're
dealing with is given a formula like
this is there a way to assign true and
false values to the variables to make
the formula true or is there no way okay
that's the question
let's try to solve this problem and see
what our algorithm is and then I'll talk
about reductions
alright let's really solve the problem I
give it you for a homework and scheme
how would you solve it Hey well let's
assume for a second in this case we've
got how many variables here X Y what
else Z
w B and here I put my formula
have every time I add a variable a
double the rows right so with two
variables I got four three variables
eight for ground rule 16 five variables
32 32 rows right how do I decide if this
formula is going to be true I have to
decide it's a lot of possibilities here
right how many possibilities are there
if one of them works I say yes the
formula can be true if none of them work
I say no it can't be
well that's fine 32 I could write a
program to do that it wouldn't take that
long after all the computer does
billions of things a second so that's
fine what if I do another problem but
this problem has 200 variables in it
right how many steps is it going to take
on the order of 2 to the 200 and that
doesn't include the time it takes to
actually take these true or false
variables and put them into here I mean
that takes some amount of time let's
call the length of this formula M and
the number of variables n then the
amount of time this takes is 2 to the N
the number 2 to the number of variables
times as much time as it takes to run
through here and put the true and false
is it times M alright the times M
doesn't really kill it so bad but the 2
to the N is depth 2 to the 200 is a huge
number take centuries to run that way
way too big so this algorithm right
right right in the arse digit away
this algorithm sucks right we're not
afraid to use the word it really does
suck this algorithm is no good it's a
bad algorithm it's too slow it's
exponential you would never implement it
it would never work not in anything
reasonable right so you need something
better so you get your best programming
team and you send them you know to work
and get a better way of doing this this
is too slow and they work and work and
work and work and they can't come up
with anything better and they sit down
and they say boss we tried for four
months so we can't come up with anything
better and you yell at them and you say
try again
so finally somebody comes back and says
I proved I can't do it any better nobody
in the world ever can and you go WOW
show me the proof and wouldn't that be
cool if they could prove that how would
you prove that you'd have to prove that
any algorithm that they tried would
never be better than two to the end how
do you quantify over the infinite number
of possible algorithms well there are
kind of places in theory of computation
where you can do this but for the most
part that is hard to do
nobody has any proof that you can't do
better this is a completely open
question whether you can do better or
not maybe you can maybe it can't but say
the top 10,000 people in the last 50
years have worked on this problem and
I've come up with nothing you kind of
figure that unless you're a complete
egomaniac you're not going to come up
with something that 10,000 people who
are probably as smart as you have worked
on for hours and hours and hours it's
probably too hard it doesn't mean it's
impossible and you might come up with it
otherwise Andrew Wiles wouldn't have
proof for miles Last Theorem right I
mean it was open for 500 years
somebody's got to do it but here
nobody's done it and everybody thinks
it's impossible all right well so what
that's not good enough there's this
notion of a problem being np-complete
and that's what we can use to get a
handle on showing something's hard
intuitively here's what it means for a
problem to be np-complete
it doesn't mean boss I know this can't
be done I proved it it means boss I
can't do this but anybody who's worked
on any of these other 900 famous open
problems can't do this either right it's
not just saying that the few people who
have worked on this problem can't do it
it's saying I connected my problem to
show that it is at least as hard as
thousands of other problems that also
remain exponential at best so your boss
has got to listen to that and say ok you
know that's half the world who's worked
on those problems and they've never made
any progress so I guess you probably
won't either intuitively that's what it
means for a problem to be np-complete
it means it's at least as hard as all
these other problems that nobody knows
and X anything better than an
exponential algorithm for now I'm going
to give you a little more specifics on
that intuition but carry that intuition
with you because it will help so the
difference between Mt
is only that the np-complete has been
shown to be these other problems
equivalent are worse
well actually equivalent yes yeah so let
me tell you what that means I didn't
tell you what NP is at all but I'll tell
you in a second yep you can find it X
and not Y not C it doesn't work then you
can rule out all the other those four
possibilities all ones there's a lot of
things like that you can try to do but
none of them work in general to get the
algorithms complexity down you're right
Seth you're right and in this particular
example there's lots of particular
things you can notice and there may be
and this is really maybe what you're
getting at maybe there's special cases
of this problem that you could solve
fast right maybe the general case is
tough but a special case might be easier
right okay well I gave you a very
specific case here where there's three
in every single we call these clauses
three variables in every single clause
the general problem actually has an
unlimited number of variables in each
clause maybe if there's three in each
clause it's easy maybe it's simpler
maybe it's not hmm
well you're always adding them together
that's how it's given to you so that's
okay you get that for free all right
before I explain to you this reduction I
want to explain to you a little bit
about what an np-complete problem is
Applause
little dot is a star and the universe of
problems representing a particular
problem satisfiability is out here
sorting numbers is in here P represents
the collection of problems that you can
solve with a polynomial time algorithm
and an algorithm an N squared algorithm
and n cubed algorithm sorting is n log n
so it's inside here these are the fast
algorithms the ones we can do on a
computer and not have the computer blow
up algorithms out here and this is a
very particular definition and we'll see
this a lot more in algorithms course but
get it here today NP does not mean not
polynomial it means non-deterministic
polynomial and intuitively here's what
that means if you have a problem and
somebody gives you a guess at the answer
in this case the guess would be a
particular set of true/false values a
particular zero and one sequence if you
can verify whether that guess works or
not in polynomial time then you've got a
non-deterministic polynomial time
algorithm what non-determinism lets you
do is do things in parallel when the
possibilities are all Ord together
there's 32 possibilities here I'll have
you all work on them about 32 people
here in parallel each of you will do one
at a time if anyone of you says yes it
works then I know the answers yes that
kind of algorithm is called a
non-deterministic algorithm and its
measured in the time that one of you
takes not the sum of you take but one of
you you get to do it in parallel it
speeds up algorithms like crazy and if
you're thinking well what kind of
ridiculous algorithm is that you can't
do that on a computer you're right you
can't they're not practical they're just
a way of thinking about algorithms that
seem to speed them up
cannot proficient at the algorithm well
and anything that you can do anything
that's NP is also going to be anything
that's NP could be converted to a poly
note could could be converted to a
real-life algorithm but it would expand
like crazy if I actually calculated how
many steps this took each of you takes
just M steps to calculate whether your
formula works but there's 2 to the N of
you working so if I actually turn it
into a real-life algorithm it would
explode into the exponential time
algorithm we thought of at the beginning
so non-deterministic polynomial means
that you get a lot for free you only
have to measure how much time it takes
you to handle one guess at the solution
if that's polynomial time the time it
takes to guess one to check one guess
then we say it's an NP so almost any
algorithm you can think of ends up being
NP there are some that aren't even NP
but it's kind of easy to come up with an
NP algorithm okay I'll give you an
example the the Traveling Salesman
problem you have a graph and distances
between cities you want to go through
all the cities and get the minimum
distance okay so you want to check
whether that numbers say is less than
some particular value say less than a
thousand I can just give you a list of
cities you run along the cities adding
up the numbers you check if it's less
than a thousand you're done but if I
want to check the real minimum I've got
to do this a lot of times an exponential
number of times non-determinism
says you can avoid doing it all those
times just do it once and count how many
how many steps it takes to do it once
yeah that if you guess and you figured
it out you would know the way you
normally proposed the Traveling it's a
good question because the way you
normally present the Traveling Salesman
problem is with a graph edges on the
graph and a number and the question is
can you get a path less than that number
so you have to be able to take every
problem and turn it to yes or no it's a
very good question
but it's a technicality I kind of want
to just answer quick and move on right
so there's a lot of algorithms out here
NP
we don't know if they can go down here
in the inner universe like
satisfiability an np-complete problem is
a problem that all the other problems in
NP reduce to it okay that means it's
harder or at least as hard as all the
other problems so if you could take
satisfiability and find out that it was
really inside here if you took your blue
elephant and put it in here it would
pull the pink elephant in with it
there are hundreds and thousands of
problems out here that nobody knows how
to get them in here
they're big open questions if you can
show that one of those problems is
np-complete then if you were able to get
it inside here then all the other
problems would come in with it right and
that's the power of showing something's
np-complete it shows you that it's
really unlikely you're ever going to get
something good alright so now I need to
show you what a reduction is Seth asked
the question whether it's easier to do
this one you know because it's ANDed
together or maybe because there's three
variables in one clause and then I
entertain the question is it easier
because there's only three in everyone
the general problem has many possible
variables in each one I'm going to
convince you right now that having three
and every one is no easier and I'm going
to do it by reducing the general problem
to one where there's only three in every
single one and what I mean by that is
this you have a general problem of
satisfiability as many variables as you
want per Clause doesn't matter how long
they are I'm going to show you how to
transform that problem into one where
there's three for every Clause and the
answer to my transform problem is going
to be the same as the answer to your
problem in the original there can be as
met enou there can be as many classes as
you want and the three variables per
clause in the original there can be many
causes and and as many variables and in
my transform version there will be three
variables per clause and as many causes
as I want in the general version
every clause of the same number very no
different numbers different numbers
right and I'm going to convince you that
having those different numbers is not
what makes the problem hard I'm going to
show you that I could very easily take
any of these general instances of this
problem convert it to one that looks
just like this and then the answer to
this would be the same as the answer to
the original therefore what if I came up
with a fast algorithm for this three
variable one what if Seth went home and
said had got one and he came in tomorrow
then what could I do
I could solve the general one I take my
general one I do this quick little
reduction to this kind of case and I
throw it into the Seth's algorithm and
Seth would have solved satisfiability
and since we know satisfiability is
np-complete the chance of Seth going
home and solving the three variable one
is pretty unlikely alright not cuz he
said steph has a chance after but he
gets an extra point yeah so I need to
convince you I can do this reduction
everyone understand what I'm trying to
do by the way if this reduction turned
out to be exponential time if the
transformation was a long process then
it's not worth squat right because if I
took a long process of transforming the
hard problem to this problem and Seth
came up with an easy and easy solution
to this I still don't have an easy
solution for my original because I've
got an exponential blow-up in the
transformation so to do a reduction
right you have to make sure that the
reduction is done in a time which is
negligible relative to what you're
trying to to to prove as impossible in
other words the reduction should be done
in polynomial time it should be an easy
reduction a simple change not a
complicated one yeah
oh good because then I'll show you in
five minutes that if there's two terms
you can do it in polynomial time
is what theoreticians do they nail every
problem down they rip it apart they take
every single parameter they can they go
right down to the border figure out
which cases are hard which cases are
easy so that people who actually have to
do engineering know don't work on this
but this you can do so in the case of
this problem
how many variables per Clause is a great
parameter focus on if there's two
variables per Clause you can do it fast
if there's three variables or more per
clause you're dead all right
there's other kinds of special cases for
problems for graph problems you can talk
about planar graphs you can talk about
trees a lot of times the problems are
easier on trees that means there's no
cycles so these are all kinds of special
parameters you can look at but let's go
ahead let's do this reduction now right
so here if I have a general
satisfiability instance there can be one
variable in it or two variables or three
variables or four variables or more okay
I'm going to show you how to transform
any instance step-by-step into one that
has three in every spot so the easiest
thing is that if it has three variables
just copy it over that's easy
what if it has one variable say it has
the variable X I have to tell you show
you how to transform this X here's how I
transform it X plus a plus B X plus a
bar plus B X plus a plus B bar X plus a
bar plus B bar where all these are
multiplied by one another I can ask you
on an exam if I felt like it
this formula is true how would you prove
that
give me a method how you'd prove that
how would you prove that this is going
to be true if and only if that's true
you do a truth table right not so bad
there'd be eight rows here one row here
if X is true then for sure these are all
true right if X is false is there any
way to get all of these true if X is
false notice I have every combination of
a and B one of them is going to be false
false no matter what the values of true
and false are for a B if I have every
combination of them one of them is going
to be false false that false false will
connect with the false X and it will
make the whole formula here false
because these are all ANDed together
that's my quick proof but you can do it
either in English like I just did you
can do it in a truth table these two are
equivalent and that's my transformation
for a single variable in two things with
three can I go backwards oh you can
definitely do boolean algebra and
distribute this all out and get ax
absolutely you could do that you could
do it good question
EJ no there's nothing wrong with saying
that that's perfectly fine there's even
a law that says you can repeat yeah
that's fine we're doing this because I
want to show you how to take a general
formula and turn it into one that has
three variables for every clause and I'm
starting by dealing with the ones that
have one per clause and now I'm going to
do the ones that have two per clause say
y&z what this would have four clauses
right I'm going to increase the number
of clauses but only by a constant factor
you know maybe a multiple of four six or
something I don't know any way to do it
no I don't think you can how do we
convert y&z same idea maybe someone can
think of it I'll give you a hint there's
only two clauses that we need here
to be a different variable so let's call
it C good idea so same idea here if Y or
Z is true then both of these are going
to be true but if y&z if Y or Z is false
then one of them has to be false right
just work or not what do you think yeah
you can prove it it's okay
these will have to be false to so you'll
get all three false
all right now if I have three you know I
just copy it that's the easy part
so now I have to deal with four five six
seven eight and I'm going to do this in
general I'm going to do it with an
example of five but my example will be
completely general and you can convert
anything that was bigger than three with
this example so I'll do an example with
five u plus V plus W plus X plus y plus
Z I take a back I'm doing it with six
how do we convert something with a lot
of things here is an idea that's going
to build into the last application that
I won't have time to do today here's an
idea that builds it on theorem proving
then we have a linking variable
something new called D we continue with
the inverse of that linking variable we
add on the next variable W and we add a
new linking variable okay what with the
next term B just following the pattern
not E good X F then not F
can just throw them in de F are all new
linking variables if you do this you can
also prove that these four are
equivalent to this statement by an
English argument by truth tables by
manipulation of it algebraically you can
do it you can prove these so now I've
given you a method that takes any
combination of these and creates a new
combination of these if there is a true
and false assignment that makes this
true it's also going to make this true
because each of these are if and only if
and vice versa if there's a true and
false assignment that makes this true it
will make this true so these problems
are identical if I solve this one I've
got a solution for my original and this
is a reduction that takes how much time
you can write a program to do this what
doesn't take so much time it takes time
proportional to the number of variables
in the clauses total you just run along
you just could or down these lists it's
not so long to do this it's not
exponential time it's polynomial time I
just look at every variable once but now
I know that that's not going to come in
tomorrow give me a solution for this
kind of problem because if he did I have
had a solution for the original and I
know somebody proved in the early 70s
that the original is np-complete that
every problem in NP reduces to it
nobody's going to get an algorithm for
the original I should say that if you go
look at slash dot now there is some guy
that's got an algorithm for an
np-complete problem that he thinks might
run in polynomial time and there's all
sorts of hype about it because that
would imply that P and NP are the same
but nobody thinks they're the same and
there's almost certainly a flaw in the
person's paper the question is how
subtle is the flaw and when the flaw is
found whether there's anything left to
the paper whether there's still
something interesting there and if there
is then it's the worthwhile and if it's
just the crank kind of thing then move
on to something else but I'm I would
wager a lot of money that it doesn't
really work okay questions about this
all right so we know this is hard that
satisfiability
with three variables per Clause is now
hard we showed that regular
satisfiability reduces to three
satisfiability and I love this symbol
because it reminds you what it means it
means regular satisfiability is no
harder is less than or equal to three
satisfiability three satisfiability is
just as hard if you can solve this you
can solve this so reducing goes in this
direction we started with this one we
reduced to that one less than or equal
sign in between yes just semantics like
the regular SAT should be slightly
harder because we do have a conversion
so I don't see how we can say this less
than or equal to well it's actually the
equal to that lets us say that the fact
is that they're really equivalent
because if you could because you can
reduce it in the other direction too so
they're equivalent for the purposes of
of whether they're polynomial time
algorithms exist they're not equivalent
for the purposes of the details of the
constants oh you're right Doug I mean if
you actually measure this this obviously
seems harder than this right I mean it's
a tougher problem but as far as
polynomial time algorithms go this is as
hard or worse right it's a good point
you raise all right so if you have a
really hard problem and you reduce it to
another problem what happens to that
problem is it hard or easy you take a
hard problem and you reduce it to a new
problem that's also hard right how do I
show that a problem is easy oh I got it
I got to do it in the backwards way if I
took 3sat and I reduced it to something
like sorting right then it would show
3sat was was easy so if you want to show
problems easy then you have to reduce it
to something that you know is easy if
you want to show a problem is hard you
have to find a problem that's hard and
reduce that problem to your problem
you can use reductions in both
directions depending on whether you want
to show something's hard or easy if you
want to show this as hard reduce a hard
problem to it if you want to show
something's easy
reduce it to something else that you
know is easy easy to get ranked isn't
that technically show that it's easier
is that problem no if you did something
easy to it it it wouldn't show anything
no that's a reduction you can if you
reduced to in fact I can reduce to
satisfiability
to satisfiability I can do that it's a
trivial reduction don't do anything to
it right but that doesn't say anything
this would still be an easy problem okay
but I'm going to reduce to
satisfiability to another problem to
basically finding you might remember
this from two months ago finally finding
strongly connected components in a graph
were doing linear algebra I tried to
connect matrices to the idea of a graph
and remember we took a matrix and
multiplied by itself a lot of times and
I said this gives you the strongly
connected components those were the
pieces where every vertex could connect
to every other one so these three they
could connect to one another and these
four could connect to one another and
you want to divide the graph into which
strongly connected components and we did
an algorithm and it turned out to be not
so efficient like N cubed or something
and I mentioned at the time that there's
a really cool algorithm that you learn
in the algorithms course that does this
in time proportional to the number of
edges in the graph a very fast algorithm
that uses a technique called depth-first
search it's a really cool algorithm it
is not obvious at all how it works I
will not explain to you the actual
details of the algorithm but I will tell
you that it exists that you'll see it in
algorithms and what I'm going to do
today in the next ten minutes is show
you how to take two satisfiability turn
it into a graph so that if I could find
the strongly connected components in
that graph I could solve two
satisfiability I'm going to reduce to
satisfiability to this graph problem
which you have to take my word for it
now we can really solve very efficiently
okay even the unification
even the inefficient algorithm is
polynomial anyway right right Chris
everybody got my plan I think this is
enough of an example here's a - static
viability instance a particular example
of a - satisfiability problem just
before we do the reduction what's the
answer to this by the way you can
probably just do it in your head can you
satisfy this or not well if X is true it
makes these to true and then if Y if Y
is false so Y naught is true you get
these to true so you can do it right I
can make X true but that's okay but
these are ORS right so so actually
there's a lot of flexibility I can solve
this the answer is yes to this question
but that's not what we're interested in
we're interested in transforming it to
another problem where the answer to that
other problem implies the answer to this
problem I'm just pointing out that the
answer happens to be yes but we do not
need to know that in doing a reduction
in fact in general when you're doing
these reductions from satisfiability to
three satisfy you better not know the
answer when you're doing the reduction
the answer is hard to do the reduction
is easy to do
you shouldn't have to figure out the
answer in during your reduction you want
to do the reduction completely oblivious
of the answer that's the whole idea of a
reduction you want to connect one
problem to another so I want you to
focus on that connection and not the
fact that you happen to be able to solve
this particular one all right so what is
the connection going to look like here's
what we're going to do I'm going to make
a graph where the vertices are going to
be the variables here I'm going to have
a vertex for every variable and a vertex
for every knot of every variable so here
I'll make a picture of this here is X
here's X bar here's Y here's Y bar
but also I don't have Z what do I got W
and V is that it I have 4x and X bar are
different variables yes sorry oh I don't
have a straight wire but I'm going to
include Y in there anyway
and it might just end up being
disconnected so if it does it won't
matter
okay so that's the first step again
imagine you wrote a computer to do this
no big deal right just look at the
variables count them off create little
circles you got a set of vertices now
now how do you make the edges here's the
tricky part and I'm not really
motivating this I'm giving you the
answer I mean to motivate it I need more
than this ten minutes so I'm just going
to show you how to do it here's what you
do for every one of these clauses say X
Y bar you're going to make two edges in
the graph you're going to take the knot
of the first one and make a directed
edge to the second one so you're going
to take not X and make a directed edge
two to the second one to not Y okay and
now vice versa you're going to take not
of the second one and make a directed
edge to the first one so that would make
a directed edge from from Y to X okay
that's the mechanical procedure there
was a reason behind this I'll try to get
to it in a minute but let's just get the
mechanical procedure down I'll try to
motivate how anybody thinks of these
things when you're first see reductions
your first sentence is God I'm busting
my head just to figure out how this
works figuring it out I'm from scratch
on my own just seems impossible and well
it is impossible for the first few times
but if you get led up to a bit by bit it
gets easier and the good news is that
you're not going to do reductions in
discrete math if you're going to do
reductions in algorithms so you got a
few months to worry about this
words also also forward and backwards
nodding one variable making an arrow to
the other
you got it Chris perfect okay so tell me
how to do this one not be 2x and not X
to be good once you do the next one
Shawn can you do the next one you get
the idea you want to take not of one
variable and make an arrow to the other
variable so what do I get not W - not Y
and then Y - 2 W you not one variable
and you make an arrow to the other
variable so not of this variable gives
you Y and an arrow to the other variable
gives you Y goes to W okay I want you to
the last one who's got it
Erica X - not Y good and why - not X
good Wow okay there it is there's my
graph
alright so Tony did I need to have the y
in there even though it didn't appear in
any of the clauses I needed to have it
still right because it connects up to
the graph right so but now you can see
that clearly I think alright if you get
a variable and you see it repeat again
with a not the answer is you cannot
satisfy this if you don't get anything
repeated in any strongly connected
component the answer is you can satisfy
it now before we check this there better
since we know this is satisfiable this
better not have any X and X bar or Y and
Y bar in any connected component and I
don't think it has in the same connected
component I don't think so in those days
and it goes to what go where Y goes yes
but Y bar can't get back to why that's
not the same strongly connected
component a strongly connected component
is a piece where everything can get to
one another
what a strongly connected component
going to you know it a variable
anticipation
oh there isn't one here but here what if
it look like this if there was a
strongly connected component in the
graph like this and the answer would be
no you can't do it let me try to
convince you for two minutes why the
answer white why this makes sense
this reaction really does work it's true
and it proves that too sad is easy as
long as you know that this is true from
algorithms all of computer science is
one big graded bundling thing you got to
know everything and then how do you know
that this connection is works well
here's the idea every set of parentheses
has to be as if history is so that if
the first part is no the second is good
so good idea if X is true do you know
anything about this could be anything if
X is false if X is false what do you
know about the Y bar Y bar has got to be
true if you have any chance to solve it
y bar has got to be true but if Y bar
has got to be true then look at all the
things with Y bar in that woven all the
things with Y in them because that would
be making the true into a false the idea
is you want to follow these implications
through and when there's only two things
in each clause these implications end up
giving you a graph let me show you if X
is false what does that imply about Y
bar the fact that Y bar is true does
that imply anything about any of the
other clauses not a not a darn thing
there's no arrows coming out of Y bar
because Y doesn't appear in any of the
other clauses for this one because Y bar
being true doesn't tell you anything
about W you'd have to have Y being true
to Y being false to tell you something
about W okay so let's go on to a
different example what about if V is
false then X has to be true so let's do
it
the
is false sorry V is false that means V
bar is true X is true if X is true that
means Y bar is false what these arrows
represent is a chain of implications of
if this is true then this guy has to be
a certain way and if this is true then
this guy's got to be a certain way so if
you get a cycle where X goes in a long
chain of reasoning back to X bar that
means if X bar is true then X is true
and if X is true X bar is true and that
can't be so that's a contradiction so
the answer is you cannot solve the two
set formula if any strongly connected
component has an X and X bar in it you
can otherwise and how do you do it
otherwise you just start here pick a
true or false
and you'll dead end without getting a
contradiction and you can just arrange
the true and false as as you go and if I
had a little more time I know I could
get this into everybody's head to make
sure you get it but I really rushed it
and and if you're feeling a little bit
overwhelmed with it it's understandable
this reduction is not obvious but study
it for a little bit to get a good sense
of reduction it's a great example for
reduction all right I'm going to quit
now I still have to do the resolution